<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  AppStream metainfo for Ants Terminal.

  Consumed by GNOME Software, KDE Discover, and distro appstream catalogues
  (Debian DEP-11, Fedora AppStream, openSUSE OBS, Arch pacman-contrib).
  The `id` matches the `.desktop` filename stem (reverse-DNS) so that
  `launchable` can tie the two together.

  Validate with:
    appstreamcli validate packaging/linux/org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml
    desktop-file-validate packaging/linux/org.ants.Terminal.desktop

  When cutting a release, add a new <release/> entry at the top of the
  <releases/> list (newest first) with version/date and a short summary
  of user-visible changes — distros surface this in the update-details UI.

  TODO(screenshots): add a <screenshots/> block once we commit real UI
  captures under docs/screenshots/. Current omission produces a validator
  warning (informational), not an error; GNOME Software falls back to the
  app icon for the store tile until screenshots land.
-->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>org.ants.Terminal</id>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.ants.Terminal.desktop</launchable>

  <name>Ants Terminal</name>
  <summary>Modern, themeable terminal emulator with GPU rendering and plugins</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>

  <developer id="org.ants">
    <name>Ants Terminal Contributors</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Ants Terminal is a fast, feature-rich terminal emulator written from
      scratch in C++20 with Qt6. It targets the capabilities modern
      terminal users expect — true-color themes, ligatures, hyperlinks,
      inline images, and a scriptable plugin system — without dragging
      in a web runtime.
    </p>
    <p>Key features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Eleven built-in themes with full ANSI palette overrides, plus automatic dark/light switching that follows the system color scheme.</li>
      <li>Optional OpenGL glyph-atlas renderer for GPU-accelerated draws; QPainter path with ligature-aware text shaping (HarfBuzz) remains the default.</li>
      <li>Inline images via Sixel, Kitty graphics protocol, and iTerm2 OSC 1337. Image paste auto-saves to disk — optimized for LLM / coding-agent workflows.</li>
      <li>Shell integration via OSC 133 (prompt jump, exit-status marks). OSC 8 hyperlinks, OSC 52 clipboard, OSC 9/777 desktop notifications, OSC 9;4 progress reporting.</li>
      <li>Kitty keyboard protocol with progressive enhancement, synchronized output, SGR mouse reporting, focus reporting.</li>
      <li>Embedded Lua 5.4 plugin system (sandboxed) with documented <code>ants.*</code> API. Session persistence saves scrollback across restarts.</li>
      <li>Built-in Project Audit panel: clazy + cppcheck + semgrep + regex rules with SARIF v2.1.0 export, AI-assisted triage, and confidence scoring.</li>
      <li>Configurable keybindings, command snippets, auto-profile rules, SSH bookmarks, and an OpenAI-compatible AI assistant dialog.</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <categories>
    <category>System</category>
    <category>TerminalEmulator</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>terminal</keyword>
    <keyword>console</keyword>
    <keyword>shell</keyword>
    <keyword>bash</keyword>
    <keyword>emulator</keyword>
    <keyword>tty</keyword>
    <keyword>command</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal</url>
  <url type="help">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/blob/main/README.md</url>
  <url type="contribute">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md</url>

  <provides>
    <binary>ants-terminal</binary>
  </provides>

  <supports>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>pointing</control>
  </supports>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <releases>
    <release version="0.6.34" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Decouples PTY read and VT parsing from the Qt GUI thread. Previously, every byte of terminal output traversed the GUI thread through <code>QSocketNotifier → Pty::dataReceived → VtParser::feed → TerminalGrid::processAction</code> and then on to paint — so heavy streams (<code>find /</code>, <code>cat biglog</code>) blocked scroll and repaint. As of 0.6.34 read + parse run on a dedicated worker <code>QThread</code> (<code>VtStream</code>); only batched <code>VtAction</code> streams cross back to GUI for grid application and paint. Ships the first 0.7.0 performance item early since the architectural change landed clean with three feature-conformance tests locking the invariants.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>VtStream</code> worker wrapper (<code>src/vtstream.{h,cpp}</code>) — owns <code>Pty</code> and <code>VtParser</code> on a dedicated QThread, accumulates parser output into <code>VtBatch</code> and ships it to GUI over <code>Qt::QueuedConnection</code>. Grid and paint path stay on GUI so the refactor surface stays small.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> back-pressure — worker buffers up to 8 batches (~128 KB of unprocessed PTY bytes) before disabling its read notifier so the kernel applies flow control to the child; GUI re-enables reads on drain. Replaces "let RAM grow unbounded while GUI catches up" with kernel-natural flow control.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>Pty::setReadEnabled(bool)</code> for the back-pressure path. <code>Pty::write</code> and <code>Pty::resize</code> are now slots so they can be invoked cross-thread via <code>QMetaObject::invokeMethod</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> three feature-conformance tests under <code>tests/features/</code> — <code>threaded_parse_equivalence</code> (11 fixtures × 6 chunking strategies, pins action-stream identity), <code>threaded_response_ordering</code> (DA1/CPR/DA2/mode-996/DSR-OK order across 3 feed strategies), and <code>threaded_resize_synchronous</code> (source-level contract that <code>invokeMethod</code> uses <code>Qt::BlockingQueuedConnection</code>).</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> all PTY-write call sites in <code>TerminalWidget</code> route through a new <code>ptyWrite()</code> helper — keystrokes, bracketed paste, Kitty kbd protocol, response callbacks, snippets, scratchpad. The helper branches on worker-active vs. legacy path; correctness is centralised.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> resize path uses <code>Qt::BlockingQueuedConnection</code> so the PTY winsize is updated before <code>resizeEvent</code> returns — no 1-frame flicker at the new grid size with old PTY dims.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> session logging and asciicast timestamps are now sampled on the worker at batch-flush time rather than on GUI at onPtyData time; asciicast recordings are more accurate under paint load. Log write granularity is per-batch rather than per-PTY-read (coarser but still monotonic).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Kill switch: set <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> in the environment to force the legacy single-threaded path while the new code proves itself. It will be removed in a follow-up release once no regressions surface.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.33" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Nine long-standing user-reported bugs around the status bar, scrollback integrity, session restore, and the Review Changes dialog — fixed in one pass. The quiet centerpiece is the root-cause diagnosis of the long tail of "Review Changes button does nothing" reports: a 0.6.26-era <code>focusChanged</code> lambda was firing a <code>singleShot(0)</code> refocus <em>between</em> a button's mousePress and mouseRelease, ripping focus off the button mid-click and silently cancelling the <code>clicked()</code> signal. Also retires the <code>ElidedLabel</code> + stylesheet-chip-padding class of bug by converting every fixed-width status-bar chip to plain <code>QLabel</code> / <code>QPushButton</code> with <code>QSizePolicy::Fixed</code>.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> one-click "Install Claude Code status-bar hooks" action in Settings &gt; General — writes <code>~/.config/ants-terminal/hooks/claude-forward.sh</code> and idempotently merges PreToolUse / PostToolUse / Stop / PreCompact / SessionStart entries into <code>~/.claude/settings.json</code>, preserving any existing hooks.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> frozen-view scrollback snapshot — while scrolled up, <code>cellAtGlobal</code> / <code>combiningAt</code> read from a snapshot of the screen at scroll-up time, not the live grid, so the viewport is completely immune to live screen writes. Locked by <code>tests/features/scrollback_frozen_view/</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> richer Claude status vocabulary (idle / thinking / bash / reading / editing / searching / browsing / planning / auditing / prompting / compacting) with distinct theme colours; plan-mode and <code>/audit</code> detection in the transcript parser; new <code>planModeChanged</code> and <code>auditingChanged</code> signals; <code>notification_timeout_ms</code> and <code>tab_color_sequence</code> config keys.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> Review Changes button is now tri-state — hidden when not a git repo, disabled when clean and in-sync, enabled otherwise. Probe switched to <code>git status --porcelain=v1 -b</code> so unpushed commits count as reviewable work. The global <code>QPushButton:hover</code> rule is now <code>:enabled</code>-gated. The dialog is fully async — opens instantly with a placeholder and streams git output in, with the status-bar button disabled while it is open.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> status-bar layout uses <code>QSizePolicy::Fixed</code> across the branch / process / Claude-status / button chips. Only the transient notification slot is elastic and elides. Branch chip colour moved from green to cyan so it is visually distinct from Claude-state chips.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the focus-redirect race — the <code>focusChanged</code> lambda now exempts <code>QAbstractButton</code> focus targets and defers while a mouse button is held down, so button clicks on status-bar chrome are no longer cancelled mid-press.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> scrollback blank-line bloat on inactive tabs after session restart. Two root causes: <code>recalcGridSize</code> ran on unlaid-out tabs and shrank grids to 3×10 (pre-layout guard added); <code>TerminalGrid::resize</code> pushed every reflowed row to scrollback (now skips entirely-blank rows).</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> tab colours not persisting across restarts — UUID-keyed <code>tab_groups</code> only worked with session persistence enabled; an ordered <code>tab_color_sequence</code> fallback is now applied at startup.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Add-to-Allowlist button gains a 3-scan debounce against TUI-repaint flicker and a shared <code>toolFinished</code> / <code>sessionStopped</code> retraction path across scroll-scan and hook detections.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.32" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Audit self-learning layer + contributor-facing docs + a one-line CI hotfix for 0.6.31's OSC 133 verifier. The headline is a per-rule fire/suppression tracker that records every audit finding and user suppression to <code>&lt;project&gt;/audit_rule_quality.json</code>, plus a new "📊 Rule Quality" button in the audit dialog that surfaces the noisiest rules first. A longest-common-substring suggester turns the last few suppressions for a noisy rule into a one-line <code>dropIfContains</code> proposal that's a copy-paste away from the user's <code>audit_rules.json</code> override pack.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — audit self-learning:</em> <code>RuleQualityTracker</code> (<code>src/auditrulequality.{h,cpp}</code>) records per-rule fire and suppression events with a 90-day rolling window and 50 000-record-per-category cap. Saves on dialog destruction (RAII) and force-flushes on each suppression so user actions are durable.</li>
          <li><em>Added — Rule Quality dialog:</em> new modal table view listing per-rule 30-day fires, 30-day suppressions, FP rate (capped 0-100 %), all-time fires, and a proposed <code>dropIfContains</code> tightening when the heuristic suggester has enough samples. Sorted by FP rate desc so the noisiest rules surface first.</li>
          <li><em>Added — LCS tightening suggester:</em> longest common substring across the last 5 suppressed line texts per rule. Floor at 6 chars + at least one structural boundary character (space, paren, brace, bracket, semicolon, quote, angle bracket) so we propose rule-shape filters, not project-noun filters. Surfaces inline in the status bar on every suppression.</li>
          <li><em>Added — docs:</em> <code>docs/RECOMMENDED_ROUTINES.md</code> captures the four Claude Code routines that earn a slot on the shared account quota for this repo — nightly audit triage, PR security review, weekly audit-rule self-triage (the deeper LLM-driven counterpart to the always-on tracker), and a monthly ROADMAP-item scoper.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — CI build:</em> 0.6.31's OSC 133 verifier used a <code>QByteArrayView</code> overload of <code>QMessageAuthenticationCode::addData</code> not available on the Ubuntu runner's Qt 6.x. Switched to the <code>(const char*, qsizetype)</code> overload present everywhere; behaviour unchanged.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.31" date="2026-04-17">
      <description>
        <p>Security + reliability release. The headline is <em>OSC 133 HMAC-signed shell integration</em>: when <code>$ANTS_OSC133_KEY</code> is set, every prompt / command / exit marker must carry a matching <code>HMAC-SHA256</code> tag, and forged markers from in-terminal processes are dropped (with a throttled status-bar warning). When the key is unset, behaviour is unchanged from 0.6.30 — no upgrade penalty for users who don't opt in.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Security:</em> OSC 133 HMAC verification closes the spoofing surface where any process writing to stdout (a malicious TUI, <code>cat malicious.txt</code>) could otherwise mint shell-integration markers and pollute prompt regions, exit codes, and the <code>command_finished</code> plugin event. Shell hooks ship under <code>${datarootdir}/ants-terminal/shell-integration/</code> for bash and zsh.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Review Changes status-bar button no longer silently swallows clicks on a clean repo — the disabled-but-visible state was advertising itself as actionable via the global hover stylesheet while never emitting <code>clicked()</code>. The button is now hidden on clean repos and reappears the moment a real diff exists.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Shift+Enter no longer wedges the terminal tab in bracketed-paste mode (0.6.26 regression). A <code>QByteArray(literal, 8)</code> truncation dropped the closing <code>[201~</code> end-paste marker; switched to <code>QByteArrayLiteral</code> so the size is derived at compile time.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Status-bar Add-to-allowlist button no longer stacks duplicates when a scroll-scan detection fires while a hook-path container is already visible — dedup lookup now uses <code>QWidget*</code> for parity with the other lookup sites.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — audit signal-to-noise:</em> Two-pass triage of the Ants and Vestige audit runs cuts the false-positive rate from ~97% to under 10% with no loss of real coverage. Tightened <code>memory_patterns</code>, <code>secrets_scan</code>, <code>file_perms</code>, and <code>header_guards</code> rules; dropped clazy <code>qt-keywords</code>; collapsed clang-tidy driver-error storms; added context-window suppressions to six rules; demoted tool timeouts and advisory checks to Info severity.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.30" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>Contributor-facing workflow infrastructure release. No runtime or behavior changes for end users — the binary is bit-identical to 0.6.29 modulo the version string. New files are tooling for contributors who clone the repo and work on it through Claude Code.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New <code>.claude/settings.json</code> wires a PostToolUse hook on Edit|Write that delegates to <code>packaging/hook-on-cmakelists-edit.sh</code>. The script runs <code>check-version-drift.sh</code> the moment an agent edits CMakeLists.txt and surfaces drift via systemMessage — closes the honor-system gap that allowed the 0.6.23 packaging slip.</li>
          <li>New <code>.claude/bump.json</code> recipe consumed by a user-level <code>/bump</code> skill. Lists the 6 version-bearing files with templated find/replace, plus 4 todos for content the recipe can't synthesise.</li>
          <li>New <code>packaging/hook-on-cmakelists-edit.sh</code>: small bash dispatcher; stdin is PostToolUse JSON, stdout is empty on clean state or a systemMessage on drift; always exits 0.</li>
          <li><code>.gitignore</code> narrowed <code>.claude/</code> → <code>.claude/*</code> with explicit exceptions for <code>settings.json</code> and <code>bump.json</code> so the team-shared workflow files commit while developer-local <code>settings.local.json</code> and <code>worktrees/</code> stay ignored.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.29" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>Status-bar reliability pass — nail down every user-reported symptom in one go: git branch chip "…" under tight layout, Review Changes button not appearing until a tab-switch, Add-to-Allowlist button silently no-op on save failure, Claude status label 2 s stale after tab-switch.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><code>ElidedLabel::minimumSizeHint</code> now returns the full-text width (capped at <code>maximumWidth</code>). Short text is guaranteed to render without elision regardless of layout squeeze — the statusbar's QBoxLayout previously compressed chips to a 3-char minimum and the text came out as "…" even with ample space. <code>sizeHint</code> also no longer reflects post-elision text (avoiding the chicken-and-egg loop where elision fed its own minimum).</li>
          <li>Review Changes button is now refreshed on every 2 s status-bar tick (not only tab-switch + Claude hook <code>fileChanged</code>). Dirty repos on startup show the button immediately; manual <code>git add</code> / <code>git commit</code> / external editor workflows flip the button live without needing Claude hooks.</li>
          <li><code>ClaudeIntegration::setShellPid</code> calls <code>pollClaudeProcess()</code> immediately on PID change so the status label reflects the new tab within one event-loop iteration rather than being <code>NotRunning</code> for up to 2 s until the next timer tick.</li>
          <li><code>ClaudeAllowlistDialog::saveSettings</code> now returns <code>bool</code>; all three callers (prompt-prefill, OK, Apply) surface failure to the user via status message or validation label. Previously every open/write/commit failure was swallowed and the button appeared to do nothing.</li>
          <li>Add-to-Allowlist button is now prompt-scoped in both creation paths: the hook-server button-group QWidget has <code>objectName "claudeAllowBtn"</code> matching the scroll-scan path, so <code>onTabChanged</code> cleans up both; the hook-server path's cleared-listener covers every terminal (not just <code>currentTerminal()</code>) so approving on the originating tab after a brief visit to another still clears the button.</li>
          <li><code>showDiffViewer</code> replaces every silent <code>return</code> with an explicit status message so the Review Changes button can't click through to nothing — previously a failed <code>focusedTerminal</code>, empty <code>shellCwd</code>, or non-zero git exit all disappeared without feedback. Combined <code>git diff HEAD</code> in a single invocation (covers worktree + index) rather than two.</li>
          <li>New <code>tests/features/status_bar_elision</code> feature test locks the short-text-never-elides invariant inside a real QMainWindow + QStatusBar harness; fails against pre-fix <code>ElidedLabel</code>, passes on fix.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.28" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>End-to-end feature review — same-class overflow sweep across the status bar, title bar, and audit dialog; quake-mode toggle fix; combining-character preservation on resize; disk-write durability hardening; auto-profile regex caching.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New <code>ElidedLabel</code> widget truncates long text with "…" to a bounded width. Applied to the three status-bar text slots (git branch, transient message, foreground process), the window title label, the Claude status label, and the audit-dialog status label — each previously grew unbounded and pushed siblings off-screen.</li>
          <li>Quake-mode toggle no longer auto-hides the window 200 ms after a show toggle. The reused <code>QPropertyAnimation</code>'s <code>finished→hide()</code> slot from a prior hide toggle was still connected on the show branch; the slot is now disconnected before every <code>start()</code> and re-attached only on the hide branch.</li>
          <li>Terminal resize preserves the per-line combining-character side table on both main and alt screens. Pre-0.6.28 every resize wiped accents, ZWJ sequences, and diacritics because the simple-copy path walked cells only. Shrink cases cleanly evict combining entries whose column falls outside the new width. New <code>tests/features/combining_on_resize</code> feature test pins the three invariants.</li>
          <li>Config and session writes now <code>fsync()</code> the temp file before atomic rename, closing the kernel-crash data-loss window on ext4 <code>data=ordered</code>.</li>
          <li>Auto-profile rule regex is cached across the 2 s poll tick instead of recompiled per-rule-per-tick, and invalid patterns are detected via <code>QRegularExpression::isValid()</code> and warned once rather than silently never matching.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.27" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Seventh release in the 0.6 UX polish pass — ncurses <code>clear</code> scrollback fix, scroll-offset clamp, tab-close visibility, Claude "prompting" state.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ncurses <code>clear</code> now correctly wipes scrollback on <code>TERM=xterm-256color</code>. The 0.6.26 Ink-overflow-repaint heuristic was false-matching the byte-burst because <code>clear</code>'s <code>\E[H\E[2J\E[3J</code> sequence overlaps with Ink's <code>clearTerminal</code>. Disambiguated via cursor position at <code>3J</code> time — <code>clear</code> emits <code>H</code> first so the cursor sits at (0,0); Ink emits <code>H</code> last so the cursor is at the bottom.</li>
          <li>Scroll-to-bottom button no longer lingers when scrollback shrinks. <code>m_scrollOffset</code> is now re-clamped in the single <code>updateScrollBar()</code> choke-point after every output batch.</li>
          <li>Tab close (×) button is always visible — removed the stylesheet rule that hid the glyph and left only an invisible hover hit-target.</li>
          <li>Claude status bar now shows "Claude: prompting" when a permission prompt is waiting, even if the transcript-driven state still reports idle/thinking. Critical when the user is scrolled up in history and can't see the live prompt.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.26" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>UX polish pass — status bar consistency, focus handling, Ink overflow-repaint fix, and tab colour gradient.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Claude Code (Ink/React TUI) overflow-repaint no longer destroys scrollback or duplicates the replay. <code>CSI 2J</code> followed within 50 ms by <code>CSI 3J</code> on the main screen is now treated as Ink's <code>clearTerminal</code> frame-reset marker (see <code>ink/build/ink.js:705</code>) rather than a user-initiated scrollback wipe — scrollback is preserved and the suppression window is armed for the subsequent replay. Standalone <code>CSI 3J</code> (user-initiated <code>clear -x</code>) still wipes scrollback as expected. Two new feature-conformance scenarios assert both behaviours.</li>
          <li>Status bar is now height-stable. <code>QStatusBar</code>'s size hint had been tracking its tallest child, so the bar grew when the transient "Add to allowlist" button appeared and shrank when it went away. A 32 px minimum-height floor keeps the bar consistent whether or not a button is attached.</li>
          <li>"Review Changes" status-bar button now matches the sibling "Add to allowlist" button's enabled look — it inherits the global <code>QPushButton</code> style instead of its own custom stylesheet (the 0.6.26 "bold to fix Gruvbox contrast" attempt made lowercase letters squish into a small-caps look on Fusion + monospace). Disabled state gets its own visual language (dashed border, italic, muted fg) so a clean-repo state reads clearly as non-actionable.</li>
          <li>Git branch chip now has a hard vertical divider separating it from the transient-status slot, visible on low-contrast themes where the chip's rounded-background treatment was indistinguishable from the status bar background.</li>
          <li>Focus auto-returns to the active terminal whenever focus lands on chrome widgets (status bar buttons, tab bar) with no dialog open. Clicking a status bar button, answering a prompt, etc., no longer leaves the keyboard parked on the button.</li>
          <li>Claude Code context-usage progress bar is hidden until the first real (non-zero) context percentage arrives. A fresh tab, or a tab where Claude was never started, no longer paints a persistent "0%" widget.</li>
          <li>Tab-colour badge replaced with a vertical gradient (transparent top → chosen colour bottom). The active-tab 2 px accent underline is preserved by excluding the bottom two pixels from the gradient area.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.25" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>User-reported scrollback regression fix plus packaging-rule hardening.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Scrolled-up viewport no longer shifts when streaming content arrives. The 0.6.21 pause and 0.6.22/0.6.24 CSI-clear window both skipped scrollback pushes, which froze the scroll anchor and let screen-scroll mechanics bleed into the user's viewport. Fix: push to scrollback while the user is scrolled up (anchor adjusts <code>m_scrollOffset</code> to compensate); the doubling-protection window still fires for the at-bottom case where the doubling symptom is observable.</li>
          <li>Extended the <code>packaging-version-drift</code> audit rule to scan <code>org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml</code>. The file's <code>&lt;release version=&gt;</code> entry is version-coupled to every release but was not previously checked. Flagged by the ninth periodic audit (2026-04-15).</li>
          <li>Extracted the drift-check logic into <code>packaging/check-version-drift.sh</code> — a standalone script that is the single source of truth. Both <code>src/auditdialog.cpp</code> and the CI workflow invoke the same script, so they can no longer drift apart.</li>
          <li>Wired the script into <code>.github/workflows/ci.yml</code> as a gating check; a PR that bumps CMakeLists.txt without updating every packaging file now fails CI instead of merging and requiring a follow-up tag.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.24" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Status-bar button-lifecycle and legibility fixes alongside the full-clear scrollback suppression extension.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Status-bar "Add to allowlist" button now persists for the full life of the Claude Code permission prompt — previously the button was retracted on the next repaint tick, vanishing within seconds of the prompt appearing.</li>
          <li>"Review Changes" button disabled-state text now readable on every theme. Previous textSecondary-based fix still failed WCAG AA on One Dark / Kanagawa; switched to textPrimary + italic + dissolved border so the label stays legible while still communicating the disabled state.</li>
          <li>Extended the 0.6.22 suppression window to <code>CSI H; CSI 0J</code> and corner-cursor <code>CSI 1J</code> — both produce the same post-state as <code>CSI 2J</code> and therefore exhibit the same doubling bug on TUI redraw bursts. Regression tests for both shapes added to <code>tests/features/scrollback_redraw/</code>.</li>
          <li>Packaging recipes (openSUSE spec, Arch PKGBUILD, Debian changelog, man page) bumped to 0.6.24 after drifting two releases behind — the exact drift the <code>packaging-version-drift</code> audit rule was written to catch.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.23" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Three user-reported UX fixes, an event-driven status-bar contract, and the first 0.7.0 performance item — SIMD VT-parser scan.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Allowlist "already covered" check no longer blocks legitimate compound rules — subsumption now splits on shell operators (<code>&amp;&amp;</code>, <code>||</code>, <code>;</code>, <code>|</code>) and requires every segment to match before declaring coverage.</li>
          <li>Right-click tab colour picker now renders visibly — a new <code>ColoredTabBar</code> paints a 3-px strip outside stylesheet influence (was defeated by QSS specificity).</li>
          <li>Status bar clears event-scoped transients (Allow buttons, notifications) on tab switch so state from one tab never leaks into another.</li>
          <li>Fixed a Shift+Enter paste-image regression.</li>
          <li>SIMD ground-state scan (SSE2 / NEON) — bulk <code>Print</code> emission on runs of safe printable-ASCII, with byte-identical action-stream regression guards.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.22" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Root-cause fix for main-screen TUI scrollback doubling, plus packaging catch-up across all recipes.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Scrollback no longer accumulates duplicates when a main-screen TUI (Claude Code v2.1+) repaints via <code>CSI 2J</code> — a 250 ms sliding window now suppresses scrollback pushes during the repaint burst.</li>
          <li>Packaging recipes (openSUSE spec, Arch PKGBUILD, Debian changelog) bumped to 0.6.22 after drifting three releases behind.</li>
          <li>openSUSE spec gains <code>%post</code>/<code>%postun</code> scriptlets for desktop-database and icon-cache refresh.</li>
          <li>Debian gains <code>postinst</code>/<code>postrm</code> scripts for the same purpose.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.21" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Audit-tool noise reduction, dialog theming, and a scrollback-insert pause for users actively reading history while a TUI repaints.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed a GNU grep 3.12 argument-ordering quirk that silently disabled the audit's <code>--include</code> file-type filter.</li>
          <li>Extended the QSS cascade so every popup dialog inherits the terminal's active theme.</li>
          <li>Added a scrollback-insert pause that stops TUI redraws from interleaving intermediate frames into the user's reading position.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.20" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-adoption bundle H5: OBS, AUR, and Debian packaging recipes.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.19" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H4: bash, zsh, and fish shell completions plus CMake install rules.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.18" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H3: ants-terminal(1) man page with CMake install rule.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.17" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H2: AppStream metainfo and spec-compliant desktop entry.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added <code>org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml</code> for GNOME Software and KDE Discover discovery.</li>
          <li>Added <code>org.ants.Terminal.desktop</code> following the reverse-DNS naming convention.</li>
          <li>CMake install rules for desktop entry, metainfo, and hicolor-theme icons at six sizes.</li>
          <li>CI validates packaging artefacts with <code>appstreamcli</code> and <code>desktop-file-validate</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.16" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H1: community and security policy documents.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added <code>CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md</code> (Contributor Covenant 2.1) with dedicated reporting channels.</li>
          <li>Changelogged the previously shipped <code>SECURITY.md</code> coordinated-disclosure policy.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.15" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Incremental scrollback reflow with a fast path for standalone lines.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.14" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Security hardening — URI scheme allowlist in <code>addRowHyperlink</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
