<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  AppStream metainfo for Ants Terminal.

  Consumed by GNOME Software, KDE Discover, and distro appstream catalogues
  (Debian DEP-11, Fedora AppStream, openSUSE OBS, Arch pacman-contrib).
  The `id` matches the `.desktop` filename stem (reverse-DNS) so that
  `launchable` can tie the two together.

  Validate with:
    appstreamcli validate packaging/linux/org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml
    desktop-file-validate packaging/linux/org.ants.Terminal.desktop

  When cutting a release, add a new <release/> entry at the top of the
  <releases/> list (newest first) with version/date and a short summary
  of user-visible changes — distros surface this in the update-details UI.

  Screenshots live under docs/screenshots/ and are referenced below via
  raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/.
  Rename there + here in the same commit — URLs are literal.
-->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>org.ants.Terminal</id>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.ants.Terminal.desktop</launchable>

  <name>Ants Terminal</name>
  <summary>Modern, themeable terminal emulator with GPU rendering and plugins</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>

  <developer id="org.ants">
    <name>Ants Terminal Contributors</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Ants Terminal is a fast, feature-rich terminal emulator written from
      scratch in C++20 with Qt6. It targets the capabilities modern
      terminal users expect — true-color themes, ligatures, hyperlinks,
      inline images, and a scriptable plugin system — without dragging
      in a web runtime.
    </p>
    <p>Key features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Eleven built-in themes with full ANSI palette overrides, plus automatic dark/light switching that follows the system color scheme.</li>
      <li>Optional OpenGL glyph-atlas renderer for GPU-accelerated draws; QPainter path with ligature-aware text shaping (HarfBuzz) remains the default.</li>
      <li>Inline images via Sixel, Kitty graphics protocol, and iTerm2 OSC 1337. Image paste auto-saves to disk — optimized for LLM / coding-agent workflows.</li>
      <li>Shell integration via OSC 133 (prompt jump, exit-status marks). OSC 8 hyperlinks, OSC 52 clipboard, OSC 9/777 desktop notifications, OSC 9;4 progress reporting.</li>
      <li>Kitty keyboard protocol with progressive enhancement, synchronized output, SGR mouse reporting, focus reporting.</li>
      <li>Embedded Lua 5.4 plugin system (sandboxed) with documented <code>ants.*</code> API. Session persistence saves scrollback across restarts.</li>
      <li>Built-in Project Audit panel: clazy + cppcheck + semgrep + regex rules with SARIF v2.1.0 export, AI-assisted triage, and confidence scoring.</li>
      <li>Configurable keybindings, command snippets, auto-profile rules, SSH bookmarks, and an OpenAI-compatible AI assistant dialog.</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <categories>
    <category>System</category>
    <category>TerminalEmulator</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>terminal</keyword>
    <keyword>console</keyword>
    <keyword>shell</keyword>
    <keyword>bash</keyword>
    <keyword>emulator</keyword>
    <keyword>tty</keyword>
    <keyword>command</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal</url>
  <url type="help">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/blob/main/README.md</url>
  <url type="contribute">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md</url>

  <provides>
    <binary>ants-terminal</binary>
  </provides>

  <supports>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>pointing</control>
  </supports>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Main terminal — custom title bar, tab gradient, status bar</caption>
      <image type="source" width="2103" height="1137">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/01-main-terminal.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Review Changes dialog — per-file diff and apply flow</caption>
      <image type="source" width="2110" height="1140">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/02-review-changes.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Project Audit panel — clazy, cppcheck, and grep findings with SARIF export</caption>
      <image type="source" width="2103" height="1137">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/03-project-audit.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.7.4" date="2026-04-20">
      <description>
        <p>A session's worth of user-facing UI fixes plus a new Debug Mode that made them possible. Tools → Debug Mode gives 14 independent category toggles (Paint, Events, Input, PTY, VT, Render, Plugins, Network, Config, Audit, Claude, Signals, Shell, Session) that write timestamped lines to ~/.local/share/ants-terminal/debug.log, enabled narrowly (one category) or broadly (all). The instrument pinpointed a ~54 Hz full-window repaint cascade that had been driving the menubar / dropdown / paste-dialog flicker across several releases.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Debug Mode:</em> env-var bootstrap (<code>ANTS_DEBUG=all</code> or <code>ANTS_DEBUG=paint,events,vt</code>) or in-app Tools → Debug Mode menu with checkable categories + Open Log File + Clear Log actions. Hot-path cost when disabled is a single bit-test.</li>
          <li><em>Added — OSC 133 prompt-on-new-line guard:</em> when a shell emits OSC 133 A (prompt start) and the cursor is not at column 0, the terminal nudges it to a new line first. Fixes "prompt glued onto the end of the previous command's output" (e.g. <code>cat file.json</code> with no trailing newline). Equivalent to zsh's PROMPT_SP, but terminal-side so it works for bash / fish / any shell that emits OSC 133.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — menubar hover flash:</em> QMenuBar now sets <code>autoFillBackground(true)</code> + <code>Qt::WA_StyledBackground</code> so the stylesheet background-color paints reliably under a WA_TranslucentBackground parent; <code>:hover</code> mirrors <code>:selected</code> to close the one-frame pre-selected hover gap; <code>setNativeMenuBar(false)</code> made explicit.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — paste-confirmation dialog:</em> rewrote to the fully async Review-Changes pattern (heap QDialog + WA_DeleteOnClose + show()/raise()/activateWindow(), no exec(), no QEventLoop). Three prior attempts via QMessageBox::exec, QDialog::exec, and show()+QEventLoop all hit the ApplicationModal-vs-frameless-parent click-swallow regression that was originally diagnosed for the Review-Changes dialog at 0.6.29.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — Command Palette idle timer churn:</em> the palette's hidden QListWidget ran its QAbstractItemView timer machinery at ~50 Hz from MainWindow construction onward, cascading a full-window repaint every frame. Lazy-create the list in <code>CommandPalette::show()</code> so the view doesn't exist until the user first presses Ctrl+Shift+P.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — QMainWindow dock animator:</em> <code>setAnimated(false)</code>. Ants has no dock widgets, but QMainWindow's built-in QWidgetAnimator ran continuously at idle.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — Qt UI effect animations disabled globally</em> (<code>UI_AnimateMenu</code>, <code>UI_FadeMenu</code>, <code>UI_AnimateCombo</code>, <code>UI_AnimateTooltip</code>, <code>UI_FadeTooltip</code>, <code>UI_AnimateToolBox</code>). These drove QPropertyAnimation(geometry) at 60 Hz on menu open/close; we have no use case for animated chrome.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — titlebar button tooltips removed.</em> A Qt / KWin / Wayland quirk fired the QTipLabel show/hide cycle on every frame while the cursor was near a titlebar button, animating the tooltip's geometry at ~60 Hz. Diagnosed via the debug-log system. Button glyphs (✥ / ✕ / ⬜ / ⟩) + hover-colour feedback give enough affordance without tooltip text.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — TerminalWidget base class:</em> QOpenGLWidget → plain QWidget. The GL widget composites its FBO through the parent's backing store and that always invalidates the top-level; PartialUpdate, WA_OpaquePaintEvent, swapInterval(0), and alpha-buffer opt-out all failed to break it. The QPainter path is unaffected (still ligature-aware via QTextLayout / HarfBuzz). The optional GL glyph-atlas renderer is dormant in 0.7.4 and returns later as an embedded QOpenGLWindow via createWindowContainer.</li>
          <li><em>Tests —</em> <code>menubar_hover_stylesheet</code>, <code>paste_dialog_custom</code>, and new <code>terminal_partial_update_mode</code> pin the invariants above (35/35 pass).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.3" date="2026-04-20">
      <description>
        <p>H6.1 of the 📦 distribution-adoption plan lands: Lua plugins inside the Flatpak sandbox. The 0.7.2 manifest shipped with plugin support disabled because <code>org.kde.Sdk//6.7</code> does not carry <code>lua54-devel</code> and <code>flathub/shared-modules</code> has no Lua 5.4 entry today. 0.7.3 closes that gap with an in-manifest Lua archive module, so a Flatpak build loads plugins the same way the openSUSE, Arch, and Debian builds do.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Lua 5.4 archive module in <code>packaging/flatpak/org.ants.Terminal.yml</code>:</em> a dedicated <code>lua</code> module appears before <code>ants-terminal</code>, built from the upstream Lua 5.4.7 source tarball with a pinned <code>sha256</code> and the <code>linux-noreadline</code> target (Ants links <code>liblua.a</code> statically — pulling readline into the sandbox would be pure bloat). <code>MYCFLAGS="-fPIC"</code> keeps the archive PIE-safe for linking into the <code>ants-terminal</code> executable; installed to <code>/app</code> via <code>make install INSTALL_TOP=/app</code>, which is exactly where CMake's <code>FindLua</code> searches by default when <code>CMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=/app</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added — auto-refresh of the Lua tarball hash:</em> the <code>lua</code> module carries an <code>x-checker-data:</code> stanza pointing at the upstream Lua FTP listing with <code>version-pattern: lua-(5\.4\.\d+)\.tar\.gz</code> and a <code>url-template</code> that substitutes the matched version into the canonical tarball URL. Flathub CI opens a PR against the Flathub repo with a refreshed <code>url</code> + <code>sha256</code> on each Lua 5.4.x point release — no manual hash churn, and 5.5.x majors are excluded (they would break the in-source <code>find_package(Lua 5.4)</code> floor).</li>
          <li><em>Added — feature test <code>tests/features/flatpak_lua_module/</code>:</em> source-grep regression pinning six invariants against the manifest YAML — Lua module precedes ants-terminal, <code>type: archive</code> with a pinned <code>sha256:</code>, <code>MYCFLAGS="-fPIC"</code> in the build commands, <code>make install INSTALL_TOP=/app</code>, the <code>linux-noreadline</code> target (guarding against the default <code>make linux</code> alias to <code>linux-readline</code>), and the <code>x-checker-data</code> stanza with the 5.4.x version-pattern.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>packaging/flatpak/README.md</code>:</em> the "Lua plugins — limitation" section is replaced with a "Lua plugins" section documenting the enabled path (archive-module build, <code>linux-noreadline</code> rationale, <code>x-checker-data</code> automation, success criterion of <code>PluginManager</code> loading a plugin inside the sandbox). Manifest header comment updated to describe the in-manifest module and the automated hash-refresh path.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>ROADMAP.md</code> H6.1</em> flipped from 📋 to ✅ (shipped in 0.7.3).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.2" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>H6 of the 📦 distribution-adoption plan lands: Flatpak packaging. One artifact that runs on every distro that ships <code>flatpak</code>, with a PTY path wired for the sandbox so the user's shell reaches the host's <code>$PATH</code> and filesystem. Unblocks the "packaged everywhere" roadmap gate without per-distro maintenance.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Flatpak manifest</em> (<code>packaging/flatpak/org.ants.Terminal.yml</code>): targets <code>org.kde.Platform//6.7</code> so the KDE SDK brings cmake, ninja, and every Qt6 component the build needs. <code>finish-args</code> cover Wayland + fallback-X11 + DRI, network (AI endpoint + SSH), portals (<code>org.freedesktop.portal.*</code> for global shortcuts / file dialogs), desktop notifications, and XDG config/data directories. Single <code>cmake-ninja</code> module; Ants source enters via <code>type: dir / path: ../..</code> for local builds and re-points to <code>type: git / url / tag</code> for Flathub submission.</li>
          <li><em>Added — Flatpak host-shell wiring in <code>ptyhandler.cpp</code>:</em> the forked child probes <code>FLATPAK_ID</code> and <code>/.flatpak-info</code> (either signal triggers the branch) and exec's the user's shell via <code>flatpak-spawn --host</code> with <code>--env=</code> forwarding for TERM / COLORTERM / TERM_PROGRAM / TERM_PROGRAM_VERSION (pulled from the <code>ANTS_VERSION</code> compile definition, not a literal) / COLORFGBG, plus <code>--directory=&lt;workDir&gt;</code> gated on <code>!workDir.isEmpty()</code>. The terminal emulator itself (VT parser, renderer, plugin VM) stays inside the sandbox; only the child shell escapes so tools and <code>$HOME</code> are reachable. Same PTY model as Ghostty's Flathub build. Outside Flatpak the existing <code>execlp</code> path runs byte-for-byte unchanged.</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>packaging/flatpak/README.md</code>:</em> local build (<code>flatpak-builder --install --user</code>), host-shell rationale, Flathub submission workflow, and the documented Lua-plugins-disabled limitation for the initial manifest (plugin support returns once a shared-modules Lua entry is wired up).</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>packaging/README.md</code> Flatpak section:</em> layout tree adds <code>flatpak/</code>; "Flatpak — <code>org.ants.Terminal.yml</code>" section mirrors the openSUSE / Arch / Debian sections; shared-concerns header updated from three recipes to four.</li>
          <li><em>Added — feature test <code>tests/features/flatpak_host_shell/</code>:</em> source-grep regression test pinning the branch shape — detection probes both signals in an OR, <code>--host</code> and <code>--</code> separators appear in argv, every TERM var crosses via <code>--env=</code>, workDir gates on <code>isEmpty()</code>, direct-exec fallback is preserved verbatim, <code>_exit(127)</code> is the post-exec fall-through on <code>execvp</code> failure.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>ROADMAP.md</code> H6</em> flipped from 📋 to ✅ manifest (0.7.2) + 📋 Flathub submission residual.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.1" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>First of the 0.8.0 🎨 multiplexing roadmap items lands ahead of the larger mux-server / remote-control work: SSH ControlMaster auto-multiplexing from the bookmark dialog. A second tab to the same host now reuses the first tab's session, skipping the full auth handshake — same precedent as kitty's <code>ssh</code> kitten, Warp's SSH blocks, and iTerm2's SSH profiles.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>SSH ControlMaster auto-multiplexing:</em> connects opened from the SSH Manager carry <code>-o ControlMaster=auto</code>, <code>-o ControlPath=$HOME/.ssh/cm-%r@%h:%p</code>, and <code>-o ControlPersist=10m</code> when the new <code>ssh_control_master</code> config key is true (default). Opt-out available for sites that forbid lingering multiplex sockets by policy. <code>$HOME</code> resolves in-process via <code>QDir::homePath()</code> so the ControlPath works under dash / POSIX <code>sh</code>; <code>%r@%h:%p</code> are OpenSSH ControlPath substitution tokens and survive shell quoting intact. Feature test <code>ssh_control_master</code> pins six invariants covering token presence/absence, <code>$HOME</code> resolution, positional ordering, and coexistence with the legacy <code>-p</code> / <code>-i</code> / extraArgs flags.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.0" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Shell integration + triggers — the 0.7.0 minor release rolls up the 0.6.1 → 0.6.45 patch-release arc into the theme the 0.7 ROADMAP plotted out. Command blocks become first-class UI, <code>.cast</code> recording ships, semantic history turns <code>path:line:col</code> into Ctrl-click jumps, OSC 133 markers gain HMAC verification, the full iTerm2-parity trigger set lands, the VT parser goes SIMD with a dedicated PTY/parse worker thread, Quake mode runs Wayland-native via layer-shell + GlobalShortcuts portal, and the H1–H4 distribution slice (SECURITY.md, AppStream metainfo, man page, shell completions) takes Ants from "side project" to "distro-ready." No breaking API changes — every plugin that loaded against 0.6.45 loads against 0.7.0.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Shell integration:</em> command blocks as first-class UI with OSC 133 prompt/command/output grouping, Ctrl+Shift+Up / Down jumps, collapsible output with "… N lines hidden" summaries, a 2px pass/fail stripe, and per-block right-click menu (Copy Command, Copy Output, Re-run, Fold/Unfold, Share as <code>.cast</code>). Asciinema <code>.cast</code> v2 recording — full-session via Ctrl+Shift+R or per-block via the context menu.</li>
          <li><em>Semantic history:</em> Ctrl-click on a <code>path:line:col</code> capture in scrollback opens the file at the cited position. CWD resolution via <code>/proc/&lt;pid&gt;/cwd</code> so relative paths Just Work. Editor support covers VS Code family, vi-family, nano, Sublime, Helix, Micro, and JetBrains.</li>
          <li><em>Security:</em> shell-side HMAC verification for OSC 133 markers — when <code>$ANTS_OSC133_KEY</code> is set, forged markers are dropped and a status-bar counter surfaces the count. Plugin capability audit UI renders every declared permission as a revocable checkbox in Settings → Plugins. Image-bomb defenses cap total decoded image bytes at 256 MB per terminal across Sixel / Kitty / iTerm2 OSC 1337.</li>
          <li><em>Triggers + plugin events:</em> full iTerm2-parity trigger rule set (<code>bell</code>, <code>inject</code>, <code>run_script</code>, <code>notify</code>, <code>sound</code>, <code>command</code>, <code>highlight_line</code>, <code>highlight_text</code>, <code>make_hyperlink</code>) with an <code>instant</code> flag. OSC 1337 SetUserVar with <code>user_var_changed</code> event. Command-palette plugin registration via <code>ants.palette.register()</code>. New events: <code>command_finished</code>, <code>pane_focused</code>, <code>theme_changed</code>, <code>window_config_reloaded</code>, <code>user_var_changed</code>, <code>palette_action</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Performance:</em> SIMD VT-parser scan — ground-state hot path scans 16 bytes at a time via SSE2 (x86_64) / NEON (ARM64). Dedicated PTY read + VT parse worker thread decouples input from the GUI with bounded back-pressure (≤ 8 batches in flight). Incremental reflow on resize skips the allocation-heavy rewrap round-trip for standalone lines.</li>
          <li><em>Platform — Wayland native:</em> layer-shell Quake mode promotes the window to <code>zwlr_layer_surface_v1</code> at <code>LayerTop</code> when <code>layer-shell-qt6-devel</code> is present (XCB path preserved for X11). Freedesktop GlobalShortcuts portal wires the <code>toggle-quake</code> id on KDE Plasma 6 and xdg-desktop-portal-hyprland / -wlr; in-app <code>QShortcut</code> fallback stays active on GNOME Shell.</li>
          <li><em>Distribution readiness (H1–H4):</em> <code>SECURITY.md</code> + <code>CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md</code> (coordinated-disclosure policy, Contributor Covenant 2.1) clear the Debian / Fedora / Ubuntu security-team review gate. AppStream metainfo + polished desktop entry with Desktop Actions for NewWindow + QuakeMode. <code>groff -man</code> man page at <code>packaging/linux/ants-terminal.1</code>. Shell completions for bash / zsh / fish installed to conventional vendor paths — auto-discovered on system-wide installs. CI runs <code>appstreamcli validate --explain</code>, <code>desktop-file-validate</code>, and <code>groff -man -Tutf8 -wall</code> on every push.</li>
          <li><em>Dev experience:</em> Project Audit gains four new rules (<code>unbounded_callback_payloads</code>, <code>qnetworkreply_no_abort</code>, <code>silent_catch</code>, <code>missing_build_flags</code>, <code>no_ci</code>), fixture-per-check self-consistency enforcement (<code>audit_fixture_coverage</code>), and a build-asan CI lane running ctest + binary smoke under ASan/UBSan on every push. <code>CONTRIBUTING.md</code> covers build modes, test layout, adding an audit rule, version-bump checklist. <code>actions/checkout</code> bumped v4.2.2 → v5.0.1 to pre-empt the 2026-06-02 Node 20 deprecation.</li>
          <li><em>Notes:</em> 0.7.0 is a minor-release rollup of 30 patch releases; the individual <code>0.6.x</code> CHANGELOG entries remain authoritative for the SHAs they shipped under. Deferred items (EGL swap-with-damage on GL, Domain abstraction, persistent workspaces, Kitty Unicode-placeholder graphics) are explicitly re-scoped to 0.8.0+.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.45" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Deferred VT-standards items from the 10th-audit research report, plus atomic-write hardening for long-lived audit state. The 11th periodic audit returned 0 of ~103 actionable findings — the baseline stays clean. User-visible win: modern Go / Rust TUIs (delta, lazygit, fzf, jj, neovim, bat, most <code>termenv</code>-based tools) can now auto-detect Ants' dark-vs-light theme without the unreliable <code>COLORFGBG</code> env var, and tmux / neovim / kitty-kitten can save-and-restore terminal state around their own output.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> OSC 10 / 11 / 12 colour queries. Apps that probe <code>\e]10;?\e\\</code> etc. get the xterm 16-bit-per-channel reply <code>\e]&lt;n&gt;;rgb:RRRR/GGGG/BBBB\e\\</code>. Only the query form is honoured — the set form is deliberately silently dropped so default fg / bg / cursor colour stays theme-driven and in-terminal programs can't inject a theme.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> DECRQSS (Request Status String). DCS <code>$q</code> requests for <code>DECSTBM</code> (scroll-region, <code>r</code>), <code>SGR</code> (current attributes, <code>m</code>), and <code>DECSCUSR</code> (cursor shape, <code> q</code>) reply with <code>DCS 1 $ r …</code> per the xterm spec. Unknown settings reply "invalid" (<code>DCS 0 $ r …</code>) rather than dropping silently so callers fall back to defaults. The DECRQSS branch gates on the <code>$q</code> prefix before Sixel's <code>q</code> search, so Sixel image traffic still routes to the image handler.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> atomic JSON writes via <code>QSaveFile</code> for four long-lived audit-state files — <code>audit_rule_quality.json</code> (frequent per-fire / per-suppression writes; corruption loses every rule score), <code>.audit_cache/trend.json</code> (cumulative severity totals), <code>.audit_cache/baseline.json</code> (fingerprints anchoring the "new findings only" filter), and the <code>.audit_suppress</code> v1 → v2 migration rewrite. Torn writes from crash or <code>kill -9</code> can no longer corrupt any of these. The one-line <code>.audit_suppress</code> append path stays non-atomic on purpose — the loader already skips malformed lines.</li>
          <li><em>Tests:</em> new <code>osc_color_query</code> feature test locks the OSC 10/11/12 response shape plus the query-only gate (set form MUST NOT produce a response); new <code>decrqss</code> test locks the DECSTBM / SGR / DECSCUSR replies, the "invalid" reply bytes, and a Sixel-routing regression guard so the new DECRQSS branch can't eat image traffic.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.44" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Project Audit dialog self-review pass. The 10th periodic audit returned 0 of 55 actionable findings — the nature of the 55 pointed at three bits of friction the dialog was creating for itself: it was auditing its own output, every "is this noise?" verdict needed an individual click, and users had no summary-level readout for "how much of this run was signal?". All three are closed in this release.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> signal-ratio readout in the summary banner. <code>renderResults()</code> now prints an "X% actionable" figure — signal / (signal + noise) where noise = suppressions + AI-verdict <code>FALSE_POSITIVE</code> — below the severity pills with colour coding (green ≥60%, amber 20–59%, red &lt;20%). A 30-day rolling average pulled from <code>RuleQualityTracker</code> sits next to it as a peer comparison ("30d avg X% actionable, n=Y fires").</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> batch AI triage. A <code>🧠 Triage visible (N)</code> button next to the confidence-sort toggle sends every visible, not-yet-triaged finding to the configured LLM in a single JSON request (hard cap 20 per batch; above that it slices and dispatches sequentially). Responses are spliced back by dedup key so a reordering model can't misalign results. Prompt-injection hardening inherited from the single-finding path. Hidden entirely when AI isn't configured.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> <code>isGeneratedFile()</code> now auto-skips prior audit artifacts — <code>docs/AUTOMATED_AUDIT_REPORT_*.{json,md,html,txt}</code> (SHA-256 dedup keys that gitleaks flagged as high-entropy secrets), <code>.audit_cache/</code> and <code>audit_rule_quality.json</code> (the dialog's own baseline + self-learning ledger; auditing them is circular), and <code>tests/audit_fixtures/**</code> (<code>bad.*</code> fixtures intentionally embed strings third-party scanners misread as real findings). No project configuration needed.</li>
          <li><em>Notes:</em> no schema changes. <code>audit_rule_quality.json</code> and <code>audit_rules.json</code> are read-compatible with prior versions. The 30-day actionable% uses <code>fires</code> as the denominator rather than run count, because run count isn't directly recorded — the label makes the denominator explicit (<code>n=&lt;count&gt; fires</code>).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.43" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Two user-reported regressions closed, plus a quality-of-life default flip. The 0.6.42 focus-redirect guards didn't cure the menubar hover flash — the real culprit was a stylesheet gap, not focus churn. And users coming back to the app expected their tabs to be waiting for them; session persistence now ships default-on, matching every modern terminal (iTerm2, Kitty, WezTerm, Konsole).</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> menubar hover no longer flashes. The 0.6.42 pass narrowed focus-redirect firing but didn't address the root cause. The stylesheet defined <code>QMenuBar::item:selected</code> without a matching base <code>QMenuBar::item</code> rule, so Qt fell back to the native style for the non-selected state and composited native drawing under the <code>:selected</code> overlay. Added an explicit transparent-background <code>QMenuBar::item</code> base rule plus a <code>:pressed</code> rule so every menubar item state is owned entirely by the stylesheet; the 0.6.42 focus guards remain as defense-in-depth.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> tabs are now remembered between sessions by default. <code>Config::sessionPersistence()</code> defaulted to <code>false</code>, so users who never toggled Settings → General → "Save and restore sessions" lost their tab set on every quit. Flipped the default to <code>true</code>; users with <code>session_persistence: false</code> explicit in <code>config.json</code> still get their opt-out honoured — only the absent-key path reads the new fallback. The 5-second uptime floor in <code>saveAllSessions()</code> still protects against crash-on-launch wiping real state.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> <code>Config::sessionPersistence()</code> default flipped from <code>false</code> to <code>true</code>. First-run users now get tab restore out of the box; explicit values in <code>config.json</code> are respected unchanged.</li>
          <li><em>Tests:</em> new <code>tests/features/session_persistence_default/</code> three-invariant feature test pins the truth table — missing key → true, explicit true → true, explicit false → false. Linked against <code>src/config.cpp</code> only (no GUI dependency). Brings the feature-test count to 25 and the total ctest count to 26.</li>
          <li><em>Internal:</em> cleaned up a <code>-Wshadow</code> warning at <code>mainwindow.cpp:3921</code> (Review-Changes finalizer lambda's <code>const Theme &amp;th</code> shadowed the outer <code>th</code>; renamed to <code>lth</code>) and dropped an unused <code>&lt;cstdlib&gt;</code> include from the new test.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.42" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Focus-redirect guard rails. Two user-visible regressions from the 0.6.26 auto-return-to-terminal behaviour — a flashing highlight as the mouse crossed the menubar, and the paste-confirmation dialog's "Paste" button silently swallowing mouse clicks — both traced back to the same <code>QApplication::focusChanged</code> handler firing through narrow windows it shouldn't. New guards short-circuit the redirect when a popup is open, when the cursor is over a menu or menubar, or when any top-level <code>QDialog</code> is visible — the last covers the <code>QMessageBox::exec()</code> modality-handshake tick during which <code>activeModalWidget()</code> can briefly be null.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> menubar File / Edit / View hover no longer flickers. The focus-redirect lambda now early-returns when <code>QApplication::activePopupWidget()</code> is non-null and when <code>QApplication::widgetAt(QCursor::pos())</code> has a <code>QMenu</code> or <code>QMenuBar</code> ancestor. Both guards are mirrored in the deferred <code>QTimer::singleShot(0,…)</code> fire-time block so a menu opened between queue and fire is still honoured.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the paste-confirmation <code>QMessageBox</code> no longer swallows clicks on the "Paste" button (pre-0.6.42 only the <code>&amp;Paste</code> mnemonic worked). The redirect now walks <code>QApplication::topLevelWidgets()</code> at queue time and early-returns on any visible <code>QDialog</code>, mirroring the fire-time check and covering the brief <code>show()</code> handshake window where <code>activeModalWidget()</code> returns null.</li>
          <li><em>Tests:</em> new <code>tests/features/focus_redirect_menu_guard/</code> source-grep pins six invariants on the focusChanged lambda in <code>src/mainwindow.cpp</code> — the popup and menu-hover guards (queue + fire time), the visible-dialog walk, and the five pre-existing guards (<code>activeModalWidget</code>, <code>QAbstractButton</code>, <code>mouseButtons</code>, <code>QDialog</code> parent chain, <code>CommandPalette</code>) that must not regress. Uses the balanced-brace scanner from 0.6.41 to avoid <code>std::regex</code> stack blow-out on a 4000+ line file.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.41" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Quake-mode + OSC 133 UX polish. Surfaces the out-of-focus portal binding state in Settings so users can tell at a glance whether their Quake hotkey escapes focus, and adds a scrollbar-adjacent tick-mark gutter that exposes OSC 133 command boundaries across the full scrollback — jump targets for <code>Ctrl+Shift+Up/Down</code> that were previously invisible.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> command-mark gutter (<code>show_command_marks</code>, default on) — a 4-px vertical strip just left of the scrollbar draws one tick per <code>PromptRegion</code>, color-coded by last exit status: green (success), red (non-zero exit), gray (in-progress, OSC 133 D not yet emitted). Positions compress linearly so a 50,000-line scrollback stays fully visible in the widget height.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> Settings → Terminal → Scrollback toggle "Show command markers in scrollbar gutter" (default on) with a tooltip explaining the color states. Propagates to all live terminals via <code>applyConfigToTerminal</code> — no restart needed.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> portal-binding status label in Settings → Quake. One line under the hotkey field reports either "Portal binding active" (green, hotkey works when Ants is unfocused — KDE Plasma 6, Hyprland, wlroots) or "Portal unavailable" (amber, hotkey works only while focused), based on <code>GlobalShortcutsPortal::isAvailable()</code> at dialog construction.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> gutter drawing gates on <code>m_showCommandMarks</code> AND non-empty <code>promptRegions()</code>, so users without shell integration see nothing change; ticks never overlap the scrollbar thumb (offset by <code>m_scrollBar->width()</code>).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.40" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>OSC 133 shell-integration polish. Adds two keyboard-driven "last completed command" actions that complement the existing block-at-cursor right-click menu with no-selection-needed top-level equivalents — the iTerm2 ⇧⌘O / WezTerm <code>CopyLastOutput</code> convention, surfaced through the View menu, the command palette, and configurable keybindings.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>TerminalWidget::copyLastCommandOutput()</code> slot — walks <code>promptRegions()</code> backwards for the most recent region with <code>commandEndMs &gt; 0 &amp;&amp; hasOutput</code> and copies the full output via <code>outputTextAt(idx)</code> (unbounded). Skips in-progress tails so <code>Ctrl+Alt+O</code> during <code>sleep 30</code> copies the previous command's output, never the partial in-progress one.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>TerminalWidget::rerunLastCommand()</code> slot — same backwards-walk / skip-in-progress rule, then writes the command text + <code>\r</code> to the PTY via <code>rerunCommandAt(idx)</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> View menu entries "Copy Last Command Output" (default <code>Ctrl+Alt+O</code>, config key <code>copy_last_output</code>) and "Re-run Last Command" (default <code>Ctrl+Alt+R</code>, config key <code>rerun_last_command</code>). Both surface automatically in the command palette; <code>Ctrl+Alt+*</code> avoids the already-taken <code>Ctrl+Shift+O</code> (split pane) and <code>Ctrl+Shift+R</code> (record session).</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> status-bar toasts for discoverability — success path shows "Copied N chars of last command output"; failure path shows "No completed command to copy (enable shell integration)", a load-bearing hint that OSC 133 needs bash/zsh/fish shell-integration hooks.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> locked by <code>tests/features/osc133_last_command</code> (CTest labels <code>features;fast</code>, part of the release gate) — pins the backwards-walk, the <code>outputTextAt</code>-not-<code>lastCommandOutput</code> choice, the keybinding wiring, and the toast contract.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.39" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Wayland-native Quake-mode, part 2 of 2 — completes the 0.7.0 roadmap item. When the <code>xdg-desktop-portal</code> service is available on the session bus, Ants Terminal now registers its Quake toggle with the Freedesktop Portal <code>org.freedesktop.portal.GlobalShortcuts</code> API (KDE Plasma 6, <code>xdg-desktop-portal-hyprland</code>, <code>xdg-desktop-portal-wlr</code>). The hotkey fires whether or not Ants has focus. On GNOME Shell (portal service present but no GlobalShortcuts backend yet) and on minimal desktops without a portal, the in-app <code>QShortcut</code> fallback from 0.6.38 stays as the activation path — no regression.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>GlobalShortcutsPortal</code> client class wrapping the three-step D-Bus handshake (<code>CreateSession</code> → session handle → <code>BindShortcuts</code> → <code>Activated</code>) behind a single Qt signal. Handles request-path prediction, custom meta-type registration for the <code>a(sa{sv})</code> shortcuts array, and session lifecycle.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> portal-aware Quake setup in <code>MainWindow</code> — when the portal is available, binds the <code>toggle-quake</code> id with <code>config.quake_hotkey</code> as the preferred trigger.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> focused double-fire debounce between the in-app <code>QShortcut</code> and the portal <code>Activated</code> paths (500 ms window) so a focused system doesn't hide-then-show the window in one frame.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>qtKeySequenceToPortalTrigger</code> helper that converts Qt's <code>"Ctrl+Shift+`"</code> into the freedesktop shortcut-syntax <code>"CTRL+SHIFT+grave"</code>. Deliberately minimal — modifiers plus a handful of common punctuation; unrecognised keys pass through.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> new <code>tests/features/global_shortcuts_portal/</code> regression test pins (1) <code>isAvailable()</code> gate on portal construction; (2) canonical D-Bus service / path / interface / method literals; (3) bound id <code>"toggle-quake"</code> matches the Activated handler filter; (4) in-app <code>QShortcut</code> fallback stays wired; (5) both activation paths debounce via <code>m_lastQuakeToggleMs</code>; (6) CMakeLists.txt lists the source + keeps <code>Qt6::DBus</code> linked; (7) header surfaces the expected public API.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.38" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Wayland-native Quake-mode, part 1 of 2. When <code>layer-shell-qt6</code> is present at build time, Ants Terminal's drop-down Quake mode now promotes its window to a <code>zwlr_layer_surface_v1</code> at the top layer, anchored to the top edge of the active screen — the Wayland equivalent of the X11 <code>_NET_WM_STATE_ABOVE</code> + client-side <code>move()</code> the XCB path has used all along. Also fixes a long-standing dead-code bug: the <code>quake_hotkey</code> config key was saved from Settings but never wired to a shortcut; the QLineEdit value is now honoured in-app. True out-of-focus global hotkey registration (via the Freedesktop Portal GlobalShortcuts API) is the 0.6.39 follow-up.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>LayerShellQt</code> integration — <code>CMakeLists.txt</code> does <code>find_package(LayerShellQt CONFIG QUIET)</code> and defines <code>ANTS_WAYLAND_LAYER_SHELL</code> when found. Missing = Wayland Quake falls back to the Qt toplevel path; X11 Quake is unaffected.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the <code>quake_hotkey</code> config key is now wired to a <code>QShortcut</code> invoking <code>toggleQuakeVisibility()</code>. Pre-0.6.38 the Settings dialog saved the user's chosen sequence but nothing consumed it.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the slide-up/slide-down animation no longer snaps on Wayland — <code>QPropertyAnimation</code> on <code>pos()</code> is a no-op there (the compositor owns position), so the Wayland path uses a plain show/hide toggle. XCB slide animation is unchanged.</li>
          <li><em>Packaging:</em> openSUSE spec adds <code>BuildRequires: cmake(LayerShellQt)</code>; Arch <code>PKGBUILD</code> adds <code>layer-shell-qt</code> to <code>makedepends</code> + <code>optdepends</code>; Debian <code>control</code> adds <code>liblayershellqt6-dev</code> to <code>Build-Depends</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> new <code>tests/features/wayland_quake_mode/</code> regression test pins (1) the layer-shell include is guarded by <code>ANTS_WAYLAND_LAYER_SHELL</code>; (2) <code>setupQuakeMode()</code> dispatches X11 vs Wayland at runtime; (3) <code>toggleQuakeVisibility()</code> skips the <code>pos()</code> animation on Wayland; (4) the <code>quake_hotkey</code> → <code>QShortcut</code> wire exists; (5) CMake uses the <code>QUIET</code> flavour of <code>find_package</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.37" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Phase 3 of the 0.7.0 threading refactor. The <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> kill-switch introduced in 0.6.34 is retired, and the legacy single-threaded read/parse code paths are deleted from <code>TerminalWidget</code>. The bake period (0.6.34 → 0.6.37) proved the worker path; the 0.6.35 hotfix proved the kill-switch worked. Every launch now goes through <code>VtStream</code> on the worker thread — one path, one set of invariants, four feature tests.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Removed:</em> the <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> environment kill-switch and the legacy <code>TerminalWidget::startShell()</code> branch it guarded.</li>
          <li><em>Removed:</em> legacy <code>m_pty</code> / <code>m_parser</code> members and the <code>onPtyData</code> slot — the widget no longer owns a <code>Pty</code> or <code>VtParser</code> directly; both live inside <code>VtStream</code> on the worker thread.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> <code>hasPty()</code> and <code>ptyChildPid()</code> simplified to worker-only checks; no behaviour change at the call sites.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.36" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Tenth periodic audit. Two actionable findings across ~110 raw — a 2% signal ratio consistent with the codebase's audit-calibration anchor. Both fixed in a single pass.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> <code>RuleQualityTracker::prune()</code> was dead code — <code>save()</code> inlined the same retention logic. Removed the dead function; <code>save()</code> is now the single source of truth for the 90-day cutoff.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> <code>pipeRun</code> regex in paste-confirmation was recompiled on every paste. Hoisted to <code>static const</code> so the pattern compiles once per process.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.35" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Hotfix for the 0.6.34 threaded-parse refactor. Keystrokes typed into the terminal were silently dropped — the echo never appeared on screen. Twelve PTY-write call sites in <code>TerminalWidget</code> (keystrokes, arrow keys, paste, focus reporting, scratchpad, context menu, and more) still carried pre-0.6.34 <code>if (m_pty) ptyWrite(...)</code> guards. Under the threaded parse path <code>m_pty</code> is null (the <code>Pty</code> now lives on the worker thread inside <code>VtStream</code>), so the guard silently swallowed every write. Replaced each with either <code>hasPty()</code> (path-agnostic) or an unconditional <code>ptyWrite(...)</code> call (the helper is null-safe). A new <code>threaded_ptywrite_gating</code> feature test pins the invariant at the source level so the bug can't come back quietly.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> keystrokes and paste no longer silently drop on the threaded parse path.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> <code>shellPid()</code> / <code>shellCwd()</code> / <code>foregroundProcess()</code> now work on the worker path via a new <code>ptyChildPid()</code> helper.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>threaded_ptywrite_gating</code> regression test — source-level guard against stale <code>m_pty</code> null-checks outside the allowlisted legacy-path functions.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.34" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Decouples PTY read and VT parsing from the Qt GUI thread. Previously, every byte of terminal output traversed the GUI thread through <code>QSocketNotifier → Pty::dataReceived → VtParser::feed → TerminalGrid::processAction</code> and then on to paint — so heavy streams (<code>find /</code>, <code>cat biglog</code>) blocked scroll and repaint. As of 0.6.34 read + parse run on a dedicated worker <code>QThread</code> (<code>VtStream</code>); only batched <code>VtAction</code> streams cross back to GUI for grid application and paint. Ships the first 0.7.0 performance item early since the architectural change landed clean with three feature-conformance tests locking the invariants.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>VtStream</code> worker wrapper (<code>src/vtstream.{h,cpp}</code>) — owns <code>Pty</code> and <code>VtParser</code> on a dedicated QThread, accumulates parser output into <code>VtBatch</code> and ships it to GUI over <code>Qt::QueuedConnection</code>. Grid and paint path stay on GUI so the refactor surface stays small.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> back-pressure — worker buffers up to 8 batches (~128 KB of unprocessed PTY bytes) before disabling its read notifier so the kernel applies flow control to the child; GUI re-enables reads on drain. Replaces "let RAM grow unbounded while GUI catches up" with kernel-natural flow control.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>Pty::setReadEnabled(bool)</code> for the back-pressure path. <code>Pty::write</code> and <code>Pty::resize</code> are now slots so they can be invoked cross-thread via <code>QMetaObject::invokeMethod</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> three feature-conformance tests under <code>tests/features/</code> — <code>threaded_parse_equivalence</code> (11 fixtures × 6 chunking strategies, pins action-stream identity), <code>threaded_response_ordering</code> (DA1/CPR/DA2/mode-996/DSR-OK order across 3 feed strategies), and <code>threaded_resize_synchronous</code> (source-level contract that <code>invokeMethod</code> uses <code>Qt::BlockingQueuedConnection</code>).</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> all PTY-write call sites in <code>TerminalWidget</code> route through a new <code>ptyWrite()</code> helper — keystrokes, bracketed paste, Kitty kbd protocol, response callbacks, snippets, scratchpad. The helper branches on worker-active vs. legacy path; correctness is centralised.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> resize path uses <code>Qt::BlockingQueuedConnection</code> so the PTY winsize is updated before <code>resizeEvent</code> returns — no 1-frame flicker at the new grid size with old PTY dims.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> session logging and asciicast timestamps are now sampled on the worker at batch-flush time rather than on GUI at onPtyData time; asciicast recordings are more accurate under paint load. Log write granularity is per-batch rather than per-PTY-read (coarser but still monotonic).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Kill switch: set <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> in the environment to force the legacy single-threaded path while the new code proves itself. It will be removed in a follow-up release once no regressions surface.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.33" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Nine long-standing user-reported bugs around the status bar, scrollback integrity, session restore, and the Review Changes dialog — fixed in one pass. The quiet centerpiece is the root-cause diagnosis of the long tail of "Review Changes button does nothing" reports: a 0.6.26-era <code>focusChanged</code> lambda was firing a <code>singleShot(0)</code> refocus <em>between</em> a button's mousePress and mouseRelease, ripping focus off the button mid-click and silently cancelling the <code>clicked()</code> signal. Also retires the <code>ElidedLabel</code> + stylesheet-chip-padding class of bug by converting every fixed-width status-bar chip to plain <code>QLabel</code> / <code>QPushButton</code> with <code>QSizePolicy::Fixed</code>.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> one-click "Install Claude Code status-bar hooks" action in Settings &gt; General — writes <code>~/.config/ants-terminal/hooks/claude-forward.sh</code> and idempotently merges PreToolUse / PostToolUse / Stop / PreCompact / SessionStart entries into <code>~/.claude/settings.json</code>, preserving any existing hooks.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> frozen-view scrollback snapshot — while scrolled up, <code>cellAtGlobal</code> / <code>combiningAt</code> read from a snapshot of the screen at scroll-up time, not the live grid, so the viewport is completely immune to live screen writes. Locked by <code>tests/features/scrollback_frozen_view/</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> richer Claude status vocabulary (idle / thinking / bash / reading / editing / searching / browsing / planning / auditing / prompting / compacting) with distinct theme colours; plan-mode and <code>/audit</code> detection in the transcript parser; new <code>planModeChanged</code> and <code>auditingChanged</code> signals; <code>notification_timeout_ms</code> and <code>tab_color_sequence</code> config keys.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> Review Changes button is now tri-state — hidden when not a git repo, disabled when clean and in-sync, enabled otherwise. Probe switched to <code>git status --porcelain=v1 -b</code> so unpushed commits count as reviewable work. The global <code>QPushButton:hover</code> rule is now <code>:enabled</code>-gated. The dialog is fully async — opens instantly with a placeholder and streams git output in, with the status-bar button disabled while it is open.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> status-bar layout uses <code>QSizePolicy::Fixed</code> across the branch / process / Claude-status / button chips. Only the transient notification slot is elastic and elides. Branch chip colour moved from green to cyan so it is visually distinct from Claude-state chips.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the focus-redirect race — the <code>focusChanged</code> lambda now exempts <code>QAbstractButton</code> focus targets and defers while a mouse button is held down, so button clicks on status-bar chrome are no longer cancelled mid-press.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> scrollback blank-line bloat on inactive tabs after session restart. Two root causes: <code>recalcGridSize</code> ran on unlaid-out tabs and shrank grids to 3×10 (pre-layout guard added); <code>TerminalGrid::resize</code> pushed every reflowed row to scrollback (now skips entirely-blank rows).</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> tab colours not persisting across restarts — UUID-keyed <code>tab_groups</code> only worked with session persistence enabled; an ordered <code>tab_color_sequence</code> fallback is now applied at startup.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Add-to-Allowlist button gains a 3-scan debounce against TUI-repaint flicker and a shared <code>toolFinished</code> / <code>sessionStopped</code> retraction path across scroll-scan and hook detections.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.32" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Audit self-learning layer + contributor-facing docs + a one-line CI hotfix for 0.6.31's OSC 133 verifier. The headline is a per-rule fire/suppression tracker that records every audit finding and user suppression to <code>&lt;project&gt;/audit_rule_quality.json</code>, plus a new "📊 Rule Quality" button in the audit dialog that surfaces the noisiest rules first. A longest-common-substring suggester turns the last few suppressions for a noisy rule into a one-line <code>dropIfContains</code> proposal that's a copy-paste away from the user's <code>audit_rules.json</code> override pack.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — audit self-learning:</em> <code>RuleQualityTracker</code> (<code>src/auditrulequality.{h,cpp}</code>) records per-rule fire and suppression events with a 90-day rolling window and 50 000-record-per-category cap. Saves on dialog destruction (RAII) and force-flushes on each suppression so user actions are durable.</li>
          <li><em>Added — Rule Quality dialog:</em> new modal table view listing per-rule 30-day fires, 30-day suppressions, FP rate (capped 0-100 %), all-time fires, and a proposed <code>dropIfContains</code> tightening when the heuristic suggester has enough samples. Sorted by FP rate desc so the noisiest rules surface first.</li>
          <li><em>Added — LCS tightening suggester:</em> longest common substring across the last 5 suppressed line texts per rule. Floor at 6 chars + at least one structural boundary character (space, paren, brace, bracket, semicolon, quote, angle bracket) so we propose rule-shape filters, not project-noun filters. Surfaces inline in the status bar on every suppression.</li>
          <li><em>Added — docs:</em> <code>docs/RECOMMENDED_ROUTINES.md</code> captures the four Claude Code routines that earn a slot on the shared account quota for this repo — nightly audit triage, PR security review, weekly audit-rule self-triage (the deeper LLM-driven counterpart to the always-on tracker), and a monthly ROADMAP-item scoper.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — CI build:</em> 0.6.31's OSC 133 verifier used a <code>QByteArrayView</code> overload of <code>QMessageAuthenticationCode::addData</code> not available on the Ubuntu runner's Qt 6.x. Switched to the <code>(const char*, qsizetype)</code> overload present everywhere; behaviour unchanged.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.31" date="2026-04-17">
      <description>
        <p>Security + reliability release. The headline is <em>OSC 133 HMAC-signed shell integration</em>: when <code>$ANTS_OSC133_KEY</code> is set, every prompt / command / exit marker must carry a matching <code>HMAC-SHA256</code> tag, and forged markers from in-terminal processes are dropped (with a throttled status-bar warning). When the key is unset, behaviour is unchanged from 0.6.30 — no upgrade penalty for users who don't opt in.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Security:</em> OSC 133 HMAC verification closes the spoofing surface where any process writing to stdout (a malicious TUI, <code>cat malicious.txt</code>) could otherwise mint shell-integration markers and pollute prompt regions, exit codes, and the <code>command_finished</code> plugin event. Shell hooks ship under <code>${datarootdir}/ants-terminal/shell-integration/</code> for bash and zsh.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Review Changes status-bar button no longer silently swallows clicks on a clean repo — the disabled-but-visible state was advertising itself as actionable via the global hover stylesheet while never emitting <code>clicked()</code>. The button is now hidden on clean repos and reappears the moment a real diff exists.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Shift+Enter no longer wedges the terminal tab in bracketed-paste mode (0.6.26 regression). A <code>QByteArray(literal, 8)</code> truncation dropped the closing <code>[201~</code> end-paste marker; switched to <code>QByteArrayLiteral</code> so the size is derived at compile time.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Status-bar Add-to-allowlist button no longer stacks duplicates when a scroll-scan detection fires while a hook-path container is already visible — dedup lookup now uses <code>QWidget*</code> for parity with the other lookup sites.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — audit signal-to-noise:</em> Two-pass triage of the Ants and Vestige audit runs cuts the false-positive rate from ~97% to under 10% with no loss of real coverage. Tightened <code>memory_patterns</code>, <code>secrets_scan</code>, <code>file_perms</code>, and <code>header_guards</code> rules; dropped clazy <code>qt-keywords</code>; collapsed clang-tidy driver-error storms; added context-window suppressions to six rules; demoted tool timeouts and advisory checks to Info severity.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.30" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>Contributor-facing workflow infrastructure release. No runtime or behavior changes for end users — the binary is bit-identical to 0.6.29 modulo the version string. New files are tooling for contributors who clone the repo and work on it through Claude Code.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New <code>.claude/settings.json</code> wires a PostToolUse hook on Edit|Write that delegates to <code>packaging/hook-on-cmakelists-edit.sh</code>. The script runs <code>check-version-drift.sh</code> the moment an agent edits CMakeLists.txt and surfaces drift via systemMessage — closes the honor-system gap that allowed the 0.6.23 packaging slip.</li>
          <li>New <code>.claude/bump.json</code> recipe consumed by a user-level <code>/bump</code> skill. Lists the 6 version-bearing files with templated find/replace, plus 4 todos for content the recipe can't synthesise.</li>
          <li>New <code>packaging/hook-on-cmakelists-edit.sh</code>: small bash dispatcher; stdin is PostToolUse JSON, stdout is empty on clean state or a systemMessage on drift; always exits 0.</li>
          <li><code>.gitignore</code> narrowed <code>.claude/</code> → <code>.claude/*</code> with explicit exceptions for <code>settings.json</code> and <code>bump.json</code> so the team-shared workflow files commit while developer-local <code>settings.local.json</code> and <code>worktrees/</code> stay ignored.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.29" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>Status-bar reliability pass — nail down every user-reported symptom in one go: git branch chip "…" under tight layout, Review Changes button not appearing until a tab-switch, Add-to-Allowlist button silently no-op on save failure, Claude status label 2 s stale after tab-switch.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><code>ElidedLabel::minimumSizeHint</code> now returns the full-text width (capped at <code>maximumWidth</code>). Short text is guaranteed to render without elision regardless of layout squeeze — the statusbar's QBoxLayout previously compressed chips to a 3-char minimum and the text came out as "…" even with ample space. <code>sizeHint</code> also no longer reflects post-elision text (avoiding the chicken-and-egg loop where elision fed its own minimum).</li>
          <li>Review Changes button is now refreshed on every 2 s status-bar tick (not only tab-switch + Claude hook <code>fileChanged</code>). Dirty repos on startup show the button immediately; manual <code>git add</code> / <code>git commit</code> / external editor workflows flip the button live without needing Claude hooks.</li>
          <li><code>ClaudeIntegration::setShellPid</code> calls <code>pollClaudeProcess()</code> immediately on PID change so the status label reflects the new tab within one event-loop iteration rather than being <code>NotRunning</code> for up to 2 s until the next timer tick.</li>
          <li><code>ClaudeAllowlistDialog::saveSettings</code> now returns <code>bool</code>; all three callers (prompt-prefill, OK, Apply) surface failure to the user via status message or validation label. Previously every open/write/commit failure was swallowed and the button appeared to do nothing.</li>
          <li>Add-to-Allowlist button is now prompt-scoped in both creation paths: the hook-server button-group QWidget has <code>objectName "claudeAllowBtn"</code> matching the scroll-scan path, so <code>onTabChanged</code> cleans up both; the hook-server path's cleared-listener covers every terminal (not just <code>currentTerminal()</code>) so approving on the originating tab after a brief visit to another still clears the button.</li>
          <li><code>showDiffViewer</code> replaces every silent <code>return</code> with an explicit status message so the Review Changes button can't click through to nothing — previously a failed <code>focusedTerminal</code>, empty <code>shellCwd</code>, or non-zero git exit all disappeared without feedback. Combined <code>git diff HEAD</code> in a single invocation (covers worktree + index) rather than two.</li>
          <li>New <code>tests/features/status_bar_elision</code> feature test locks the short-text-never-elides invariant inside a real QMainWindow + QStatusBar harness; fails against pre-fix <code>ElidedLabel</code>, passes on fix.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.28" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>End-to-end feature review — same-class overflow sweep across the status bar, title bar, and audit dialog; quake-mode toggle fix; combining-character preservation on resize; disk-write durability hardening; auto-profile regex caching.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New <code>ElidedLabel</code> widget truncates long text with "…" to a bounded width. Applied to the three status-bar text slots (git branch, transient message, foreground process), the window title label, the Claude status label, and the audit-dialog status label — each previously grew unbounded and pushed siblings off-screen.</li>
          <li>Quake-mode toggle no longer auto-hides the window 200 ms after a show toggle. The reused <code>QPropertyAnimation</code>'s <code>finished→hide()</code> slot from a prior hide toggle was still connected on the show branch; the slot is now disconnected before every <code>start()</code> and re-attached only on the hide branch.</li>
          <li>Terminal resize preserves the per-line combining-character side table on both main and alt screens. Pre-0.6.28 every resize wiped accents, ZWJ sequences, and diacritics because the simple-copy path walked cells only. Shrink cases cleanly evict combining entries whose column falls outside the new width. New <code>tests/features/combining_on_resize</code> feature test pins the three invariants.</li>
          <li>Config and session writes now <code>fsync()</code> the temp file before atomic rename, closing the kernel-crash data-loss window on ext4 <code>data=ordered</code>.</li>
          <li>Auto-profile rule regex is cached across the 2 s poll tick instead of recompiled per-rule-per-tick, and invalid patterns are detected via <code>QRegularExpression::isValid()</code> and warned once rather than silently never matching.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.27" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Seventh release in the 0.6 UX polish pass — ncurses <code>clear</code> scrollback fix, scroll-offset clamp, tab-close visibility, Claude "prompting" state.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ncurses <code>clear</code> now correctly wipes scrollback on <code>TERM=xterm-256color</code>. The 0.6.26 Ink-overflow-repaint heuristic was false-matching the byte-burst because <code>clear</code>'s <code>\E[H\E[2J\E[3J</code> sequence overlaps with Ink's <code>clearTerminal</code>. Disambiguated via cursor position at <code>3J</code> time — <code>clear</code> emits <code>H</code> first so the cursor sits at (0,0); Ink emits <code>H</code> last so the cursor is at the bottom.</li>
          <li>Scroll-to-bottom button no longer lingers when scrollback shrinks. <code>m_scrollOffset</code> is now re-clamped in the single <code>updateScrollBar()</code> choke-point after every output batch.</li>
          <li>Tab close (×) button is always visible — removed the stylesheet rule that hid the glyph and left only an invisible hover hit-target.</li>
          <li>Claude status bar now shows "Claude: prompting" when a permission prompt is waiting, even if the transcript-driven state still reports idle/thinking. Critical when the user is scrolled up in history and can't see the live prompt.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.26" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>UX polish pass — status bar consistency, focus handling, Ink overflow-repaint fix, and tab colour gradient.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Claude Code (Ink/React TUI) overflow-repaint no longer destroys scrollback or duplicates the replay. <code>CSI 2J</code> followed within 50 ms by <code>CSI 3J</code> on the main screen is now treated as Ink's <code>clearTerminal</code> frame-reset marker (see <code>ink/build/ink.js:705</code>) rather than a user-initiated scrollback wipe — scrollback is preserved and the suppression window is armed for the subsequent replay. Standalone <code>CSI 3J</code> (user-initiated <code>clear -x</code>) still wipes scrollback as expected. Two new feature-conformance scenarios assert both behaviours.</li>
          <li>Status bar is now height-stable. <code>QStatusBar</code>'s size hint had been tracking its tallest child, so the bar grew when the transient "Add to allowlist" button appeared and shrank when it went away. A 32 px minimum-height floor keeps the bar consistent whether or not a button is attached.</li>
          <li>"Review Changes" status-bar button now matches the sibling "Add to allowlist" button's enabled look — it inherits the global <code>QPushButton</code> style instead of its own custom stylesheet (the 0.6.26 "bold to fix Gruvbox contrast" attempt made lowercase letters squish into a small-caps look on Fusion + monospace). Disabled state gets its own visual language (dashed border, italic, muted fg) so a clean-repo state reads clearly as non-actionable.</li>
          <li>Git branch chip now has a hard vertical divider separating it from the transient-status slot, visible on low-contrast themes where the chip's rounded-background treatment was indistinguishable from the status bar background.</li>
          <li>Focus auto-returns to the active terminal whenever focus lands on chrome widgets (status bar buttons, tab bar) with no dialog open. Clicking a status bar button, answering a prompt, etc., no longer leaves the keyboard parked on the button.</li>
          <li>Claude Code context-usage progress bar is hidden until the first real (non-zero) context percentage arrives. A fresh tab, or a tab where Claude was never started, no longer paints a persistent "0%" widget.</li>
          <li>Tab-colour badge replaced with a vertical gradient (transparent top → chosen colour bottom). The active-tab 2 px accent underline is preserved by excluding the bottom two pixels from the gradient area.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.25" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>User-reported scrollback regression fix plus packaging-rule hardening.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Scrolled-up viewport no longer shifts when streaming content arrives. The 0.6.21 pause and 0.6.22/0.6.24 CSI-clear window both skipped scrollback pushes, which froze the scroll anchor and let screen-scroll mechanics bleed into the user's viewport. Fix: push to scrollback while the user is scrolled up (anchor adjusts <code>m_scrollOffset</code> to compensate); the doubling-protection window still fires for the at-bottom case where the doubling symptom is observable.</li>
          <li>Extended the <code>packaging-version-drift</code> audit rule to scan <code>org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml</code>. The file's <code>&lt;release version=&gt;</code> entry is version-coupled to every release but was not previously checked. Flagged by the ninth periodic audit (2026-04-15).</li>
          <li>Extracted the drift-check logic into <code>packaging/check-version-drift.sh</code> — a standalone script that is the single source of truth. Both <code>src/auditdialog.cpp</code> and the CI workflow invoke the same script, so they can no longer drift apart.</li>
          <li>Wired the script into <code>.github/workflows/ci.yml</code> as a gating check; a PR that bumps CMakeLists.txt without updating every packaging file now fails CI instead of merging and requiring a follow-up tag.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.24" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Status-bar button-lifecycle and legibility fixes alongside the full-clear scrollback suppression extension.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Status-bar "Add to allowlist" button now persists for the full life of the Claude Code permission prompt — previously the button was retracted on the next repaint tick, vanishing within seconds of the prompt appearing.</li>
          <li>"Review Changes" button disabled-state text now readable on every theme. Previous textSecondary-based fix still failed WCAG AA on One Dark / Kanagawa; switched to textPrimary + italic + dissolved border so the label stays legible while still communicating the disabled state.</li>
          <li>Extended the 0.6.22 suppression window to <code>CSI H; CSI 0J</code> and corner-cursor <code>CSI 1J</code> — both produce the same post-state as <code>CSI 2J</code> and therefore exhibit the same doubling bug on TUI redraw bursts. Regression tests for both shapes added to <code>tests/features/scrollback_redraw/</code>.</li>
          <li>Packaging recipes (openSUSE spec, Arch PKGBUILD, Debian changelog, man page) bumped to 0.6.24 after drifting two releases behind — the exact drift the <code>packaging-version-drift</code> audit rule was written to catch.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.23" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Three user-reported UX fixes, an event-driven status-bar contract, and the first 0.7.0 performance item — SIMD VT-parser scan.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Allowlist "already covered" check no longer blocks legitimate compound rules — subsumption now splits on shell operators (<code>&amp;&amp;</code>, <code>||</code>, <code>;</code>, <code>|</code>) and requires every segment to match before declaring coverage.</li>
          <li>Right-click tab colour picker now renders visibly — a new <code>ColoredTabBar</code> paints a 3-px strip outside stylesheet influence (was defeated by QSS specificity).</li>
          <li>Status bar clears event-scoped transients (Allow buttons, notifications) on tab switch so state from one tab never leaks into another.</li>
          <li>Fixed a Shift+Enter paste-image regression.</li>
          <li>SIMD ground-state scan (SSE2 / NEON) — bulk <code>Print</code> emission on runs of safe printable-ASCII, with byte-identical action-stream regression guards.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.22" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Root-cause fix for main-screen TUI scrollback doubling, plus packaging catch-up across all recipes.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Scrollback no longer accumulates duplicates when a main-screen TUI (Claude Code v2.1+) repaints via <code>CSI 2J</code> — a 250 ms sliding window now suppresses scrollback pushes during the repaint burst.</li>
          <li>Packaging recipes (openSUSE spec, Arch PKGBUILD, Debian changelog) bumped to 0.6.22 after drifting three releases behind.</li>
          <li>openSUSE spec gains <code>%post</code>/<code>%postun</code> scriptlets for desktop-database and icon-cache refresh.</li>
          <li>Debian gains <code>postinst</code>/<code>postrm</code> scripts for the same purpose.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.21" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Audit-tool noise reduction, dialog theming, and a scrollback-insert pause for users actively reading history while a TUI repaints.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed a GNU grep 3.12 argument-ordering quirk that silently disabled the audit's <code>--include</code> file-type filter.</li>
          <li>Extended the QSS cascade so every popup dialog inherits the terminal's active theme.</li>
          <li>Added a scrollback-insert pause that stops TUI redraws from interleaving intermediate frames into the user's reading position.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.20" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-adoption bundle H5: OBS, AUR, and Debian packaging recipes.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.19" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H4: bash, zsh, and fish shell completions plus CMake install rules.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.18" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H3: ants-terminal(1) man page with CMake install rule.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.17" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H2: AppStream metainfo and spec-compliant desktop entry.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added <code>org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml</code> for GNOME Software and KDE Discover discovery.</li>
          <li>Added <code>org.ants.Terminal.desktop</code> following the reverse-DNS naming convention.</li>
          <li>CMake install rules for desktop entry, metainfo, and hicolor-theme icons at six sizes.</li>
          <li>CI validates packaging artefacts with <code>appstreamcli</code> and <code>desktop-file-validate</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.16" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H1: community and security policy documents.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added <code>CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md</code> (Contributor Covenant 2.1) with dedicated reporting channels.</li>
          <li>Changelogged the previously shipped <code>SECURITY.md</code> coordinated-disclosure policy.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.15" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Incremental scrollback reflow with a fast path for standalone lines.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.14" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Security hardening — URI scheme allowlist in <code>addRowHyperlink</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
