<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  AppStream metainfo for Ants Terminal.

  Consumed by GNOME Software, KDE Discover, and distro appstream catalogues
  (Debian DEP-11, Fedora AppStream, openSUSE OBS, Arch pacman-contrib).
  The `id` matches the `.desktop` filename stem (reverse-DNS) so that
  `launchable` can tie the two together.

  Validate with:
    appstreamcli validate packaging/linux/org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml
    desktop-file-validate packaging/linux/org.ants.Terminal.desktop

  When cutting a release, add a new <release/> entry at the top of the
  <releases/> list (newest first) with version/date and a short summary
  of user-visible changes — distros surface this in the update-details UI.

  Screenshots live under docs/screenshots/ and are referenced below via
  raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/.
  Rename there + here in the same commit — URLs are literal.
-->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>org.ants.Terminal</id>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.ants.Terminal.desktop</launchable>

  <name>Ants Terminal</name>
  <summary>Modern, themeable terminal emulator with ligatures, inline images, and Lua plugins</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>

  <developer id="org.ants">
    <name>Ants Terminal Contributors</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Ants Terminal is a fast, feature-rich terminal emulator written from
      scratch in C++20 with Qt6. It targets the capabilities modern
      terminal users expect — true-color themes, ligatures, hyperlinks,
      inline images, and a scriptable plugin system — without dragging
      in a web runtime.
    </p>
    <p>Key features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Eleven built-in themes with full ANSI palette overrides, plus automatic dark/light switching that follows the system color scheme.</li>
      <li>Ligature-aware QPainter text shaping (HarfBuzz) with partial-rect updates for sub-millisecond redraws on noisy output.</li>
      <li>Inline images via Sixel, Kitty graphics protocol, and iTerm2 OSC 1337. Image paste auto-saves to disk — optimized for LLM / coding-agent workflows.</li>
      <li>Shell integration via OSC 133 (prompt jump, exit-status marks). OSC 8 hyperlinks, OSC 52 clipboard, OSC 9/777 desktop notifications, OSC 9;4 progress reporting.</li>
      <li>Kitty keyboard protocol with progressive enhancement, synchronized output, SGR mouse reporting, focus reporting.</li>
      <li>Embedded Lua 5.4 plugin system (sandboxed) with documented <code>ants.*</code> API. Session persistence saves scrollback across restarts.</li>
      <li>Built-in Project Audit panel: clazy + cppcheck + semgrep + regex rules with SARIF v2.1.0 export, AI-assisted triage, and confidence scoring.</li>
      <li>Configurable keybindings, command snippets, auto-profile rules, SSH bookmarks, and an OpenAI-compatible AI assistant dialog.</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <categories>
    <category>System</category>
    <category>TerminalEmulator</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>terminal</keyword>
    <keyword>console</keyword>
    <keyword>shell</keyword>
    <keyword>bash</keyword>
    <keyword>emulator</keyword>
    <keyword>tty</keyword>
    <keyword>command</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal</url>
  <url type="help">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/blob/main/README.md</url>
  <url type="contribute">https://github.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md</url>

  <provides>
    <binary>ants-terminal</binary>
  </provides>

  <supports>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>pointing</control>
  </supports>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Main terminal — custom title bar, tab gradient, status bar</caption>
      <image type="source" width="2103" height="1137">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/01-main-terminal.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Review Changes dialog — per-file diff and apply flow</caption>
      <image type="source" width="2110" height="1140">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/02-review-changes.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Project Audit panel — clazy, cppcheck, and grep findings with SARIF export</caption>
      <image type="source" width="2103" height="1137">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/milnet01/ants-terminal/main/docs/screenshots/03-project-audit.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.7.70" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle G Tier 2 heavy-items closeout. ANTS-1135 (post-fork setenv signal-safety: pre-fork envp build + execle in child, replacing the prior execlp+setenv-loop pattern that was not on POSIX async-signal-safe list); ANTS-1133 partial (CSI Pn I / Z / ` — CHT / CBT / HPA verbs added on top of REP from 0.7.69); ANTS-1139 partial (markdown bold rendered, tables render as &lt;table&gt; not &lt;pre&gt;); ANTS-1140 partial (reverseTopLevelSections cache).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.69" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle G Tier 2 final closeouts. ANTS-1134 (span cache invalidation across scrollback push), ANTS-1138 (auto-profile-rules pattern cache invalidation via generation counter), ANTS-1142 (KDE-presence guard lifted into shared kwinPresent() helper used by KWinPositionTracker + moveViaKWin + centerWindow), ANTS-1144 (Claude transcript render cap at last 2000 entries). ANTS-1133 partial — CSI Pn b (REP) handler shipped; other CSI-spec gaps remain deferred.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.68" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle G Tier 2 closeouts — knocking off the deferred sub-fixes annotated in 0.7.67. ANTS-1136 (5/5 — RuleQualityTracker durability), ANTS-1141 (5/5 — parent-dir fsync after rename), ANTS-1142 (3/4 — MainWindow listens to sessionFailed with status-bar fallback), ANTS-1144 (2/3 — BgTasks dialog ANSI/SGR/OSC strip in tail output).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.67" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle G Tier 2 progress sweep. 8 ANTS IDs touched: ANTS-1134 (modifier-only keypress guard), ANTS-1136 (audit pipeline doc + correctness — 4/5 sub-fixes), ANTS-1137 (MainWindow chrome perf), ANTS-1138 (applyTheme early-return), ANTS-1141 (Config + persistence — 4/5 sub-fixes), ANTS-1142 (Wayland portal + debug log — 2/4), ANTS-1143 (PLUGINS.md spec drift), ANTS-1144 (AI dialog partial-stream fail-closed — 1/3). Remaining Tier 2 sub-fixes deferred to 0.7.68 with explicit annotations in ROADMAP.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.66" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle G Tier 1 remainder. Two HIGH fixes from the 2026-05-01 indie-review sweep — ANTS-1131 (PTY child-process lifecycle: WNOHANG=0 orphan + m_planModeByPid PID-reuse poisoning) and ANTS-1132 (IPC socket trust-model gaps: SO_PEERCRED UID match on remote-control accept, UserAccessOption + lstat-checked S_ISSOCK precheck on Claude hook + MCP server starts, per-connection idle timeout). Tier 2 + Tier 3 follow in subsequent bumps.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.65" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle G Tier 1 fix-pass. Two CRITICAL fixes from the 2026-05-01 multi-agent indie-review sweep — ANTS-1118 (smooth-scroll snapshot race during streaming, root cause identified by the terminal-widget-paint reviewer) and ANTS-1130 (VT alt-screen + scroll-region invariants — DECSET 47/1047/1049 conflation, resize() destroying DECSTBM, alt scroll-region OOB on shrink-resize). Two more Tier 1 items (ANTS-1131 PTY child lifecycle + ANTS-1132 IPC socket trust gaps) defer to 0.7.66 to keep this release's blast radius small.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Smooth-scroll snapshot race — wheelEvent now triggers snapshot capture + scrollback-insertion pause on user scroll INTENT rather than committed offset transition. Closes a 16–32 ms race window where the first smoothScrollStep tick produced no offset change, letting onVtBatch mutate visible viewport rows before the snapshot was captured. (ANTS-1118)</li>
          <li>VT alt-screen + scroll-region invariants — split DECSET 47/1047/1049 (only 1049 carries DECSC semantics per xterm ctlseqs); resize() preserves DECSTBM by clamping existing scroll region to the new row range instead of resetting to fullscreen; alt scroll-region clamped symmetrically (previously unclamped — could leave m_altScrollBottom > m_rows-1 and produce OOB reads on next scrollUp after exit-from-alt). (ANTS-1130)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.64" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Companion partial closeouts pre-Bundle-G. ANTS-1106 ships the Roadmap viewer's Kind-faceted secondary filter — the last half of the "mandatory Kind: field + viewer faceted categorisation" item, with the field-required half having landed in 0.7.59 alongside the standards doc update. Three status hygiene flips for ANTS-1116 v1 (<code>ants-helper drift-check</code>) and ANTS-1117 v1 (<code>roadmap-query</code> + <code>tab-list</code> IPC verbs) — both shipped in 0.7.59 but the status emoji never flipped. ANTS-1118 reframed from HIGH to MEDIUM after the user confirmed the bug downgraded post-0.7.63 (still a temporary visual artifact, but the scrollback buffer itself is intact).</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Roadmap viewer Kind-faceted filter — a new Kind row in RoadmapDialog underneath the existing status-checkbox row, with one toggle per Kind value (12 total — the 10 spec-defined plus the de-facto research / ux values). OR-include semantics across the active Kinds; bullets without a Kind: line are excluded under non-empty filters. (ANTS-1106)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ROADMAP status flips for ANTS-1116 v1 + ANTS-1117 v1 — both shipped in 0.7.59; the status emoji never flipped. v2 of each (MCP server wrapper + audit-run IPC verb) explicitly stays deferred per their specs, gated on ANTS-1120 measurement validation.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ANTS-1118 severity downgraded HIGH → MEDIUM after user confirmation — scrollback buffer is intact, visible artifact is a paint-cycle race during streaming. Folded into Bundle G (full /audit + /indie-review) as a candidate finding for the multi-agent fresh-eyes pass.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.63" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Outstanding-queue cleanup pre-Bundle-G (full /audit + /indie-review). ANTS-1014 clipboard-write redaction lands as the one real code fix — centralises 15 raw <code>setText(...)</code> sites behind a single hygiene funnel, with OSC 52 (the headline exfil vector flagged by the 7th-audit memory) and Lua plugin <code>ants.clipboard.write</code> getting a 1 MiB cap + NUL strip while user-initiated copy actions pass through unchanged. Two regressions get explicit "awaiting repro" status flips so the upcoming review pass doesn't re-flag them as untreated bugs, and six big items get explicit deferral annotations with re-evaluation triggers so orphan planned bullets read as deferred-by-design rather than forgotten.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Clipboard-write redaction funnel — new <code>src/clipboardguard.{h,cpp}</code> module with a pure <code>sanitize(text, source)</code> helper splitting on a <code>Source</code> enum (<code>Trusted</code> / <code>UntrustedPty</code> / <code>UntrustedPlugin</code>). Untrusted sources cap at 1 MiB; all sources strip <code>QChar(0)</code>. All 15 raw <code>QApplication::clipboard()-&gt;setText(...)</code> sites in <code>terminalwidget.cpp</code> + <code>mainwindow.cpp</code> converted with appropriate source classifications. (ANTS-1014)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ROADMAP outstanding-queue cleanup — ANTS-1052 + ANTS-1118 flipped to "Awaiting user repro" status; ANTS-1043 / 1044 / 1003-1006 / 1107 / 1108 / 1115 annotated with explicit deferral rationale + re-evaluation triggers.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.62" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Bundle B of the pre-0.7.61 outstanding-item triage — two small UX wins that close ROADMAP carryover. The update-available indicator moves out of the status bar onto the menu bar so the one-shot "you have a new version" call-to-action reads as visually loud chrome instead of competing with the steady-state widgets, and the git-branch chip on the status bar gains a colour cue (green for main/master/trunk, amber for everything else) that pairs it visually with the existing "Public/Private" repo-visibility pill next to it.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Update-available indicator promoted from a status-bar <code>QLabel</code> to a top-level menu-bar <code>QAction</code>, inserted to the right of <code>&amp;Help</code>. URL is stashed via <code>QAction::setData</code>; the <code>triggered</code> lambda replays it through the existing <code>handleUpdateClicked</code> slot — same in-place AppImageUpdate flow, same Update / Skip / Postpone dialog. Status bar reclaims its rightmost slot for steady-state telemetry. (ANTS-1124)</li>
          <li>Git-branch chip on the status bar gains a branch-derived colour cue. New pure helper <code>branchchip::isPrimaryBranch</code> returns true for <code>main</code> / <code>master</code> / <code>trunk</code>, false for every other ref. Both styling sites (<code>applyTheme</code> for theme switches, <code>updateStatusBar</code> for per-poll branch changes) consult the helper and pick <code>theme.ansi[2]</code> (green, same role as the "Public" visibility pill) or <code>theme.ansi[3]</code> (amber, same role as "Private"). Visually pairs the chip with the pill; functionally tells the user at a glance whether they are on the project's primary branch. (ANTS-1109)</li>
          <li>ROADMAP.md status flips for ANTS-1100 (<code>RoadmapDialog</code> faceted-tabs redesign) and ANTS-1119 (<code>AuditEngine</code> extraction) — both shipped in 0.7.59, status emoji never flipped. ANTS-1049 body trimmed to a "subsumed by ANTS-1044" note (same scope as the structural-tier <code>auditdialog.cpp</code> decomposition).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Test <code>tests/features/github_status_bar/</code> updated to reflect the ANTS-1124 migration: INV-1, INV-2, INV-11 now assert the new <code>QAction</code> shape plus a negative regression check that no <code>m_updateAvailableLabel</code> identifier survives anywhere in <code>mainwindow.{h,cpp}</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.61" date="2026-04-30">
      <description>
        <p>Dialog-and-roadmap polish bundle — fixes three user-visible chrome bugs (theme propagation to dialogs, focus-return on dialog close, pseudo-modal click-blocking on the parent), splits the now-260 KiB ROADMAP.md by minor version so tooling can keep up, retires two long-deprecated standards docs, and folds in a batch of indie-review Tier-3 closures.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Per-version ROADMAP archive — closed minors rotate to <code>docs/roadmap/&lt;MAJOR&gt;.&lt;MINOR&gt;.md</code> via <code>packaging/rotate-roadmap.sh</code>. The viewer pulls archives in only on demand (History preset OR non-empty search). Numeric <code>(major, minor)</code> descending sort defeats the lexical-sort trap at minor 10. Per-file 8 MiB cap + total 64 MiB cap. Initial archives at 0.5.md and 0.6.md. (ANTS-1125)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Theme stylesheet now reaches top-level dialogs. Switched <code>MainWindow::applyTheme</code> from <code>setStyleSheet(ss)</code> on the MainWindow instance to <code>qApp-&gt;setStyleSheet(ss)</code> — Qt's stylesheet engine only propagates through a widget's render subtree, not through QObject parent-child relationships, so top-level QDialogs never inherited the theme. All 9 dialog classes plus 7 ad-hoc <code>new QDialog(this)</code> instances now match. (ANTS-1128)</li>
          <li>Auto-return focus to terminal when any dialog closes. The qApp eventFilter gained a Close-event branch backed by a pure-logic helper <code>dialogfocus::shouldRefocusOnDialogClose</code>; refocus is deferred via <code>QTimer::singleShot(0)</code> so the dialog teardown completes first. Stacked-dialog suppression and early-startup null-guard included. (ANTS-1050)</li>
          <li>Pseudo-modal blocking on the parent. 0.7.50 made all dialogs non-modal to dodge QTBUG-79126 on Wayland; click-blocking restored manually via <code>dialogfocus::shouldSuppressEventForDialog</code>. Mouse / key / wheel events landing outside any visible dialog's tree are swallowed. (ANTS-1051)</li>
          <li>Menubar dropdown flicker confirmed resolved by the 0.7.5 NoAnimStyle plus HoverMove suppression — the KWin-side experimentation hypothesis didn't materialise. (ANTS-1058)</li>
          <li>XcbPositionTracker renamed to KWinPositionTracker (the class talks to KWin's scripting D-Bus interface, not XCB). KDE-presence guard bails before any temp-file write on non-KDE compositors. <code>QScopeGuard</code> ensures the temp script is removed on every synchronous failure path. (ANTS-1045)</li>
          <li>Post-fork heap allocations in flatpak-spawn argv build retired. Detection plus <code>snprintf</code> into stack buffers now happens pre-fork; the child only assembles a stack-allocated argv table and calls <code>execvp</code> — strictly POSIX async-signal-safe. (ANTS-1046)</li>
          <li>RoadmapDialog::rebuild's <code>readAll</code> now caps at 8 MiB; <code>refreshReviewButton</code> deduplicates overlapping <code>git status</code> probes via <code>m_reviewProbeInFlight</code>. (ANTS-1012, ANTS-1013)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Removed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Deprecated top-level <code>STANDARDS.md</code> and <code>RULES.md</code> retired (user-authorised). Both predated the <code>docs/standards/</code> bundle and duplicated content. Live references updated across CONTRIBUTING.md, PLUGINS.md, README.md, and the audit dialog's "Review with Claude" header. (ANTS-1105)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.60" date="2026-04-30">
      <description>
        <p>ANTS-1123 indie-review Tier 2 + Tier 3 fold-in — the remaining hardening + polish bullets from the 0.7.59 4-agent independent review of the Claude Code companion features. Cache contract on the <code>roadmap-query</code> IPC verb honours the spec "≤ 100 ms" budget literally; <code>ants-helper</code> rejects malformed JSON input shapes; <code>AuditEngine::parseFindings</code> no longer emits bogus SARIF locators for version-string tokens; RoadmapDialog gracefully handles a corrupt persisted geometry blob and preserves user state on Custom-tab clicks. CLAUDE.md streamlined.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><code>ants-helper</code> now rejects non-object JSON request bodies (<code>[]</code>, <code>42</code>, <code>"foo"</code>) with a usage-error envelope instead of silently treating them as <code>{}</code>; stdin-open failure surfaces a usage error rather than degrading to empty input. (F6, F7)</li>
          <li><code>parseFindings</code> regex tightened to require an alphabetic-led extension — bare version-string locators like <code>cargo/1.75</code> no longer create bogus SARIF <code>physicalLocation</code> entries. Short-circuited the per-line regex chain (was matching three regexes per line; now one). (M1, L1)</li>
          <li><code>roadmap-query</code> cache now honours the spec INV-10 "≤ 100 ms" wall-clock bound on top of the existing mtime check, so an in-place edit within the same mtime tick is still picked up. (F1)</li>
          <li>Roadmap dialog: corrupt persisted geometry blob is now cleared instead of masquerading as valid forever; clicking the "Custom" tab preserves user checkbox tuning and sort order; tab-order array gained a <code>static_assert</code> against the <code>Preset</code> enum size. (LOW-1, LOW-2, LOW-3)</li>
          <li>ANTS-1117 spec § Error-response shape rewritten to the flat-envelope convention (<code>{ok:true, bullets:[...]}</code>) the codebase actually ships — earlier nested-on-<code>data</code> wording was the outlier. (F9)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.59" date="2026-04-30">
      <description>
        <p>Claude Code companion features — faceted preset tabs and search on the Roadmap viewer (ANTS-1100), two read-only IPC verbs Claude can drive (tab-list, roadmap-query; ANTS-1117 v1), an optional standalone CLI helper (ants-helper drift-check; ANTS-1116 v1), an audit-engine extraction that unblocks future non-GUI audit consumers (ANTS-1119 v1), and a measurement gate that grounds further companion work in real token counts (ANTS-1120). Bundled with documentation cold-eyes review (ANTS-1121), audit fold-in fixes (ANTS-1122), and Tier 1 indie-review fixes (ANTS-1123).</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Roadmap dialog faceted preset tabs — Full / History / Current / Next / Far Future / Custom — each mapping to a (filter, sort) preset evaluated in pure C++. New search box accepts substring or <code>id:NNNN</code> shorthand to jump to a specific bullet. Default size 1200×800 with persisted geometry round-trip via <code>Config::roadmapDialogGeometry</code>. (ANTS-1100)</li>
          <li>Two new remote-control IPC verbs (read-only): <code>roadmap-query</code> returns parsed ROADMAP bullets (id, status, headline, kind, lanes); <code>tab-list</code> returns rich per-tab snapshots (index, title, cwd, shell_pid, claude_running, color). Both inherit the existing UID-scoped trust check. (ANTS-1117 v1)</li>
          <li>Optional <code>ants-helper</code> CLI binary (built when CMake is invoked with <code>-DANTS_ENABLE_HELPER_CLI=ON</code>). v1 ships <code>ants-helper drift-check</code>, which wraps <code>packaging/check-version-drift.sh</code> and emits a unified JSON envelope Claude can parse without re-interpreting the script's stdout. Builds against Qt6::Core only. (ANTS-1116 v1)</li>
          <li><code>AuditEngine</code> GUI-free module — the data-shape types and three pure parsing functions extracted from <code>auditdialog.cpp</code> into <code>src/auditengine.{h,cpp}</code> depending on Qt6::Core only. Pure refactor; audit pipeline output is byte-identical pre/post. Unblocks future non-GUI audit consumers. (ANTS-1119 v1)</li>
          <li>Companion-instrumentation harness (ANTS-1120) — <code>scripts/measure-companion-tokens.sh</code> skeleton plus journal placeholder for measuring per-call token savings of the helper-stub vs baseline configurations before any further companion bullets ship.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><code>Kind:</code> field is now required on every actionable ROADMAP.md bullet (previously optional, inferred from section context). All 100 unannotated bullets backfilled. Spec updated at <code>docs/standards/roadmap-format.md § 3.5</code> and synced to the user-level <code>/start-app</code> template. (ANTS-1106)</li>
          <li>Documentation tree refresh (ANTS-1121, full-app cold-eyes review): retired GPU-renderer references from STANDARDS.md / RULES.md / PLUGINS.md (the <code>glrenderer.cpp</code> path was removed in 0.7.44); refreshed version stamps across PLUGINS.md, SECURITY.md, packaging/README.md, README.md, and CONTRIBUTING.md; relocated archival snapshots (DISCOVERY.md, AUDIT.md, FIXPLAN.md, project_audit_updates.md) from project root to <code>docs/journal/</code> with historical-snapshot headers; retired the stale <code>docs/AUTOMATED_AUDIT_REPORT.md</code> copy.</li>
          <li>Audit-engine fold-in fixes (ANTS-1122) — clazy <code>range-loop-detach</code> in <code>antshelper.cpp</code> and <code>roadmapdialog.cpp::parseBullets</code>; cppcheck <code>constVariablePointer</code> in <code>auditengine.cpp::applyFilter</code>; cppcheck <code>returnByReference</code> on <code>MainWindow::roadmapPathForRemote()</code>. Strengthened <code>tests/features/roadmap_viewer_tabs/</code> with negative-case and parsed-numeric invariants.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Section-reference drift in newly-authored specs — <code>docs/specs/ANTS-1117.md</code>, <code>docs/specs/ANTS-1120.md</code>, and <code>docs/decisions/0002-cold-eyes-companion-cleanup.md</code> cited <code>§ 1.2</code> / <code>§ 3.1</code> / <code>§ 3.5</code> for facts that actually live in <code>§ 3.3</code> (status emojis) and <code>§ 3.5.1</code> (stable-ID immutability). Corrected during the cold-eyes cross-check pass.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>regex-DoS divergence closed. Pre-0.7.59 the engine extraction had left two independent definitions of <code>isCatastrophicRegex</code> / <code>hardenUserRegex</code> between <code>auditengine.cpp</code> and <code>auditdialog.cpp</code> with differing LIMIT_MATCH values (200000 vs 100000), no double-prefix guard on the engine version, and shape detectors that caught different sets of catastrophic-backtracking patterns. A pattern that triggered the bound on one path could slip through on the other. Unified to a single definition exported from the engine; both call sites delegate. (ANTS-1123 indie-review C1+C2+C3+H1)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.58" date="2026-04-30">
      <description>
        <p>Runtime toggle for the ANTS-1054 dialog tracer. The 0.7.57 env-var-only path required restarting Ants Terminal to diagnose the user-reported mystery flashing dialogs; the new menu action lets the user enable / disable the tracer mid-session without losing tab state.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Tools → Debug Mode → "Trace dialog show events" — checkable menu action that toggles the same DialogShowTracer the ANTS_TRACE_DIALOGS=1 env var path installs. Output goes to stderr (always) and to the events debug-log category when enabled. Status-bar transient confirms the toggle. (ANTS-1054 follow-up)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>DialogShowTracer extracted from src/main.cpp to its own src/dialogshowtracer.{h,cpp} translation unit so both the startup env-var path and the runtime menu toggle call one setActive(bool) entry point. Process-global instance is parented to qApp; idempotent install / uninstall.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.57" date="2026-04-30">
      <description>
        <p>Indie-review backlog cleanup — surgical Tier 3 fixes (shellQuote whitelist, claudeChildrenOf extraction), a diagnostic for the mystery flashing-dialog report, a cppcheck returnByReference perf sweep, and a ROADMAP audit that flipped 28 prior indie-review items from planned to done once verified shipped in 0.7.52–0.7.55.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ANTS_TRACE_DIALOGS=1 env var installs a DialogShowTracer event filter on the QApplication. Logs every top-level QWidget/QDialog Show event with className, objectName, windowTitle, parent, and geometry to stderr. Diagnostic step (a) of ANTS-1054 — the user reported a small popup flashing periodically in the centre of the terminal; the trace attributes the next occurrence to either an Ants spawn site (logged) or a child process (silent trace). Zero cost when the env var is unset.</li>
          <li>tests/features/shellutils_whitelist/ — feature test for the ANTS-1047 fix. Verifies four invariants: empty input maps to '', the whitelist [A-Za-z0-9_-./:@%+,] passes through, anything outside it forces single-quote wrapping (specifically the glob/redirection/bracket characters the old denylist missed), and embedded single quotes round-trip via the POSIX 'X'\''Y' form.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ClaudeIntegration::findClaudeChildPid(pid_t) — extracted from the two near-identical /proc/&lt;pid&gt;/task/&lt;pid&gt;/children walks in pollClaudeProcess and ClaudeTabTracker::detectClaudeChild. Both call sites share one helper; detectClaudeChild also gains the /proc-scan fallback that previously only pollClaudeProcess had. (ANTS-1048)</li>
          <li>Cppcheck returnByReference perf sweep across seven hot getters: Config::loadFailureBackupPath, ClaudeBgTaskTracker::transcriptPath, GhostLineEdit::ghostSuffix, TerminalGrid::windowTitle, TerminalWidget::shellTitle, TerminalWidget::imagePasteDir, PluginManager::pluginDir. Each was returning a QString by value — now returns const QString&amp;.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>shellutils.h::shellQuote switched from a denylist regex to a whitelist regex. The denylist missed glob wildcards (*, ?), redirection (&lt;, &gt;), and bracket-expansion specials ([, ]); a path containing any of those reached the shell unquoted and underwent globbing. Whitelist closes the class — anything outside [A-Za-z0-9_-./:@%+,] gets single-quote wrapped. Affects every caller of shellQuote — mainwindow.cpp claude-launch builders and sshdialog.cpp ssh-argv construction. (ANTS-1047)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ROADMAP.md hygiene — flipped 28 [ANTS-1015..1042, 1047, 1048] bullets from planned to done after verifying each item shipped in the 0.7.52–0.7.55 cycle (or in this 0.7.57 bundle). Each done bullet now cites the shipped version and the source-comment line. ANTS-1054 flipped to in-progress with the diagnostic-shipped note. Tier 3 refactors ANTS-1043, 1044, 1045, 1046, 1049 remain planned (large-scope items deferred).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.56" date="2026-04-30">
      <description>
        <p>App-Build suite alignment — confirm-on-close for tabs running non-shell processes, four-doc shareable standards bundle synced to the user-level /start-app template, CI-blocking metainfo escape fix, and the strategic roadmap for incorporating the App-Build workflow natively into Ants Terminal so users can run as much of it as possible without spending Claude tokens.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Confirm-on-close for tabs running non-shell processes (vim, top, claude, tail -f, ...). Wayland-correct non-modal dialog names the process; "Don't ask again" checkbox flips Config::confirmCloseWithProcesses to false. Default on. Probe walks /proc/&lt;pid&gt;/task/&lt;pid&gt;/children transitively (cap 256 visited PIDs) against an 11-shell allowlist (bash/zsh/fish/sh/ksh/dash/ash/tcsh/csh/mksh/yash). Locked by 11 invariants in tests/features/confirm_close_with_processes/.</li>
          <li>Reopen-closed-tab via Ctrl+Shift+Z — surfaced as already-shipped during the confirm-on-close pass; m_closedTabs deque (cap 10) plus File → Undo Close Tab.</li>
          <li>Four-document shareable standards bundle at docs/standards/ (coding · documentation · testing · commits) plus an index README, with the detailed ROADMAP/CHANGELOG format spec carried as a sub-spec at docs/standards/roadmap-format.md. Commits standard mandates &lt;ID&gt;: &lt;description&gt; subjects; testing standard mandates TDD by default.</li>
          <li>ADR scaffolding at docs/decisions/ (Michael Nygard format) plus docs/specs/ and docs/journal/ placeholder folders.</li>
          <li>Roadmap for incorporating the App-Build workflow natively into Ants Terminal (ANTS-1108) — Workflow panel that runs the mechanical 70 % of the per-phase 9-step loop in C++ (ID allocation, /audit, ctest, drift checks, /debt-sweep, /bump, /release, fold-in templating, atomic CHANGELOG/ROADMAP edits) with zero LLM round-trips.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ROADMAP masthead now points to docs/standards/roadmap-format.md for the format spec; docs/standards/ is now byte-identical to the user-level /start-app template, with per-language idiom examples and push-policy details delegated to the global ~/.claude/CLAUDE.md.</li>
          <li>README.md project-structure tree adds docs/standards/, docs/decisions/, docs/specs/, docs/journal/; flags STANDARDS.md / RULES.md as deprecated (retire under ANTS-1105 with explicit user confirmation).</li>
          <li>Roadmap-dialog redesign refined per user feedback — tabs now Full / History / Current / Next / Far Future, search field above the TOC, default size bumped to ~1200x800 with persisted geometry.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>CHANGELOG.md was missing a top-level [Unreleased] block that the Roadmap dialog reads for current-work signaling.</li>
          <li>Unescaped &amp; in the 0.7.55 metainfo &lt;release&gt; body broke appstreamcli validate and turned CI red on every commit since the release. Now &amp;amp;.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.55" date="2026-04-28">
      <description>
        <p>VT parser correctness + audit-dialog hardening from the 2026-04-27 indie-review. Six fixes — multi-row OSC 8 hyperlink span emission, ITU/ECMA-48 colon-RGB form parsing, audit comment-suppress hyphen handling, trend-snapshot dedup, bg-tasks liveness sweep split from full reparse, and a hot-path returnByReference fix.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Multi-row OSC 8 hyperlink spans miscoded. Pre-fix a hyperlink that wrapped to multiple rows stored only a single span on the start row with the wrong endCol; now emits per-row spans on close. Pre-0.7.55 shape preserved for single-row spans + the resize-pushed-text-to-scrollback edge case.</li>
          <li>ITU/ECMA-48 colon-RGB form 38:2::r:g:b dropped a channel. Parser now detects the 4-slot colon group (colorspace + R + G + B) and reads R/G/B from the right offsets. Legacy 38;2;r;g;b and 3-slot 38:2:r:g:b continue unchanged.</li>
          <li>Audit comment-suppress regex mis-handled hyphenated rule IDs (// nosemgrep: bash-c-non-literal matched only bash). Terminator class shrunk to [)\]]|$; hyphenated IDs now suppress correctly.</li>
          <li>Trend snapshot duplicated on every UI filter click. Gated by m_snapshotPersisted (reset in runAudit, set on first authoritative render). Re-renders triggered by severity-pill toggles skip the append.</li>
          <li>bg-tasks: split liveness sweep from full transcript reparse. Added sweepLiveness() that walks m_tasks via stat() calls + mtime check; the 2 s status-timer drives this cheap sweep instead of the 16 MiB transcript reparse. File-watcher continues to drive full rescan() on transcript-changed.</li>
          <li>ClaudeBgTaskTracker::tasks() returned by value on the hot path. cppcheck-flagged returnByReference. Now returns const &amp;.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.54" date="2026-04-28">
      <description>
        <p>A11y + UX bundle from the 2026-04-27 indie-review. Six fixes — accessibility plumbing on status-bar surfaces and ToggleSwitch, plan-mode persistence across tab switches, an SSE iteration cap to prevent UI freeze on misbehaving AI endpoints, and IPv6 support in the SSH Quick Connect parser.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>A11y — status-bar QLabels gain setAccessibleName. Branch chip, repo visibility, foreground-process, status-message slot, Claude session label, context bar, Review Changes button. Screen readers (Orca / NVDA / VoiceOver) now announce semantic text instead of raw tab content or Powerline glyph codepoints. Claude session label additionally updates accessibleDescription on every state transition.</li>
          <li>A11y — ToggleSwitch a11y plumbing. Default accessibleName + QAccessibleStateChangeEvent on every check-state flip. Keyboard users now get immediate AT-SPI / UIAutomation confirmation when their toggle lands.</li>
          <li>Plan-mode survives tab switch. setShellPid used to reset m_planMode = false on every pid change; now caches per-pid plan-mode state and restores it across tab flips so the indicator doesn't flicker off→on.</li>
          <li>AI SSE parser caps per-tick iterations at 256 + re-arms via singleShot(0). Prevents UI freeze on misbehaving endpoints streaming millions of tiny lines in one buffer.</li>
          <li>SSH Quick Connect parses IPv6 host literals. [2001:db8::1]:2222 used to parse as host=[2001 port=0; now matches RFC 3986 §3.2.2 / OpenSSH command-line convention.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.53" date="2026-04-28">
      <description>
        <p>Tier-1 remainders + VT/paste/plugin hardening from the 2026-04-27 indie-review. Six security-class fixes — three completing the Tier-1 ship-this-week list (the OSC-ESC parser RCE-adjacent leak, X10 mouse UTF-8 corruption, Lua plugin permission allow-list/intersect drift), three from Tier-2 paste/image hardening.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>HIGH — VT parser dispatched OSC's trailing ESC byte as a real ESC sequence. A crafted OSC ending in `ESC c` triggered RIS (full terminal reset); `ESC D` triggered IND; etc. RCE-adjacent because OSC payloads can arrive from a hostile remote shell or trigger-rule expansion. Fixed at the C0 pre-handler — string-state ESC no longer transitions to Escape; new *StringEsc peek-states consume the trailing byte. Locked by tests/features/vt_osc_esc_discard/ (5 invariants × 11 sub-cases).</li>
          <li>HIGH — X10 mouse byte > 0xDF corrupted UTF-8 stream. Coordinates clamped to 223 in X10 mode. SGR mode unaffected.</li>
          <li>HIGH — Lua plugin permission allow-list + intersect missing. Manifest entries now filtered against knownPermissions() (clipboard.write, settings); prompt-result intersected with requested set before reaching engine.</li>
          <li>HIGH — Image-paste filename injection + path escape. m_imagePasteDir canonicalised + required under $HOME; UUID4 suffix on filename to prevent millisecond-collision clobbers.</li>
          <li>HIGH — Paste preview split on LF only. Bare \r terminator spoofed multi-line payload as single line. Now normalises \r\n + \r to \n for display; actual paste still writes bytes verbatim.</li>
          <li>HIGH — Bracketed-paste 8-bit C1 form \x9B[200~ not stripped. Now strips 7-bit (\x1B[), raw 8-bit (\x9B), and UTF-8-encoded 8-bit (\xC2\x9B) forms.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.52" date="2026-04-28">
      <description>
        <p>First Tier-1 sweep of the 2026-04-27 indie-review findings. Eight fixes covering CRITICAL data-loss / security regressions plus HIGH security-class hardening — <code>SessionManager</code> silent scrollback loss, the same Wayland modal-grab pattern from 0.7.50 lurking in the update-confirmation dialog, SARIF/HTML reports leaking secrets at 0644, and five smaller HIGH items. The user-reported GitHub repo-type chip regression is also resolved (verified visible).</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>CRITICAL — SessionManager silent data loss. saveSession + saveTabOrder used QFile::rename, which on POSIX refuses to overwrite an existing destination. Every session save AFTER the first silently failed: the .dat file held the original snapshot, .dat.tmp accumulated each new write, user scrollback never updated past the first save. Switched both to std::rename (POSIX rename(2) — atomic replace), mirroring the 0.7.12 Config fix. Errno logged on failure; orphaned .tmp removed.</li>
          <li>CRITICAL — Update-confirmation dialog same Wayland modal-grab regression as 0.7.50 About fix. handleUpdateClicked was a QMessageBox box(this); box.exec() — exactly the pattern that drops button clicks on KDE/KWin + frameless+translucent parent per QTBUG-79126 / QTBUG-90005. Converted to the proven non-modal QDialog + plain QPushButton + clicked→close shape, mirroring the 0.7.50 About-dialog fix.</li>
          <li>CRITICAL — SARIF / HTML export not atomic + 0644 perms. The reports embed every finding including any leaked secret surfaced by the gitleaks / secrets_scan rules. Switched to QSaveFile + commit() (atomic write-rename-fsync) plus setOwnerOnlyPerms (0600).</li>
          <li>HIGH — new-tab / launch IPC commands bypassed the send-text C0 filter. A same-UID attacker reaching the rc socket got ESC-sequence / OSC 52 / bracketed-paste primitives via a different command than the one that was hardened. Both now route through filterControlChars by default; both honour a raw:true opt-out.</li>
          <li>HIGH — OSC 8 file:// and ftp:// schemes removed from the hyperlink allowlist. xdg-open file:///foo.desktop autoexecutes via the desktop's .desktop handler (RCE-adjacent); ftp:// drops credentials in plaintext. Allowlist now covers only http/https/mailto.</li>
          <li>HIGH — SSH extraArgs quote-bypass on the dangerous-option allowlist. The previous regex split fractured quoted args, letting -o "ProxyCommand=…" silently bypass the case-insensitive ProxyCommand match. Switched to QProcess::splitCommand which mirrors POSIX shell quoting.</li>
          <li>HIGH — extractCwdFromTranscript unbounded readLine. Caps readLine at 64 KiB so a corrupted transcript with a multi-GiB single-line head doesn't OOM the process.</li>
          <li>HIGH — AI endpoint scheme allowlist (http/https only). Rejects file:// / gopher:// / bare-host schemes up-front rather than at request time when the body is already serialised.</li>
          <li>HIGH — openFileAtPath argv-injection via attacker-controlled paths starting with -. The helper prepends ./ to single-arg combined-path branches and inserts -- before the path on separate-arg branches.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>User reports resolved:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>GitHub Public/Private repo-type chip not showing — user confirmed via screenshot 2026-04-28 that the chip is now visible.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.51" date="2026-04-28">
      <description>
        <p>Hot-reload doesn't loop any more. Same-day follow-up to 0.7.50 — three reported symptoms (status bar permanently sticking at "Config reloaded from disk", Help → Check for Updates appearing to do nothing, Settings → Preferences not opening) all traced to a single root cause: <code>MainWindow::onConfigFileChanged</code> re-entering itself in an infinite inotify loop. The 0.7.31 attempt at fixing the same loop (<code>m_configWatcher->blockSignals(true/false)</code> bracketing) never worked because Qt reads inotify events from the event loop after the slot returns — outliving the <code>blockSignals</code> window. Fix is at the source: make the setters idempotent so the slot has nothing to re-trigger.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Config reload re-entered itself in an inotify loop. <code>Config::setTheme</code> unconditionally called <code>save()</code> even when the value matched, so any <code>applyTheme(m_config.theme())</code> from inside <code>onConfigFileChanged</code> rewrote the watched file → kernel inotify event → next event-loop tick re-emits <code>fileChanged</code> → slot re-enters → loop. <code>setTheme</code> now early-returns when the value matches, breaking the loop at its source. <code>onConfigFileChanged</code> additionally skips the no-op <code>applyTheme</code> call when the theme didn't change, and carries an <code>m_inConfigReload</code> re-entrancy flag (cleared via <code>QTimer::singleShot(0, ...)</code> so a save inside the slot is dropped but a subsequent genuine external edit is honored). The failed 0.7.31 <code>blockSignals</code> calls are removed. User-visible: status bar stops sticking, Help → Check for Updates produces a visible toast, Settings → Preferences opens. Locked down by tests/features/config_reload_loop_safety/ — INV-1 idempotent setter, INV-2 no-op skip, INV-3 re-entrancy guard, INV-4 failed blockSignals removed.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.50" date="2026-04-28">
      <description>
        <p>Round four on the same dialog-button bug — and the matching Roadmap-dialog Close button. Three prior fix attempts (0.7.22, 0.7.35, 0.7.49) each diagnosed a downstream symptom rather than the actual root cause; this release identifies it from upstream Qt bug reports and applies the fix that the bg-tasks dialog has been quietly using all along.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Both Help → About OK buttons (still) didn't dismiss the dialog in 0.7.49, and the Roadmap dialog's Close button hadn't worked since 0.7.43 either. User report 2026-04-28: "OK buttons still do nothing on the 2 About dialogs… Close button does nothing on the Roadmap either." Real root cause: both upstream Qt bugs QTBUG-79126 ("Dialogs behavior on Wayland is wrong") and QTBUG-90005 ("global modality on Wayland") document that Wayland's xdg-shell protocol has no equivalent of <code>Qt::ApplicationModal</code>. Calling <code>setModal(true)</code> (which 0.7.49 added) is a no-op on Wayland except for an aggravating side effect: KWin/Wayland routes click events into the modal-grab handler which then drops them. The role-based dispatch path inside <code>QDialogButtonBox</code> is a known second aggravator on the same bug. The Background Tasks dialog has been working all along on the same parent-window flags — by being non-modal, with a plain <code>QPushButton</code> whose <code>clicked()</code> is wired directly to <code>QDialog::close</code>. Both About dialogs and the Roadmap dialog now follow that proven shape: non-modal, plain <code>QPushButton</code>, direct <code>clicked()</code> → <code>close()</code>. No more <code>setModal(true)</code>, no more <code>QDialogButtonBox</code>. The OK / Close click reaches its slot and the dialog dismisses on the first try.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.49" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Three follow-up fixes to user reports against 0.7.48 — the About menu's OK buttons silently no-op'd again, the GitHub Public/Private badge wanted to live next to the git branch on the left, and the Background Tasks chip showed phantom counts of tasks that had long since exited.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Both Help → About dialogs now dismiss on the OK button. The 0.7.35 attempt at this bug only swapped the dialog type from <code>QMessageBox</code> to a custom <code>QDialog</code>; both dialogs still went through <code>exec()</code>. On KDE/KWin + Qt 6.11 with the frameless + <code>WA_TranslucentBackground</code> MainWindow, the nested <code>QEventLoop</code> opened by <code>exec()</code> does not surface the dialog as the active input window — the OK button never receives focus and the click silently no-ops. Both handlers now use the heap + <code>WA_DeleteOnClose</code> + <code>show()</code> + <code>raise()</code> + <code>activateWindow()</code> pattern that the Background Tasks, Settings, and Claude Transcript dialogs already use successfully under the same parent-window flags. The OK button's <code>clicked()</code> signal is also wired directly to <code>QDialog::accept</code> alongside the existing <code>QDialogButtonBox::accepted</code> connection. The "About Qt" entry dropped <code>QMessageBox::aboutQt</code> for a custom QDialog with the same heap+show treatment, surfacing the Qt runtime + build versions and a link to qt.io/licensing.</li>
          <li>Background Tasks chip now reflects only tasks that are genuinely running. The transcript-only completion detection used through 0.7.48 only marked tasks finished when Claude Code recorded a matching <code>KillShell</code> event or a <code>BashOutput</code> tool_result with status completed/killed/failed — tasks that were spawned and never polled stayed running indefinitely (the user-reported "12 tasks" phantom count). <code>parseTranscript</code> now performs a liveness sweep at the end: each unfinished task whose output file no longer exists OR whose mtime is older than a 60 s staleness window is flipped to finished. <code>ClaudeBgTaskTracker::rescan</code> was promoted to <code>public slots:</code> and the 2 s status timer drives <code>refreshBgTasksButton</code> so the sweep keeps firing while the transcript is silent. The chip falls to 0 within ~60 s of the last task going idle.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>GitHub Public/Private badge moved to the left side of the status bar, next to the git-branch chip. Was on the right (<code>addPermanentWidget</code>, shipped 0.7.45) where it sat alongside the Claude Code chrome; the user asked 2026-04-27 to move it next to the branch where the two badges read as a "branch · visibility" pair. Restyled to match the branch chip — same rounded <code>bgSecondary</code> fill + <code>border-1px</code> frame — while keeping the green-for-public / red-for-private foreground colour from 0.7.45.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.48" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Two tab-bar fixes the user spotted after 0.7.47 shipped. The per-tab Claude Code activity dot was only painting on one tab — the most recently focused one — even when several tabs each had their own running Claude Code session. The dot also sat too close to the tab text. The first is a real correctness bug; the second is comfort.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Per-tab Claude state dot now renders on every tab with a live Claude Code session, not just the most recently focused one. <code>ClaudeTabTracker::detectClaudeChild</code> was assigning each shell the system-wide newest <code>*.jsonl</code> as its transcript path on first detection, so all N tabs running Claude ended up watching the same file and the inverse path-to-pid map was last-write-wins. The 0.7.44 walk-up logic from <code>ClaudeIntegration::activeSessionPath</code> is now extracted as a static helper <code>ClaudeIntegration::sessionPathForCwd(cwd)</code> and called from the tracker, with cwd taken from <code>/proc/&lt;claudePid&gt;/cwd</code> (falling back to <code>/proc/&lt;shellPid&gt;/cwd</code>). Two shells in two distinct project trees now end up with two distinct transcript paths and two independent state streams.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Tab leading-edge gutter widened from 16 px to 22 px (<code>QTabBar::tab</code> stylesheet → <code>padding: 6px 16px 6px 22px</code>). The Claude state dot's center moves from <code>r.left() + 8</code> to <code>r.left() + 11</code> so it stays gutter-centered, leaving roughly 7 px between the dot's right edge and the first character of the tab text instead of the previous 4 px. Tabs without a Claude indicator pick up the same widened leading padding; the bar still looks balanced.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Pinned by INV-8 in <code>tests/features/claude_tab_status_indicator/spec.md</code>: a source-grep half asserts the tracker calls <code>sessionPathForCwd</code> and reads <code>/proc/&lt;pid&gt;/cwd</code>; a round-trip half builds a synthetic <code>~/.claude/projects/</code> tree with two encoded subdirs and verifies each cwd resolves to its own subdir's <code>.jsonl</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.47" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Smaller-footprint update checks plus a pre-update warning dialog. Two pieces of user feedback after 0.7.46 shipped: the hourly background check was too noisy, and clicking the update badge to kick AppImageUpdate should warn that the terminal will need to be quit and re-launched (active Claude Code sessions will be disconnected). Both addressed in this release.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>A new <code>Help → Check for Updates</code> menu action with the objectName <code>helpCheckForUpdatesAction</code>. The result lands as a status-bar message ("Up to date" / "Update check failed: ..." / the existing badge-show flow when a newer release exists).</li>
          <li>A pre-update confirmation <code>QMessageBox</code> in <code>handleUpdateClicked</code>. The dialog explains that AppImageUpdate writes the new release alongside the running binary, that the user will need to quit and re-launch to use it, and that active Claude Code sessions will be disconnected and need to be reconnected. Cancel short-circuits the spawn and surfaces "Update cancelled." in the status bar.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><code>checkForUpdates(bool userInitiated = false)</code>. The new <code>userInitiated</code> parameter scopes whether negative results are surfaced — startup probes stay silent so launch noise stays low; manual clicks from the Help menu surface their result so the user sees something happen.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Removed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The hourly <code>m_updateCheckTimer</code> background poll. Updates are now checked at startup (5 s after launch) and on demand via the Help menu only.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/github_status_bar/</code> — extended from 16 to 17 invariants. INV-9 (revised) enforces the absence of the hourly timer plus the presence of the menu action plus the userInitiated flag plumbing. INV-17 (new) walks <code>handleUpdateClicked</code> asserting the dialog construction precedes the startDetached call, the dialog text mentions "quit and re-launch" + "Claude Code" + "reconnected", and Cancel surfaces a status message.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.46" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Phase B of the auto-update story — actual in-place binary updates via AppImageUpdate and zsync. The 0.7.45 status bar notifier knew about new releases but only opened a download page; this release closes the loop. Click the update badge and the AppImage updates itself. v0.7.46 is the first release whose binary can be updated in place; pre-0.7.46 binaries shipped without the embedded metadata and continue to be manual-download only.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Update-information ELF note plus a <code>.zsync</code> sidecar in every release. The build workflow now passes a <code>UPDATE_INFORMATION</code> environment variable to linuxdeploy that uses the GitHub-releases-zsync schema; linuxdeploy embeds the string into the AppImage's update-info ELF note and produces the sidecar alongside. Both files are uploaded to each release.</li>
          <li>A new click handler on the update-available label, <code>MainWindow::handleUpdateClicked</code>, wired via <code>linkActivated</code>. Probes for <code>AppImageUpdate</code> (GUI) first, <code>appimageupdatetool</code> (CLI) second; reads the <code>$APPIMAGE</code> env var to find the on-disk AppImage path; runs the updater detached via <code>QProcess::startDetached</code>. Falls back to opening the release page in the user's browser only when neither tool is installed or the binary isn't running as an AppImage.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The update-available label now uses <code>setOpenExternalLinks(false)</code>; clicks route through the new handler instead of being auto-opened by Qt.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/github_status_bar/</code> — extended from 12 to 16 invariants. INV-11 (revised) requires the <code>linkActivated</code> connection. INV-13 source-greps the workflow for the <code>UPDATE_INFORMATION</code> env var with the right schema. INV-14 confirms the <code>.zsync</code> sidecar upload. INV-15 walks the new handler asserting both updater names, the <code>$APPIMAGE</code> read, and the browser fallback. INV-16 confirms <code>QProcess::startDetached</code> is used so the updater outlives the parent process.</p>
        <p>Notes: AppImage updates write a fresh file alongside the original (with a <code>.zs-old</code> suffix on the previous version) — the running process keeps the old contents in memory until the user quits and relaunches. The first release that can use this feature is 0.7.46 itself; earlier AppImages were built without the metadata.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.45" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>GitHub-aware status bar — two new badges that surface context the user previously had to alt-tab to a browser to see. A Public/Private repo visibility badge for the active tab's project, and an "↗ Update vX.Y.Z available" notifier that checks the GitHub releases API hourly and lets the user click through to the release page when a newer version exists.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Public/Private repo badge — a small <code>QLabel</code> next to the Roadmap button. Theme-derived colour, green for public, amber for private. Per-tab via <code>refreshStatusBarForActiveTab</code> calling a new <code>refreshRepoVisibility()</code>: walks the active tab's <code>shellCwd()</code> up for a <code>.git</code> ancestor, parses <code>[remote "origin"]</code> from <code>.git/config</code> (handles both the HTTPS and SSH URL forms GitHub uses), and resolves visibility via the <code>gh repo view</code> CLI with the minimal <code>--json visibility</code> field set. 10-minute cache by repo root. Failure modes (no <code>.git</code>, non-GitHub origin, <code>gh</code> missing or unauthenticated, network error) all hide the label.</li>
          <li>Clickable update notifier — a cyan <code>QLabel</code> with <code>setOpenExternalLinks(true)</code> shown when a newer GitHub release exists. A new <code>checkForUpdates()</code> slot queries the project's <code>releases/latest</code> endpoint via <code>QNetworkAccessManager</code>, parses <code>tag_name</code>, and compares against <code>ANTS_VERSION</code> via the new pure helper <code>compareSemver</code>. Hourly timer plus a 5 s <code>singleShot</code> on startup. Click opens the release page in the user's browser.</li>
          <li>Pure helpers added to <code>mainwindow.cpp</code>: <code>findGitRepoRoot</code>, <code>parseGithubOriginSlug</code>, and <code>compareSemver</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/github_status_bar/</code> — 12 invariants covering label declaration, construction, object-name, hidden-default state, helper presence, both URL-form handling, <code>refreshStatusBarForActiveTab</code> wiring, four hide-on-failure branches in <code>refreshRepoVisibility</code>, the 10-minute cache TTL, the minimal <code>gh</code> invocation, the 60-min timer plus 5 s <code>singleShot</code>, the releases-latest endpoint plus User-Agent header, <code>setOpenExternalLinks(true)</code>, and component-wise integer comparison in <code>compareSemver</code>.</p>
        <p>Out of scope: actual binary auto-update via AppImageUpdate or zsync. That's a follow-up release that needs the build workflow to publish a <code>.zsync</code> sidecar and embed the GitHub-releases zsync update-information string in the linuxdeploy command. This release only notifies; the user clicks through to download.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.44" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Two themed cleanups in one bundle. Retiring the dormant GPU-accelerated glyph-atlas renderer (compiled-but-unreachable since 0.7.4) and its no-op user-facing chrome (Settings checkbox + View menu action) — ~900 LoC removed, retires ROADMAP § "Renderer subsystem decision". Plus scoping the Background Tasks dialog to the active tab's project tree so sessions running in another project's window don't leak into this window's button.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Background Tasks button now scopes to the active tab's project.</em> Previously <code>ClaudeIntegration::activeSessionPath()</code> walked <code>~/.claude/projects/</code> system-wide and returned the most-recently-modified <code>.jsonl</code>, which meant a busy session in one project's window would surface its bg-tasks count on a sibling window pointed at a different project. The method now accepts a <code>projectCwd</code> argument; the active tab's <code>shellCwd()</code> is encoded via <code>encodeProjectPath</code> and the helper walks up the cwd probing each ancestor's <code>~/.claude/projects/&lt;encoded&gt;/</code> subdir, returning the deepest match's newest <code>.jsonl</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Removed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>src/glrenderer.{h,cpp}</code> (~900 LoC).</em> The optional GPU-accelerated glyph-atlas renderer with GLSL 3.3 shaders + instanced quads + a per-cell vertex buffer. Disabled in 0.7.4 when <code>TerminalWidget</code> switched from <code>QOpenGLWidget</code> to plain <code>QWidget</code>; sat compiled-but-unreachable for 39 releases.</li>
          <li><em><code>gpu_rendering</code> Config key + Settings checkbox + View menu action.</em> All three wrote to the dormant bool with no observable effect since 0.7.4. Removed in this release. Existing config files with <code>"gpu_rendering": true</code> are silently ignored — <code>Config</code> doesn't validate unknown JSON keys.</li>
          <li><em><code>TerminalWidget::setGpuRendering(bool)</code> / <code>gpuRendering()</code></em> + the <code>m_glRenderer</code> / <code>m_gpuRendering</code> members.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/claude_bg_tasks_button/</code> — extended from 10 to 11 invariants. INV-11 is a three-part check on the project-scoping fix: header signature accepts <code>projectCwd</code>, implementation walks up via <code>cdUp</code> + <code>encodeProjectPath</code>, and <code>MainWindow::refreshBgTasksButton</code> reads <code>focusedTerminal()-&gt;shellCwd()</code> and passes it through to <code>activeSessionPath(cwd)</code>. <code>tests/features/settings_restore_defaults/spec.md</code> updated to drop the no-longer-applicable <code>gpuRendering off</code> clause.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.43" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Roadmap viewer polish — the dialog the previous release introduced gets a working <em>Close</em> button and a dynamic section-navigation sidebar that lists every heading in the active <code>ROADMAP.md</code> and lets the user click to jump. The TOC is built per project from whatever headings the file happens to have (no hardcoded section names) so the same dialog adapts to every repo that opens with a roadmap.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>TOC sidebar in the Roadmap viewer.</em> <code>QSplitter(Qt::Horizontal)</code> inside <code>RoadmapDialog</code> puts a <code>QListWidget</code> (<code>objectName "roadmap-toc"</code>) on the left and the rendered viewer on the right. The list is rebuilt from the markdown on every refresh — including live-update events on <code>ROADMAP.md</code> change — and entries are indented two spaces per level above 1 with level-1 headings shown bold. Click or activate an entry → the viewer scrolls to the matching heading.</li>
          <li><em>Anchor-emitting renderer.</em> <code>RoadmapDialog::renderHtml</code> now prepends <code>&lt;a name="roadmap-toc-N"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</code> before each <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;h2&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;h3&gt;</code>/<code>&lt;h4&gt;</code> it emits. The N-th anchor matches the N-th entry returned by the new pure helper <code>RoadmapDialog::extractToc</code>, which returns a <code>QVector&lt;TocEntry&gt;</code> of <code>{level, text, anchor}</code> triples. Both helpers are pure and static so they're driven by the feature-conformance test without spinning a Qt widget tree.</li>
          <li><em><code>QTextBrowser</code> in place of <code>QTextEdit</code>.</em> Required for <code>scrollToAnchor</code> support. Links are pinned non-navigable (<code>setOpenLinks(false)</code> / <code>setOpenExternalLinks(false)</code>) so a stray markdown link can't replace the document.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Close button in the Roadmap viewer is now actually clickable.</em> The dialog used the role-based <code>QDialogButtonBox::rejected</code> signal alone; under some Qt 6 builds the standard <code>Close</code> button does not trigger that signal, leaving the button looking active but doing nothing. The Close button is now wired both via <code>rejected()</code> (kept as belt-and-braces) and via a direct <code>clicked</code> connection on the underlying <code>QPushButton</code> retrieved with <code>button(QDialogButtonBox::Close)</code>. The direct connect is the authoritative fix.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/roadmap_viewer/</code> — extended from 10 to 14 invariants. INV-11 verifies <code>extractToc</code> returns a 5-entry list with matching levels, raw text, and <code>roadmap-toc-N</code> anchors against a known multi-level input. INV-12 verifies <code>renderHtml</code> emits the anchor before each heading. INV-13 source-greps for <code>QSplitter</code> + <code>roadmap-toc</code> objectName + <code>scrollToAnchor</code> in the dialog. INV-14 source-greps the Close-button direct <code>QAbstractButton::clicked</code> connection.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.42" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Inline ghost-text completion in the Command Palette — Claude Code's <code>/slash</code>-command UX, ported to Ctrl+Shift+P. As you type, the unmatched suffix of the top fuzzy-match is rendered in a dimmed colour right after the cursor; <code>Tab</code> commits the suggestion into the input. Retires ROADMAP § "Command Palette ghost-completion (near-term, small scope)".</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>GhostLineEdit</code> subclass of <code>QLineEdit</code>.</em> Lives in <code>src/commandpalette.h</code>. Carries a <code>m_ghost</code> string set via <code>setGhostSuffix()</code>; <code>paintEvent</code> calls <code>QLineEdit::paintEvent(event)</code> first, then opens a fresh <code>QPainter</code> and draws the ghost at <code>cursorRect().right() + 1</code> using <code>palette().color(QPalette::Text)</code> with <code>setAlphaF(0.45)</code>. No layout changes — the suffix overlays the existing line-edit content area, so palette geometry is unchanged.</li>
          <li><em><code>CommandPalette::updateGhostCompletion(filter)</code>.</em> Invoked from <code>populateList</code> after the result list is rebuilt. Looks at <code>m_list-&gt;item(0)</code>, recovers the underlying <code>QAction</code>, strips <code>&amp;</code> accelerators, and: if the filter is empty, list is empty, or the action name does not start with the filter (case-insensitive), <code>setGhostSuffix("")</code>; otherwise <code>setGhostSuffix(name.mid(filter.length()))</code> (preserving the action name's original casing in the ghost). <code>contains()</code>-only matches get an empty ghost — the visual contract is that the suffix appears flush after the user's typed input, which only makes sense for prefix matches.</li>
          <li><em><code>Tab</code>-key commit handler.</em> <code>eventFilter</code> adds <code>Qt::Key_Tab</code> → <code>commitGhost()</code>, which appends the ghost suffix to the input via <code>setText</code>; the follow-up <code>textChanged → filterActions → populateList → updateGhostCompletion</code> cycle clears the ghost in the same dispatch since the new filter equals the action name's tail exactly. The post-commit text equals the visible composition (user-typed prefix + ghost suffix), so user-typed casing is preserved — same as shell-completion semantics. Tab is always consumed by the palette (even when the ghost is empty) so focus cannot leak out of the input. <code>Tab</code> does not also execute the action — the user presses <code>Enter</code> to run, matching Claude Code's <code>/slash</code>-completion contract.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/command_palette_ghost_completion/</code> — ten invariants on the <code>GhostLineEdit</code> existence, ghost-empty vs ghost-set transitions across empty / prefix / uppercase-prefix / contains-only / no-match filters, Tab commit semantics (text and ghost state), Tab-with-empty-ghost focus retention, source-grep on the dimmed-color literal and <code>cursorRect</code> anchor, and Esc dismiss regression. Drives <code>CommandPalette</code> directly under <code>QT_QPA_PLATFORM=offscreen</code>. Pre-fix verification: with the implementation stashed, the test fails to even compile (missing <code>GhostLineEdit</code> symbol). Out of scope: the in-terminal shell ghost-suggestion (fish-style, OSC 133 prompt-detection + history scraping) remains <code>💭</code> in ROADMAP, deferred past 1.0.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.41" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Accessibility. Every glyph-only chrome control now carries an explicit <code>setAccessibleName</code> and <code>setAccessibleDescription</code>, so Orca, Speakup, and other AT-SPI screen readers announce them by purpose ("Close window") instead of by codepoint name ("eight-spoked asterisk", "multiplication sign x"). Two ROADMAP items retired in one bundle: § "Accessibility pass on chrome" (mainwindow / palette / title-bar control labels) and § "AT-SPI introspection lane" (an automated check that every user-visible chrome control carries a name).</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Accessible names on TitleBar window controls.</em> <code>centerBtn</code> ("Center window"), <code>minimizeBtn</code> ("Minimize window"), <code>maximizeBtn</code> ("Maximize window" / "Maximize or restore this window"), and <code>closeBtn</code> ("Close window") each get an explicit <code>setAccessibleName</code> + <code>setAccessibleDescription</code> set immediately after <code>setText</code> in <code>titlebar.cpp:54-97</code>. Each button also gains a stable <code>objectName</code> so the introspection test can find them deterministically. Visual rendering is unchanged — the glyphs (<code>✥ – □ ✕</code>) still drive the on-screen pixels; only the AT-SPI tree changed.</li>
          <li><em>Accessible names on the Command Palette.</em> The search input (objectName <code>commandPaletteInput</code>) gets <code>Command palette search</code> / <code>Type to filter actions; Tab to commit; Esc to dismiss</code>; the result list (objectName <code>commandPaletteList</code>) gets <code>Command palette results</code> / <code>Available actions matching the current filter</code>. Placeholder text and visible behaviour are unchanged: the placeholder is a typing hint for sighted users; the accessible name is what screen readers announce on focus.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by a new <code>tests/features/a11y_chrome_names/</code> spec + test (eight invariants — T1–T4 each TitleBar button has the right accessibleName + non-empty accessibleDescription; T5/T6 the CommandPalette input + list have theirs; T7 the AT-SPI introspection lane sweeps every reachable <code>QAbstractButton</code>/<code>QLineEdit</code> in the chrome tree; T8/T9 source-grep counts on <code>titlebar.cpp</code>/<code>commandpalette.cpp</code> so a refactor that drops the calls fails the build, not just AT-SPI usage at runtime). The test runs under <code>QT_QPA_PLATFORM=offscreen</code>, so it works in CI without a display. <code>tr()</code> translation hooks are deferred to the 0.9.0 H10 i18n bundle.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.40" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Performance. Two Tier 3 perf items from <code>ROADMAP.md § 0.7.x ⚡ / 🏗 Tier 3 — structural</code> retired in one bundle: scroll-region rotate plus a zero-copy <code>VtBatch</code> hop across the worker→GUI thread boundary. Both are observably equivalent at the API level — the existing <code>tests/features/scroll_region_rotate/</code> and <code>tests/features/threaded_parse_equivalence/</code> regressions pass unchanged — so the win is throughput / cost, not visible behaviour.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>TerminalGrid::scrollUp</code> / <code>scrollDown</code> use <code>std::rotate</code>.</em> Replaced the per-iteration <code>m_screenLines.erase + insert</code> loop with a single rotate over <code>[scrollTop, scrollBottom]</code>, gated by a pool-salvage / scrollback-push pre-pass and a fresh-blank post-pass. The CSI 2J doubling-guard window check now runs once per batch (microsecond-scale elapsed time made the per-iteration window-extend redundant). <code>m_scrollback</code> cap enforcement collapses from N <code>pop_front</code> passes to one. On <code>CSI 100 S</code> against an 80-row screen, the row-shift cost goes from O(count × rows) memmoves (8000) to O(rows) (80).</li>
          <li><em><code>VtStream::batchReady</code> carries <code>VtBatchPtr</code> instead of <code>const VtBatch &amp;</code>.</em> New alias <code>using VtBatchPtr = std::shared_ptr&lt;const VtBatch&gt;;</code> in <code>vtstream.h</code>. Qt's queued-connection plumbing must own dispatched parameters, so the prior <code>const T &amp;</code> signal forced a deep copy of the entire batch (the <code>actions</code> vector + <code>rawBytes</code> <code>QByteArray</code>) on every worker→GUI hop. The shared_ptr wrap reduces the cross-thread payload to a 16-byte atomic refcount bump; the underlying <code>VtBatch</code> lives on the heap and is not duplicated. Both emit sites (<code>flushBatch</code>, <code>onPtyFinished</code>) build via <code>std::make_shared&lt;VtBatch&gt;()</code>; <code>TerminalWidget::onVtBatch</code> signature is now <code>void onVtBatch(VtBatchPtr batch)</code> with field access via <code>batch-&gt;…</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by a new <code>tests/features/vtbatch_zero_copy/</code> spec + test (5 source-grep invariants pinning the cross-thread signal shape so a future refactor cannot silently revert to the deep-copy form). Behavioural equivalence on the action stream stays covered by <code>tests/features/threaded_parse_equivalence/</code>; rotation correctness stays covered by the 8 algorithm-agnostic invariants in <code>tests/features/scroll_region_rotate/</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.39" date="2026-04-27">
      <description>
        <p>Claude Code UX bundle plus a status-bar Roadmap viewer. Two user requests landed in quick succession. Request 1: "Let's have a round dot on each tab that has a Claude Code session running (no icons or anything else other than the tab label). The dot will change colour with the various states that Claude Code is in. Each state has its own colour (grey for idle). Then extend those colours to the status bar Claude Code status too." Request 2: "Add a button on the status bar to view the roadmap. So, it brings up a dialog showing the roadmap. It should have filters as well to show what is outstanding and what is completed. If at all possible, it should also highlight what item is being done currently. The roadmap button should only show if there is roadmap documentation — let's simplify that to requiring a roadmap.md file only."</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Unified Claude state-dot palette across tabs and status bar.</em> New static helper <code>ClaudeTabIndicator::color(Glyph)</code> in <code>coloredtabbar.h</code> is the single source of truth for an eight-state palette: Idle grey, Thinking blue, ToolUse yellow, Bash green, Planning cyan, Auditing magenta, Compacting violet, AwaitingInput orange. Red is intentionally absent — AwaitingInput is a normal interaction state, not an error. <code>ColoredTabBar::paintEvent</code> uses a single <code>kDotRadius = 4</code> for every state; the prior AwaitingInput "outline + radius 5" treatment is removed. The bottom status-bar Claude Code label was rewired to map current state through the same helper, replacing prior <code>Theme::ansi[]</code> mappings that drifted from the tab dot's colour.</li>
          <li><em>Auditing now lights the per-tab dot.</em> Plumbed into <code>ClaudeTabTracker::ShellState::auditing</code> (mirrored from <code>ClaudeTranscriptSnapshot.auditing</code>); tab provider routes it to <code>Glyph::Auditing</code> magenta. Precedence chain unchanged across both surfaces: AwaitingInput → Planning → Auditing → state-derived.</li>
          <li><em>Status-bar Roadmap viewer button (<code>roadmapdialog.{h,cpp}</code>).</em> Visible iff the active tab's <code>shellCwd()</code> contains a <code>ROADMAP.md</code> (case-insensitive). Click opens a non-modal <code>RoadmapDialog</code> with five peer category checkboxes (Done, Planned, In progress, Considered, Currently being tackled), all default-checked. The static <code>RoadmapDialog::renderHtml</code> helper is pure so tests can drive it without a Qt widget.</li>
          <li><em>"Currently being tackled" highlight.</em> A bullet matches the current-work signal if its first-80-character normalised payload contains a phrase from a signal set built from the local <code>CHANGELOG.md</code> <code>[Unreleased]</code> bullets and the last 5 non-release/non-merge/non-revert git commit subjects. Matched bullets get a yellow left-border CSS highlight (the same ToolUse yellow from the dot palette). When the signal set is empty, no highlight renders.</li>
          <li><em>Live-tail dialog mechanics.</em> <code>QFileSystemWatcher</code> on <code>ROADMAP.md</code> and <code>CHANGELOG.md</code>, 200 ms debounce, plus the same scroll-preservation triple shipped with 0.7.37 / 0.7.38: <code>m_lastHtml</code> shared_ptr cache + skip-identical-HTML guard, capture vbar before <code>setHtml</code>, restore with <code>qMin(saved, vbar->maximum())</code> clamp, was-at-bottom pin so live appends stay visible.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed: <code>ClaudeTabIndicator::Glyph</code> enum gains <code>Auditing</code> between <code>Planning</code> and <code>Compacting</code>; <code>ClaudeTabTracker::ShellState</code> gains a <code>bool auditing</code> field with a comparison branch in <code>maybeEmit</code>. <code>MainWindow::applyClaudeStatusLabel</code> no longer reads <code>Theme::ansi[]</code> for Claude-label colours — all state → colour mappings now route through the unified helper. Removed: AwaitingInput-specific dot decoration (radius 5 + white outline); colour alone is the differentiator now.</p>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/claude_state_dot_palette/</code> (8 invariants) and <code>tests/features/roadmap_viewer/</code> (10 hybrid invariants — source-grep plus behavioural drives of the static <code>renderHtml</code> helper).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.38" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Feature. Background-tasks status-bar surface for Claude Code. User request 2026-04-25: "a button on the status bar when there are background tasks being run. We then click the button to view what Claude Code shows for the background tasks. The button opens a dialog showing the live update info on the background tasks." Claude Code can spawn long-running tasks via <code>Bash</code> or <code>Task</code> with <code>run_in_background: true</code>. The TUI shows a sidebar listing them with their tail output; users dropping into a different tab to keep working had no way to see those tasks from Ants Terminal — they had to flip back to the TUI and parse the sidebar by hand.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Background-tasks tracker.</em> A pure parser walks the active session's transcript JSONL, recognizing <code>tool_use</code> blocks whose <code>input.run_in_background == true</code> (start) and <code>tool_result</code> blocks whose <code>toolUseResult.backgroundTaskId</code> is set (confirmation, with the on-disk output path extracted from the result body). Completion / kill state is derived from subsequent <code>BashOutput</code> results carrying <code>status: "completed" | "killed" | "failed"</code> and from <code>KillShell</code> tool calls. Static <code>parseTranscript(path)</code> is testable without a watcher.</li>
          <li><em>Status-bar button.</em> Sibling to the Review Changes button; same fixed sizePolicy contract. Hidden by default; visible only while the running count is greater than zero for the active tab's session. Label re-renders as "Background Tasks (N)"; tooltip discloses running + total. Re-targeted on tab switch via the unified <code>refreshStatusBarForActiveTab</code> path, so each tab's session drives its own count independently.</li>
          <li><em>Live-tail dialog.</em> Mirrors the Review Changes live-update model that 0.7.37 stabilized. <code>QFileSystemWatcher</code> covers each task's <code>.output</code> file plus the transcript path; a 200 ms debounce timer collapses bursts of <code>fileChanged</code> signals into one render. Skip-identical-HTML guard plus capture-vbar-before-<code>setHtml</code> + restore-after with <code>qMin(..., maximum())</code> clamp keeps absolute scroll position when content changes. Bonus "was at bottom" detection: when the user is tailing the bottom, pin them to the bottom across appends so live output stays visible without manual scrolling.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by a new <code>tests/features/claude_bg_tasks_button/</code> spec + test (10 invariants — source-grep harness, no Qt link).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.37" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>UX bug fix. Live-update regression in the Review Changes dialog (the QFileSystemWatcher + 300ms debounce wiring added in 0.7.32). User report 2026-04-25: "When using the Review Changes dialog, the constant resetting of the text means that if I scroll, it resets to the beginning every refresh. That means I can't scroll basically." The 0.7.32 finalize lambda called <code>setHtml</code> unconditionally on every probe completion, snapping the QTextEdit scroll bar back to the top — on a long diff with active live updates the dialog became unscrollable.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Review Changes dialog: scroll position preserved across live refreshes.</em> Two-layer guard around the <code>setHtml</code> call inside <code>MainWindow::showDiffViewer</code>'s <code>finalize</code> lambda. (1) An <code>auto lastHtml = std::make_shared&lt;QString&gt;()</code> cache threaded through <code>runProbes</code> and <code>finalize</code> lets <code>finalize</code> early-return when the new render is byte-identical to the previous one — the common case during idle live-update tics. Selection, cursor, and scroll are byte-perfectly preserved. (2) When content does change, vertical and horizontal scroll-bar values are captured before <code>setHtml</code> and restored after, clamped to <code>bar->maximum()</code> so a shorter render after a commit doesn't over-scroll. First-render carve-out (<code>isFirstRender = lastHtml->isEmpty()</code>) keeps the initial paint at the top.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by a new <code>tests/features/review_changes_scroll_preserve/</code> spec + test (6 invariants — source-grep harness scoped to the <code>showDiffViewer</code> body).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.36" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>UX bug fix. Same translucent-parent failure mode that bit the menubar in 0.7.25/0.7.26 caught in two more places (user report, post-0.7.32): "The tabs themselves are fine but the rest of the tab bar across the window is transparent as well as the background for the status bar." The 0.7.32 close-button SVG drew the user's eye to the empty-area fill that had been mis-painted all along; the bug was not introduced by 0.7.32 but became visible because the new tab look re-balanced what the user noticed.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Tab bar empty area paints opaque under <code>WA_TranslucentBackground</code>.</em> Was: the strip to the right of the last tab rendered the desktop wallpaper through, with the QSS <code>QTabBar { background-color: ... }</code> rule silently dropped by Qt's stylesheet engine on KWin + Breeze + Qt 6 once <code>WA_OpaquePaintEvent</code> was set on the widget — same root cause documented in <code>opaquemenubar.h</code>. Now: <code>ColoredTabBar</code> exposes <code>setBackgroundFill(QColor)</code> and prepends a <code>CompositionMode_Source</code> <code>fillRect</code> to its existing <code>paintEvent</code>, before the base class draws tabs and before the colour-group gradient overlay. <code>applyTheme()</code> pushes <code>theme.bgSecondary</code> into the override.</li>
          <li><em>Status bar background paints opaque under <code>WA_TranslucentBackground</code>.</em> Was: the entire status bar strip rendered the desktop wallpaper through — same root cause as the tab bar above. Now: a header-only <code>OpaqueStatusBar</code> mirrors <code>OpaqueMenuBar</code> (<code>paintEvent</code> <code>fillRect</code> → delegate). <code>MainWindow</code> constructs an <code>OpaqueStatusBar</code>, installs it via <code>setStatusBar(...)</code> <em>before</em> the first <code>statusBar()</code> call (Qt's lazy-creation would otherwise install a plain <code>QStatusBar</code> that paints transparent), and pushes <code>theme.bgSecondary</code> via <code>setBackgroundFill</code> from <code>applyTheme()</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by a new <code>tests/features/tabbar_statusbar_opaque/</code> spec + test (5 invariants — source-grep harness, no display required).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.35" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>UX bug fix. Single user-reported regression in the Help → About Ants Terminal dialog (the GUI version indicator added in 0.7.22).</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>About Ants Terminal dialog OK button silently no-op'd.</em> Was: <code>Help → About Ants Terminal…</code> opened correctly, but clicking <code>OK</code> did nothing — the dialog could only be dismissed via the window-manager close button. The 0.7.22 implementation used <code>QMessageBox::Ok</code> with <code>Qt::TextBrowserInteraction</code> (which pulls in <code>Qt::TextSelectableByMouse</code>); under the combination of our frameless <code>MainWindow</code>, <code>Qt::WA_TranslucentBackground</code>, KDE Plasma + KWin, and Qt 6.11 this caused the OK click to be silently dropped. Now: the About handler builds a custom <code>QDialog</code> with a <code>QDialogButtonBox(QDialogButtonBox::Ok)</code> whose <code>accepted</code> signal is explicitly connected to <code>QDialog::accept</code> — standard, testable, independent of QMessageBox's internal standard-button dispatch.</li>
          <li><em>About dialog GitHub link was a visual-only no-op.</em> Was: the link was rendered as clickable (cursor changed on hover) because <code>Qt::TextBrowserInteraction</code> enables <code>Qt::LinksAccessibleByMouse</code>, but <code>setOpenExternalLinks(true)</code> was never called on the label — clicking emitted <code>linkActivated()</code> into the void. Now: the body <code>QLabel</code> has <code>setOpenExternalLinks(true)</code>, so clicking the GitHub URL opens it in the user's browser.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by an updated <code>tests/features/help_about_menu/</code> spec + test (8 invariants — pre-fix source fails 6 of them).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.34" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Terminal correctness. One ROADMAP item retiring the last known DECOM (origin mode) bug — tmux/screen save-restore round-trips were silently dropping the origin-mode flag and ignoring scroll-region-relative coordinates on absolute cursor moves.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>CUP / HVP / VPA translate to scroll-region origin under DECOM.</em> Was: with origin mode (<code>CSI ?6h</code>) active and a scroll region set via DECSTBM, <code>CSI 1;1H</code> jumped to absolute (0, 0) and <code>CSI 99;1H</code> clamped to the bottom of the entire screen instead of the bottom of the scroll region. Programs that depend on origin-mode-relative positioning (vim split-window cursor restoration, screen's caption line, tmux status redraws) wrote to the wrong row. Now: the <code>'H'</code>, <code>'f'</code>, and <code>'d'</code> cases add <code>m_scrollTop</code> to the requested row when <code>m_originMode</code> is set, then clamp to <code>[m_scrollTop, m_scrollBottom]</code>. Behaviour matches xterm.</li>
          <li><em>DECSC saves DECOM + DECAWM, DECRC restores them.</em> Was: <code>saveCursor()</code> stored only (row, col, attrs), so a TUI that flipped origin mode or auto-wrap, did <code>CSI s</code>/<code>ESC 7</code>, ran code that re-toggled the flag, then <code>CSI u</code>/<code>ESC 8</code>'d, ended up with the flag in whatever state the inner code left it — silent coordinate-space corruption. Now: new <code>m_savedOriginMode</code> and <code>m_savedAutoWrap</code> members capture the flags on save and restore them on restore, matching the VT420 spec.</li>
          <li><em>DECSTBM home position respects DECOM.</em> Was: <code>setScrollRegion()</code> always homed the cursor to absolute (0, 0). Now: when <code>m_originMode</code> is on at the time DECSTBM lands, the cursor moves to (m_scrollTop, 0) — the top-left of the origin-mode coordinate space — as xterm does.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Locked by <code>tests/features/origin_mode_correctness/</code> — 12 behavioural invariants plus 4 source-grep checks.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.33" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Lifecycle / cleanup. Three ROADMAP items addressing GUI-thread blocking on shutdown, an xdg-desktop-portal session leak, and two latent issues (OOM surface + symlink escape) in the Lua plugin loader.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>PTY destructor escalation runs off the main thread.</em> Was: SIGTERM-then-busy-wait-then-SIGKILL ran on the GUI thread; N split panes closing together blocked window close N × 500 ms. Now: the SIGTERM/SIGKILL escalation moves to a detached <code>std::thread</code> capturing the pid by value. Cheap pre-escalation reap (SIGHUP + close master fd + WNOHANG) stays inline so well-behaved children don't pay a thread spawn. Synchronous fallback retained for the rare case of thread-creation failure under <code>ulimit -u</code> pressure. Locked by <code>tests/features/pty_dtor_off_main_thread/</code> with 11 invariants.</li>
          <li><em>GlobalShortcutsPortal closes its session on destruction.</em> Was: no destructor at all — the session handle leaked for the lifetime of the D-Bus client. xdg-desktop-portal accumulated one orphan session per Ants invocation that crashed or was SIGKILLed before implicit cleanup. Now: destructor issues an asynchronous <code>org.freedesktop.portal.Session.Close</code> call against the session handle when non-empty. Locked by <code>tests/features/portal_session_close/</code> with 8 invariants.</li>
          <li><em>Plugin manifest cap + canonical plugin path.</em> Was: <code>f.readAll()</code> on <code>manifest.json</code> was unbounded (multi-GB manifest would OOM before JSON parsing); plugin scan used <code>QDir::Dirs</code> without <code>NoSymLinks</code> or canonical anchoring (a tarball symlink could redirect <code>init.lua</code> loading to <code>/etc/cron.daily</code>). Now: 1 MiB manifest cap via bounded <code>f.read</code>; scan anchors on <code>QFileInfo::canonicalFilePath</code>, passes <code>QDir::NoSymLinks</code>, and per-entry verifies canonical containment inside the plugin root. Locked by <code>tests/features/plugin_manifest_safety/</code> with 12 invariants.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.32" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Dialog UX. Three Settings dialog ROADMAP items (dependency-UI gating, Cancel rollback for Profiles, Restore Defaults per-tab) plus a user feedback fix for the Review Changes dialog (2026-04-25): pre-fix it only surfaced current-branch state and missed work living on other branches.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Restore Defaults per primary Settings tab.</em> General, Appearance, Terminal, AI tabs now each have a dedicated "Restore Defaults" button that resets only that tab's controls to the schema defaults (matching <code>Config::xxx()</code> getter defaults). Reset slots mutate widget state only — applySettings still commits, Cancel still rolls back. Locked by <code>tests/features/settings_restore_defaults/</code> with 22 invariants.</li>
          <li><em>Review Changes dialog: per-branch summary + cross-branch unpushed.</em> Was: three async git probes (status, diff HEAD, log @{u}..HEAD) all scoped to the current branch — a user with feature branches sitting on a clean branch saw "no unpushed". Now: two additional probes (<code>git for-each-ref refs/heads</code> + <code>git log --branches --not --remotes</code>) surface every local branch with its ahead/behind/gone state and every commit reachable from any local branch but not from any remote-tracking branch. Copy Diff includes both new sections.</li>
          <li><em>Review Changes dialog: live updates.</em> User feedback 2026-04-25: dialog should refresh as the user works. Was: probes ran once on dialog open and never again. Now: QFileSystemWatcher watches the working directory plus <code>.git/HEAD</code>, <code>.git/index</code>, <code>.git/refs/heads</code>, <code>.git/refs/remotes</code>, <code>.git/logs/HEAD</code>. A 300 ms single-shot QTimer debounces the burst of fileChanged events that <code>git pull</code> fires. A manual Refresh button bypasses the debounce. A live-status label confirms the watcher is wired. Probe spawning is now a re-callable <code>runProbes</code> lambda that constructs a fresh ProbeState per call so concurrent in-flight probes from a previous render can't poison the new one. Locked by <code>tests/features/review_changes_branches/</code> — 33 invariants total covering both branch-awareness and live-update wiring.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Tab close button (×) always visible, not hover-only.</em> User feedback 2026-04-25. The 0.6.27 platform-style fallback still rendered hover-only on Fusion / qt6ct / some Plasma colour schemes. Now: explicit data-URI SVG <code>image: url(...)</code> rules in both default and :hover <code>QTabBar::close-button</code> variants. Glyph re-tints with the active theme; hover keeps the ansi-red will-click background. Locked by <code>tests/features/tab_close_button_visible/</code> with 11 invariants.</li>
          <li><em>Dependency-UI enable gating in Settings.</em> Was: master checkboxes <code>m_aiEnabled</code>, <code>m_autoColorScheme</code>, <code>m_quakeMode</code> gated logic but not UI — typing an API key into a feature-disabled AI tab produced silent no-ops. Now: <code>QCheckBox::toggled</code> is wired to <code>setEnabled</code> on every dependent sibling, with a one-shot sync call at construction so the initial state matches the loaded config. Disabled controls keep their values so toggling the master back on restores the prior selection. Locked by <code>tests/features/settings_dependency_gating/</code> with 16 invariants.</li>
          <li><em>Profiles tab honors Cancel/OK semantics.</em> Was: profile Save/Delete/Load buttons mutated <code>m_config</code> immediately, bypassing the OK/Cancel pattern every other tab follows. Now: buttons mutate a pending-state pair (<code>m_pendingProfiles</code> + <code>m_pendingActiveProfile</code>); applySettings is the single commit point. Cancel discards staged edits cleanly. Locked by <code>tests/features/settings_profile_cancel_rollback/</code> with 11 invariants including a global "exactly one m_config-&gt;setProfiles call site" check.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.31" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Persistence integrity (cross-file). Four items addressing the silent-data-loss / permission-drift / concurrent-writer surfaces that span Config, ClaudeAllowlist, SessionManager, and SettingsDialog. Splits the growing <code>secureio.h</code> into <code>secureio.h</code> (perms) + <code>configbackup.h</code> (rotation + cooperative write lock) before a third helper landed.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>ConfigWriteLock cooperative write lock for shared config files (src/configbackup.h).</em> Was: two simultaneously-running Ants instances saving the same <code>~/.config/ants-terminal/config.json</code> raced over <code>&lt;path&gt;.tmp</code> + <code>rename(2)</code> — both writers truncated the shared tmp, partial bytes interleaved on the same inode, and last-rename-wins silently dropped one process's keystrokes / settings / profile / AI key. Same shape for <code>~/.claude/settings.json</code> where Allowlist + Install-hooks + git-context-installer all read-modify-write with no serialization. Now: an RAII guard wraps POSIX <code>flock(2)</code> on a sibling <code>&lt;path&gt;.lock</code> file with a 5-second poll deadline (100 × 50 ms), advisory so cooperating callers serialize while non-cooperating editors (vim, jq) bypass by design. Config::save, ClaudeAllowlistDialog::saveSettings, SettingsDialog::installClaudeHooks, and SettingsDialog::installClaudeGitContextHook now construct ConfigWriteLock with an acquired() guard before the write block; failure to acquire logs and returns. Locked by <code>tests/features/concurrent_writer_lock/</code> — 5 runtime invariants via fork(2) so flock semantics are honestly tested across processes, plus 7 source-grep invariants on each save site.</li>
          <li><em>Belt-and-suspenders post-rename setOwnerOnlyPerms at every persistence site.</em> Was: each site set 0600 on the temp fd before write but relied on rename(2) preserving perms across the swap. ext4/xfs/btrfs honor that; FAT/exFAT (no POSIX bits at all), some SMB/NFS servers (server-side rename applies server umask), and Qt's copy+unlink fallback (cross-device rename, exotic mounts) do not. Files containing ai_api_key (config.json), Claude Code bearer tokens (settings.json), or paste-buffer scrollback content (session_*.dat) could land 0644 on those filesystems and leak to every UID on the host. Now: each site re-chmods the final inode after rename / commit() returns success — idempotent on POSIX filesystems, essential elsewhere. Locked by <code>tests/features/persistence_post_rename_chmod/</code> with 10 source-grep invariants spanning config.cpp / sessionmanager.cpp / settingsdialog.cpp.</li>
          <li><em>secureio.h / configbackup.h split.</em> <code>secureio.h</code> is now perms-only — setOwnerOnlyPerms(QFileDevice&amp;) and setOwnerOnlyPerms(const QString&amp;), the original 0600-bitmask helpers that ~12 callers reach for. <code>configbackup.h</code> is the new home for rotateCorruptFileAside (silent-data-loss recovery, was 0.7.12) and the new ConfigWriteLock (concurrent-writer guard, added this release). The split preempts a third-helper cliff: the file was straddling perms + recovery + lock concerns and a fourth would have made the include cost-of-business across the codebase. Locked by <code>tests/features/secureio_configbackup_split/</code> — 13 invariants on file-content boundaries, non-copyable lock, and downstream caller include sets.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Behavioural test coverage extended to the parse-failure mirror sites in ClaudeAllowlist + SettingsDialog.</em> The 0.7.12 silent-data-loss-on-parse-failure refuse pattern shipped in three sites — Config::load, ClaudeAllowlistDialog::saveSettings, and SettingsDialog::install{ClaudeHooks,ClaudeGitContextHook} — but only Config had a regression test. Now they have their own dedicated test: <code>tests/features/settings_parse_failure_mirror/</code> with 8 invariants covering rotation call sites, return-false-after-rotation gating, and the open-failure branch distinct from the parse-failure branch.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.30" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Session-file integrity. Three ROADMAP § 0.7.12 Tier 2 items shipped together as bundle 0.7.30, all in <code>sessionmanager.cpp</code>: a SHA-256 envelope around the qCompress payload, a pre-flight on qCompress's 4-byte uncompressed-length prefix, and per-cell <code>QDataStream::status()</code> checks inside the decode loops.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>V4 SHA-256 envelope around session-file payload (SessionManager::serialize, SessionManager::restore, ENVELOPE_MAGIC, ENVELOPE_VERSION).</em> Was: session files at <code>$XDG_DATA_HOME/ants-terminal/sessions/session_&lt;tabId&gt;.dat</code> were raw <code>qCompress</code> output with no payload integrity. Anyone with write access to that directory (the user's own UID, a compromised local process, an npm dependency, a runaway <code>pip install</code> post-exec) could plant a crafted session that fed arbitrary codepoints, fg/bg colors, and attribute flags into the grid on next restore — a render surface, not a sandbox. Now: serialize wraps the qCompress output in a V4 envelope <code>[SHEC magic 0x53484543][envelope version=1][SHA-256 of payload (32 bytes)][payload length (uint32)][compressed payload]</code>; restore peeks the magic, verifies the hash, and refuses to restore on version mismatch, length disagreement, or hash mismatch. Inner <code>QDataStream</code> format unchanged (still V3) — the integrity layer is framing-only. Legacy V1-V3 files (no envelope) continue to load via the magic-peek fall-through; their next save writes them out as V4 organically. Locked by a four-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/session_sha256_checksum</code>) that flips red against pre-fix source on eight assertions.</li>
          <li><em>qUncompress length-prefix pre-flight (SessionManager::restore, MAX_UNCOMPRESSED).</em> Was: a crafted file claiming 500 MB uncompressed in qCompress's 4-byte big-endian prefix triggered a 500 MB allocation that the post-hoc <code>raw.size() &gt; 500MB</code> cap could only catch after the damage was done — and the on-disk payload could be tiny, so the allocation pressure showed up with no concomitant disk-space anomaly. Now: restore reads the first 4 bytes of the compressed payload, reconstructs the big-endian uint32, and rejects any claim above <code>MAX_UNCOMPRESSED</code> (500 MB) BEFORE qUncompress runs — constant-time, no allocator pressure. Short-payload guard (<code>compressed.size() &lt; 4</code>) keeps the same path safe against truncated inputs that can't carry a length prefix. The post-decompression cap remains as a defense-in-depth backstop. Locked by a four-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/session_qcompress_length_guard</code>).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>QDataStream::status() checks inside cell-decode loops (SessionManager::restore readCell / readCombining).</em> Was: the <code>readCell</code> lambda was void; a stream truncated mid-cell still flowed default-constructed <code>QRgb</code> and <code>uint8_t</code> values through <code>QColor::fromRgba</code> etc. into the cell, silently writing uninitialized fg/bg/flags into the grid. The surrounding loops didn't check per-iteration status either, so the grid kept accepting cells from a stream already at <code>ReadPastEnd</code>. Now: <code>readCell</code> returns bool and short-circuits on <code>in.status() != QDataStream::Ok</code>; every call site (scrollback cells, screen cells in range, screen cells skipped on width shrink, screen cells skipped on height shrink) is guarded by <code>if (!readCell(...)) return false</code>. The combining-character helper checks status after each codepoint read so a stream truncated mid-codepoint can't push default-constructed 0 into the combining map either. Pre-fix, a partial save (kernel crash mid-fsync, disk-full mid-write, hostile sender truncating the envelope payload) could materialize as garbage cells in the next restore — not a crash, but a corrupted scrollback. Locked by a three-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/session_cell_loop_stream_status</code>).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.29" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Audit pipeline II — output quality. Three ROADMAP § 0.7.12 items shipped together as bundle 0.7.29, all in <code>auditdialog.cpp</code>: SARIF v2.1.0 <code>result.suppressions[]</code> array, a regex-DoS watchdog on user-supplied patterns, and a widened 96-bit dedup key.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>SARIF v2.1.0 <code>result.suppressions[]</code> array (AuditDialog::exportSarif, loadSuppressions, saveSuppression, m_suppressionReasons map, Finding::suppressed).</em> Was: SARIF export silently dropped findings whose dedup key matched <code>~/.audit_suppress</code>, producing a falsely-clean report that defeated the suppression-trend telemetry already computed for the in-app dashboard. Now: a parallel <code>QHash&lt;QString,QString&gt; m_suppressionReasons</code> map populated alongside <code>m_suppressedKeys</code> carries the user's free-text reason from the JSONL file into memory; the parse pipeline marks suppressed findings instead of dropping them; render paths (UI, HTML, plain-text) continue to filter via <code>isSuppressed</code>; the SARIF export iterates ALL findings and attaches a <code>suppressions[]</code> block (kind: external, state: accepted, justification: the user's reason) per SARIF v2.1.0 §3.34. GitHub Code Scanning, SonarQube, and the VSCode SARIF Viewer now see the full audit picture and can compute fires-vs-suppressions ratios across export boundaries. Locked by a five-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/audit_sarif_suppressions</code>) that flips red against pre-fix source on seven assertions.</li>
          <li><em>Regex-DoS watchdog on user-supplied audit patterns (isCatastrophicRegex, hardenUserRegex, applyFilter, loadAllowlist).</em> Was: user patterns from <code>audit_rules.json</code> (<code>OutputFilter::dropIfMatches</code>) and <code>.audit_allowlist.json</code> (<code>AllowlistEntry::lineRegex</code>) flowed straight into QRegularExpression with no shape check and no match-time bound. A pathological pattern committed in either file could pin the GUI thread for seconds with classic catastrophic backtracking on adversarial scanner output (<code>(.+)+</code>, <code>(\w*)*</code>, <code>(.*)+</code> against long lines). Now: a static <code>isCatastrophicRegex</code> heuristic rejects nested-quantifier shapes at compile time with a qWarning naming the offending pattern; the rule keeps running without the filter rather than refusing to load. Patterns that pass the shape check are wrapped in PCRE2's <code>(*LIMIT_MATCH=100000)</code> inline option via <code>hardenUserRegex</code> so even catastrophic shapes that slip past the heuristic have a bounded match-step budget — PCRE2 returns "no match" on overrun (fail-safe). 100k steps handles every sane pattern (typical match completes in &lt; 1k) and aborts adversarial patterns within milliseconds. Locked by a four-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/audit_regex_dos_watchdog</code>).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Widen <code>computeDedup</code> from 64 to 96 bits (computeDedup, AuditDialog::isSuppressed, Finding::dedupKey).</em> Was: SHA-256 truncated to 16 hex chars (64 bits) — same key serves as the SARIF partialFingerprint, the suppression-JSONL key, the rule-quality bucket, and the in-app "Suppress" anchor URL. The 64-bit collision threshold (~2^32 entries at 50% collision probability) was comfortable but tight given the multi-role usage; a single false-collision cost a wrong-finding suppression. Now: <code>.left(24)</code> (96 bits) raises the birthday threshold to ~2^48 for 8 extra bytes per stored key — well past any plausible project's lifetime collection. A new <code>bool AuditDialog::isSuppressed(const QString &amp;dedupKey) const</code> helper encapsulates a backward-compat lookup: match either the full 24-char key OR the leading 16-char prefix, so existing pre-0.7.29 user <code>~/.audit_suppress</code> entries continue to suppress new 24-char findings without forcing a migration. Six render-pipeline call sites that previously read <code>m_suppressedKeys.contains(f.dedupKey)</code> now route through the helper. Locked by a four-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/audit_dedup_96bit</code>) that flips red against pre-fix source on five assertions.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.28" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Audit pipeline I — process-side robustness. Three ROADMAP § 0.7.12 Tier 2 items shipped together as bundle 0.7.28: per-tool timeout overrides, incremental QProcess output drain with a 64 MiB cap, and a distinct tool-crash warning that no longer hides as "0 findings."</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>AuditCheck::timeoutMs — per-check QProcess timeout.</em> Was: <code>m_timeout->start(30000)</code> hard-coded for every check, with the timeout-handler lambda printing a literal "Timed out (30s)" warning. Slow tools (cppcheck on a 500k-line tree, semgrep, osv-scanner, trufflehog, clang-tidy, clazy on Qt-heavy code) routinely exceeded the 30 s cap and got demoted to tool-health warnings instead of producing findings. Now: <code>int timeoutMs = 30000;</code> trailing field on AuditCheck (default preserves the pre-fix global), <code>m_timeout->start(check.timeoutMs)</code> at the use site, and a calibration loop at the end of populateChecks bumps known-slow tools to 60 s / 90 s / 120 s. Locked by a four-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/audit_per_tool_timeout</code>) that flips red against pre-fix source.</li>
          <li><em>Incremental QProcess output drain with 64 MiB cap.</em> Was: <code>readAllStandardOutput()</code> called once inside onCheckFinished. QProcess buffered without bound — a runaway semgrep against generated code could buffer hundreds of MB before the timeout fired. Now: ctor wires readyReadStandardOutput / readyReadStandardError to new drain slots that append to <code>m_currentOutput</code> / <code>m_currentError</code> incrementally; on overflow the process is killed and <code>m_outputOverflowed</code> is flagged. onCheckFinished reads from the buffers instead of the live process and surfaces a distinct "Output exceeded N MiB cap" warning when overflow occurred. A new connectProcessSignals helper centralises the three connections so the kill / reconnect cycles never lose a drain slot. Locked by a six-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/audit_incremental_output_drain</code>).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Tool-crash distinct from "no findings" (AuditDialog::onCheckFinished).</em> Was: <code>void onCheckFinished(int /*exitCode*/, QProcess::ExitStatus /*status*/)</code> — both parameters discarded. A tool that segfaulted with empty stdout was indistinguishable from a clean run; same went for clang-tidy missing compile_commands.json (non-zero exit, stderr-only). Now: parameters named, function branches on QProcess::CrashExit to emit a "Tool crashed" warning; on non-zero-exit-with-stderr-only to emit a "Tool exited N" warning. Both demoted to Severity::Info so they don't sort to the top of the report. The four exit modes (timeout / overflow / crash / non-zero-with-stderr-only) funnel through a single makeToolHealthWarning helper that centralises the row shape. Locked by a four-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/audit_tool_crash_distinct</code>).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.27" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>PTY-handler hardening sweep. Two 0.7.12 ROADMAP Tier 2 items shipped together — child-side FD closure no longer relies on a hard-coded <code>fd&lt;1024</code> cap, and master-side writes no longer drop data on EAGAIN.</p>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>PTY child uses <code>close_range(2)</code> with RLIMIT_NOFILE-bounded fallback (<code>Pty::start</code>).</em> Was: <code>for (int fd = 3; fd &lt; 1024; ++fd) ::close(fd)</code> — silently leaked any inherited FD with index ≥ 1024 into the user's shell on systemd-service / container / hardened-server profiles. Qt's display socket, D-Bus session connection, plugin HTTP sockets, Lua VM eventfds, and the remote-control IPC socket are all valid leak candidates; a leaked AI HTTP socket is a credentials-exfiltration vector, a leaked D-Bus socket lets the shell impersonate the user's desktop session, a leaked remote-control socket is a UID-scope RCE-by-proxy vector. Now: post-fork child branch issues <code>::syscall(SYS_close_range, 3, ~0U, 0)</code> first — single signal-safe syscall on Linux 5.9+, atomic over the whole range, ignores the soft cap. Fallback path consults <code>getrlimit(RLIMIT_NOFILE)</code> and iterates up to the runtime soft cap, capped at 65536 to bound the worst-case syscall storm on profiles where <code>rlim_cur</code> is in the hundreds of thousands. Locked by a five-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/pty_closefrom</code>) that flips red against pre-fix source.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>Pty::write</code> queues on EAGAIN instead of dropping bytes (<code>Pty::write</code>, new <code>Pty::onWriteReady</code>).</em> Was: the master FD is non-blocking, so a slow consumer on the slave side could fill the kernel PTY buffer; on EAGAIN the write loop broke out with the comment "EAGAIN or fatal error", silently dropping the unwritten remainder. Provoked by realistic bursts — large pastes, AI-dialog command insertions, plugin-driven keystroke floods, or writes into a slave whose reader is suspended. Now: a new <code>m_pendingWrite</code> byte buffer plus a <code>QSocketNotifier(QSocketNotifier::Write)</code> on the master FD (initially disabled — PTY masters are writable nearly continuously and a hot notifier would burn CPU). On EAGAIN the remainder is queued, the notifier enabled; when the kernel signals writability <code>onWriteReady</code> drains and disables. Fresh <code>write()</code> calls during a non-empty queue append rather than bypass, preserving FIFO ordering. Queue capped at 4 MiB so a permanently-stuck slave cannot OOM the GUI. Locked by a seven-invariant regression test (<code>tests/features/pty_write_eagain_queue</code>) that flips red against pre-fix source.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.26" date="2026-04-25">
      <description>
        <p>Menubar opacity — the actual root-cause fix. 0.7.25's palette + widget-local-QSS belt-and-suspenders did not in fact suspend any belt: the user reported the desktop wallpaper still showing through the menubar strip on KWin + Breeze + Qt 6.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Menubar background now actually paints opaquely under <code>WA_TranslucentBackground</code> (<code>OpaqueMenuBar</code>, <code>MainWindow::applyTheme</code>).</em> User report 2026-04-25: "I can clearly see my desktop background behind it." Root cause: under <code>WA_TranslucentBackground</code> parent + <code>WA_OpaquePaintEvent</code> on the menubar, none of the conventional opaque-paint paths runs reliably on every WM/style stack. <code>autoFillBackground</code> is suppressed by <code>WA_OpaquePaintEvent</code> (the contract is "the widget paints all pixels"), <code>QPalette::Window</code> is only consulted by <code>autoFillBackground</code> and inherits the suppression, and QSS <code>QMenuBar { background-color: … }</code> — which is supposed to draw via <code>QStyleSheetStyle::drawControl(CE_MenuBarEmptyArea)</code> — is silently skipped on KWin + Breeze + Qt 6 when <code>WA_OpaquePaintEvent</code> is set, because the QSS engine assumes the widget owns those pixels. Net effect: every safeguard 0.7.25 added was correctly installed and not painting anything; the menubar surface stayed cleared-to-transparent and the compositor showed the wallpaper through. New file <code>src/opaquemenubar.h</code> defines <code>OpaqueMenuBar</code>, a <code>QMenuBar</code> subclass whose <code>paintEvent</code> runs <code>QPainter::fillRect(rect(), m_bg)</code> with <code>CompositionMode_Source</code> before delegating to <code>QMenuBar::paintEvent</code>. <code>m_menuBar</code> is now an <code>OpaqueMenuBar</code> and <code>applyTheme</code> sets the fill colour via <code>setBackgroundFill(theme.bgSecondary)</code>. Regression test <code>tests/features/menubar_hover_stylesheet</code> extended with INV-8 — three new assertions pinning the construction site, the <code>setBackgroundFill</code> call, and the presence of <code>paintEvent</code> + <code>fillRect</code> inside <code>opaquemenubar.h</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.25" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Memory-DoS hardening on OSC 8 hyperlinks and Kitty APC graphics chunks, plus a menubar-opacity fix reported mid-session. Locked by a 5-invariant regression test that flips red against pre-fix source.</p>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>OSC 8 URI cap and Kitty APC chunk-buffer cap (<code>TerminalGrid</code>).</em> Two attacker-controlled accumulators used to be bounded only by the VT parser's per-envelope 10 MB ceiling. A hostile program could emit one <code>\x1b]8;;&lt;10MB-URI&gt;\x07</code> per scrollback line and wedge tens of GB into per-row <code>HyperlinkSpan</code> copies, or keep sending <code>\x1b_G...,m=1,...\x07</code> frames without ever closing with <code>m=0</code>, growing <code>m_kittyChunkBuffer</code> unbounded. <code>src/terminalgrid.h</code> now declares <code>MAX_OSC8_URI_BYTES = 2048</code> and <code>MAX_KITTY_CHUNK_BYTES = 32 MiB</code>. Oversized OSC 8 URIs take the invalid-scheme drop path so following text prints unlinked; the APC chunk path clears and <code>shrink_to_fit</code>s the staging buffer on cap breach so a subsequent <code>m=0</code> sees an empty buffer rather than attacker-prepended garbage.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Menubar renders opaque under <code>WA_TranslucentBackground</code> (<code>MainWindow::applyTheme</code>).</em> User report 2026-04-25: "the background of the menubar is transparent." The top-level QSS cascade could race with the compositor damage rect, letting whatever sat behind the window bleed through before polish. <code>applyTheme</code> now installs a belt-and-suspenders opaque fill on <code>m_menuBar</code> — <code>QPalette::Window = theme.bgSecondary</code> so <code>autoFillBackground</code> lays down an opaque fill before QSS paints, plus a widget-local <code>setStyleSheet(QMenuBar ...)</code> block so the menubar's own style engine polishes independently of the top-level cascade. Mirrors the pattern already used on the custom title bar and status bar.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.24" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Wide-char (CJK / wide emoji) overwrite no longer strands its mate. 0.7.12 Tier 2 hardening item. Locked by a 5-subcase behavioral regression test that flips 4 subcases red against pre-fix source.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Wide-char overwrite now zeroes the stranded mate (<code>TerminalGrid</code>).</em> A wide character occupies two adjacent cells — a first half (<code>isWideChar=true</code>, codepoint=CP) and a continuation (<code>isWideCont=true</code>, codepoint=0). Before this release, three write paths left half-pairs in an inconsistent state when a new write landed on only one half: narrow writes over a continuation left the mate at <code>col-1</code> still claiming <code>isWideChar=true</code> with no neighbor (rendered with a gap); narrow writes over a first half left the old continuation at <code>col+1</code> claiming <code>isWideCont=true</code> with no mate (blocked selection / copy); a wide write shifted by one from an existing wide pair orphaned the old continuation at <code>col+2</code>; and the SIMD-coalesced fast path <code>handleAsciiPrintRun</code> had the same left/right edge issues on its write span. Consolidated into a single <code>breakWidePairsAround(row, startCol, endCol)</code> helper that runs before every write site.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.23" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>xterm-compatible Background Color Erase (BCE) across every scroll and erase path. 0.7.12 Tier 2 hardening item. Locked by a 10-subcase behavioral regression test that flips 5 subcases red against pre-fix source.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>BCE on scroll and insert/delete paths.</em> Apps that paint with a non-default SGR background (<code>\e[44m</code> etc.) and then scroll, insert lines, delete lines, delete chars, or insert blanks expect the newly-exposed cells to inherit the current background — the xterm convention vim, less, tmux, mc, and htop rely on for full-screen painted backgrounds. Pre-fix, <code>takeBlankedCellsRow()</code> hardcoded the default bg, so <code>CSI L</code> / <code>CSI M</code> / <code>CSI S</code> / <code>CSI T</code> and the LF-past-scroll-bottom auto-scroll all produced default-bg gaps through painted regions. <code>deleteChars</code> and <code>insertBlanks</code> used raw current-attrs bg without the validity fallback that <code>clearRow</code> already had. Consolidated the policy into one <code>TerminalGrid::eraseBg()</code> helper; every erase/scroll callsite now reads from it.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.22" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>User ask 2026-04-24 — "How do I see what version of Ants Terminal I am running? Can you please add a GUI version?"</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Help → About Ants Terminal…</em> — new rightmost menu carrying a rich-text About dialog that shows the running <code>ANTS_VERSION</code>, the Qt runtime version, the Lua engine version (when compiled with <code>ANTS_LUA_PLUGINS</code>), and a clickable GitHub homepage link. Plus a second action <em>About Qt…</em> routing to Qt's stock aboutQt dialog. Version is read directly from the CMake-defined <code>ANTS_VERSION</code> macro — no hardcoded literal that could drift on bumps.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.21" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Lua sandbox hardening trio from the 0.7.12 /indie-review. Three small defense-in-depth fixes in <code>LuaEngine</code>, all locked by a behavioral + source-grep regression test that flips 5 of 9 invariants red against pre-fix source.</p>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>string.dump</code> removed from the plugin sandbox.</em> Lua 5.4 has no bytecode verifier — <code>string.dump(f)</code> returns bytecode that a crafted loader call could execute, corrupting state and escaping the sandbox. <code>load</code>/<code>loadstring</code>/<code>loadfile</code> are already nilled at init, but any future C API wrapping <code>luaL_loadbuffer</code> with plugin-supplied data would reopen the surface. Closed at the sandbox layer via <code>lua_setfield</code> on the already-loaded string table.</li>
          <li><em><code>LuaEngine::loadScript</code> forces <code>"t"</code> (text-only) load mode.</em> Pre-fix, <code>luaL_dofile</code> forwarded to <code>luaL_loadfilex</code> with <code>mode=nullptr</code>, accepting both text and binary chunks. The 0x1b-first-byte peek was the first rejection gate; the loader call is now the second gate, so a future refactor that drops the peek still gets a rejection.</li>
          <li><em>Instruction-count hook cleared before <code>lua_close</code> in <code>shutdown</code>.</em> <code>lua_close</code> runs pending <code>__gc</code> metamethods which can execute arbitrary Lua code. If the hook fires mid-close and walks back into registry data via <code>__ants_engine</code>, that's a UAF window. <code>lua_sethook(m_state, nullptr, 0, 0)</code> before the close removes that window; C-side cleanup proceeds without any Lua-level observer.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.20" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Tier 2 hardening sweep — three open items from the 0.7.12 /indie-review landed as one release. Each fix has a behavioral regression test, source-grep on the load-bearing tokens, and was verified to fail against pre-fix source via <code>git stash</code> before locking. All 71 fast tests green.</p>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>debug.log</code> lands 0600 regardless of umask.</em> The debug log was being created with the process umask (typically 0644 under 0022). The log can include PTY keystrokes, AI endpoint request + response bodies, OSC 133 HMAC digest material, and Claude transcript parse state. <code>DebugLog::setActive</code> now calls <code>setOwnerOnlyPerms</code> on both the opened <code>QFileDevice</code> and the path string immediately after open — the fd-level call covers the just-opened descriptor; the path-level call narrows any pre-existing 0644 file that append reused from a prior (pre-fix) run.</li>
          <li><em>Audit path-traversal guard on finding <code>file</code> fields.</em> User-supplied audit rules, <code>audit_rules.json</code> in a cloned project, and external scanner regex outputs can all produce findings whose <code>file</code> field is a traversal payload (<code>../../etc/passwd</code> style). Pre-fix, six call sites across <code>AuditDialog</code> concatenated <code>m_projectPath + "/" + f.file</code> and passed the result to snippet preview, comment classifier, inline-suppress scan, and the AI-triage POST body — a CWE-22 + OWASP-LLM06 exfiltration chain because the AI-triage surface forwards snippet contents to the configured chat-completions endpoint. New <code>AuditDialog::resolveProjectPath</code> helper canonicalizes the candidate path (resolves <code>..</code> + dereferences symlinks in a single <code>QFileInfo::canonicalFilePath</code> call), requires the result to sit under the canonical project root with an anchored-slash prefix, and returns empty on rejection. All six call sites migrated.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Settings dialog discarded on external config reload.</em> <code>MainWindow</code> caches the Settings dialog across Preferences… opens; the dialog was constructed with the Config pointer and populated its widgets at construction. When <code>QFileSystemWatcher</code> fired on an external edit, the Config pointer's target was reassigned fresh from disk but the cached dialog still held pre-reload widget state. Next Preferences… open would show stale values, and clicking OK would replay them over the fresh Config — silently undoing the external edit. <code>onConfigFileChanged</code> now closes the dialog if visible, schedules it via <code>deleteLater()</code>, and nulls the pointer so the next open rebuilds from the freshly reloaded Config.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.19" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>CI un-break + tab-rename persistence. CI had been red since 0.7.17 on the AppStream metainfo validation step because the 0.7.17 release description embedded a plaintext <code>https://</code> URL as an example of what the new secret-redactor scrubs, which the validator correctly rejects. Rewrote the example to use a non-URL inline form. Separately, user asked whether manual tab renames survive Ants restart — they didn't, because the pin map lived only in MainWindow memory. Fixed by bumping the session-file schema to V3 with a trailing <code>pinnedTitle</code> field.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Manual tab renames persist across Ants Terminal sessions.</em> The right-click "Rename Tab…" pin (<code>m_tabTitlePins</code>) is now written to and read from each per-tab session file. A tab renamed to "Deploy" or "Prod DB" or "Claude #3" keeps that label after the app exits and relaunches. <code>SessionManager</code> schema bumped to V3: a trailing <code>QString pinnedTitle</code> field appended after the V2 <code>cwd</code>. V2 files continue to load with the pin out-param defaulting to empty.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>AppStream metainfo validation passes again.</em> The 0.7.17 and 0.7.18 release descriptions failed <code>appstreamcli validate --explain</code> with <code>description-has-plaintext-url</code>. Example rewritten to non-URL form; CI build-test step now green.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>SessionManager::restore</code> initializes optional out-params before reading.</em> Callers that pre-populated <code>QString *cwd</code> or <code>QString *pinnedTitle</code> would previously see their sentinel survive an older-format load. Fixed by clearing both at function entry; the version-gated read blocks still only populate them when the on-disk format actually has the field.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.18" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Post-0.7.17 documentation + tech-debt sweep. Three parallel audit agents (doc drift, source debt, spec-vs-code drift) inventoried every doc-vs-code mismatch, stale TODO, dead config key, and spec line-number drift across the tree. Two real bugs landed: the Settings → General Shell picker now actually launches the user's chosen shell (previously persisted to config.json but silently dropped by the PTY launch path), and <code>Qt::WA_OpaquePaintEvent</code> on the menubar closes the remaining mouse-move-over-menubar dropdown flicker on KWin. The <code>background_alpha</code> config key was removed as redundant — user confirmed the <code>opacity</code> knob already does what they want (translucent terminal area, solid chrome).</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>Config::shellCommand()</code> actually launches the user's shell.</em> Settings → General's Shell picker (Default / bash / zsh / fish / Custom…) has persisted the user's choice to <code>shell_command</code> in <code>config.json</code> since the original implementation, and the Settings dialog loads/re-displays it correctly. But <code>TerminalWidget::startShell</code> took only a working directory and invoked <code>VtStream::start</code> with a hardcoded empty shell arg — <code>Pty::start</code>'s empty-shell fallback (<code>$SHELL</code> → <code>pw_shell</code> → <code>/bin/bash</code>) always fired, silently dropping the user's choice. Fix: <code>startShell</code> gains a <code>shell</code> parameter, the <code>QMetaObject::invokeMethod</code> call forwards it instead of <code>QString()</code>, and every production call site in <code>MainWindow</code> passes <code>m_config.shellCommand()</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Dropdown flicker on mouse-move over open menubar item (KWin).</em> The menubar's <code>autoFillBackground</code> + stylesheet fully cover every pixel on every paint, so marking it opaque-on-paint stops Qt from invalidating the translucent parent's compositor region under it. <code>MainWindow</code> ctor now sets <code>Qt::WA_OpaquePaintEvent</code> on <code>m_menuBar</code> — the QSS comment always promised this was set at the construction site; the call itself was missing. Flagged in 0.7.12 Tier 3.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>README.md config-defaults table corrected.</em> <code>session_persistence</code> default was shown as <code>false</code> but the code default in <code>config.cpp</code> is <code>true</code>. <code>font_size</code> range was shown as 8–32 but the code range is 4–48. Both corrected.</li>
          <li><em>PLUGINS.md Lua resource-limit docs.</em> Previously claimed limits are enforced "per plugin per event invocation" with each event getting a fresh 10 M-instruction budget. The implementation sets <code>lua_sethook(LUA_MASKCOUNT, 10000000)</code> once at engine init; the counter accumulates across all handlers in the same VM until the hook fires. Doc rewritten to describe the real contract.</li>
          <li><em><code>tests/features/terminal_partial_update_mode/spec.md</code> rewritten to match the live test.</em> The <code>.cpp</code> test was updated in 0.7.4 to enforce the post-refactor invariant (TerminalWidget is a plain <code>QWidget</code>, no <code>QOpenGLWidget::</code> calls), but the adjacent <code>spec.md</code> still documented the pre-0.7.4 <code>setUpdateBehavior(PartialUpdate)</code> fix that didn't work. Spec now matches the test.</li>
          <li><em>Spec line-number drift corrected</em> in four spec.md files: <code>osc133_hmac_verification</code>, <code>session_persistence_default</code>, <code>review_changes_click</code>, <code>ai_context_redaction</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Removed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>background_alpha</code> config key + <code>Config::backgroundAlpha()</code> / <code>setBackgroundAlpha()</code> + <code>TerminalWidget::setBackgroundAlpha</code> / <code>backgroundAlpha</code> + <code>m_backgroundAlpha</code> member.</em> User confirmed (2026-04-24) they use <code>opacity</code> ~0.9-0.95 to make the terminal area translucent while chrome stays solid — exactly what the <code>opacity</code> config key already does (paint site applies per-pixel alpha via <code>m_windowOpacity</code>). Since <code>background_alpha</code> had no UI widget, no paint-site consumer, and overlapped intent with <code>opacity</code>, removed entirely. Stale key in existing <code>config.json</code> files is harmlessly ignored on load (Qt's JSON parser tolerates unknown keys).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.17" date="2026-04-24">
      <description>
        <p>Hot-path parser optimization plus two /indie-review security follow-ups. VtParser printable-ASCII runs now coalesce into a single <code>VtAction</code> carrying a pointer+length slice of the feed buffer, and <code>TerminalGrid::handleAsciiPrintRun</code> batches per-row cell writes so <code>markScreenDirty</code>, the combining-char erase, and the <code>cell()</code> clamp all fire once per row instead of once per byte. Rebench on 8 MiB corpora: <code>ascii_print</code> 24.4 → 30.7 MB/s (+26%), <code>ansi_sgr</code> 27.5 → 31.4 MB/s (+14%). RIS (<code>ESC c</code>) now preserves all 8 integration callbacks — previously <code>tput reset</code> silenced desktop notifications, progress bars, command-finished plugin events, user-var theming hooks, and the OSC 133 HMAC forgery alarm permanently. Two new token-saving developer hooks for Claude Code users land alongside the perf work: a <code>UserPromptSubmit</code> git-context hook that feeds <code>&lt;git-context&gt;</code> to Claude on every prompt (saving ~400–600 tokens per turn that would otherwise go to a <code>Bash(git status)</code> call), and OWASP LLM06 secret redaction on the outbound AI-dialog request body.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Claude Code <code>UserPromptSubmit</code> git-context hook.</em> New Settings button "Install git-context hook" installs <code>~/.config/ants-terminal/hooks/claude-git-context.sh</code> and merges a <code>hooks.UserPromptSubmit</code> entry into <code>~/.claude/settings.json</code>. The script emits a compact <code>&lt;git-context&gt;</code> block (branch, upstream, ahead/behind counts, staged / unstaged / untracked file counts) on every user prompt so Claude Code sees repo state without spending tokens on a <code>Bash(git status)</code> round-trip. Global scope — installed at user level so every project inherits. No-op outside git repos / when <code>git</code> isn't on PATH.</li>
          <li><em><code>src/secretredact.h</code> — OWASP LLM06 defense layer.</em> Header-only module exposing <code>SecretRedact::scrub(QString)</code>. Regex-scrubs 14 well-known secret shapes: AWS AKIA/ASIA, GitHub classic / OAuth / app / fine-grained PATs, Anthropic, OpenAI project + legacy, Slack, Stripe, JWT, <code>Bearer &lt;token&gt;</code> headers, generic <code>api_key=</code>/<code>token=</code>/<code>password=</code>/<code>secret=</code> assignments, and multi-line PEM private-key blocks. Replacements are <code>[REDACTED:&lt;kind&gt;]</code> so the LLM still sees the surrounding command shape. Priority-ordered so <code>sk-ant-</code> is labelled <code>anthropic</code>, not mislabelled as legacy <code>openai</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>VtAction</code> carries an optional coalesced Print run.</em> Two new fields point into the caller's feed buffer (valid for the duration of the <code>ActionCallback</code> call only). <code>VtStream::onPtyData</code>'s batch path materializes runs into per-byte <code>Print</code> actions before queuing for the GUI thread, since its batch outlives the feed buffer. Lifetime invariant documented in <code>vtparser.h</code>.</li>
          <li><em><code>AiDialog::sendRequest</code> scrubs both outbound strings.</em> The terminal scrollback context and the user's own question both pass through <code>SecretRedact::scrub</code> before reaching the JSON body. When <code>redactedCount &gt; 0</code>, the dialog appends a System chat-history note so the user knows the payload differs from what they saw. Chat history's "You:" display intentionally shows pre-redaction text (redaction is a network-boundary concern, not a UX one).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Claude allowlist <code>settings.local.json</code> perms survive rename fallback.</em> <code>ClaudeAllowlistDialog::saveSettings</code> previously set 0600 only on the <code>QSaveFile</code> temp fd. Most local filesystems preserve fd perms across <code>rename(2)</code>, but FAT/exFAT on removable media don't carry POSIX perm bits, some SMB/NFS servers apply umask to the rename destination, and Qt's <code>QSaveFile::commit</code> falls back to copy+unlink on cross-device renames — in all three cases the final file landed at the process umask (typically 0644). Since the file can hold Claude Code bearer tokens, the widened perms were a credential-leak surface. Fix: after <code>commit()</code> returns true, re-apply <code>setOwnerOnlyPerms</code> on the final path (the pre-commit fd-level chmod is retained — neither call subsumes the other). Flagged by the 2026-04-23 <code>/indie-review</code>.</li>
          <li><em>AI context + user-message secret redaction (OWASP LLM06).</em> The AI dialog previously shipped recent scrollback verbatim to whichever endpoint the user had configured — a single <code>cat .env</code>, <code>aws configure show</code>, or <code>git clone</code> with an embedded <code>ghp_</code> token in the URL in scrollback exfiltrated credentials. Complements the 0.7.12 LLM01/LLM02 fix (<code>ai_insert_command_sanitize</code>) — that handled AI → PTY; this handles PTY → AI.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Right-click "Rename Tab…" pins the label.</em> User report 2026-04-24: Claude Code's per-prompt OSC 0/2 title writes wiped manual tab names within seconds. The rename handler wrote directly to <code>setTabText</code> without populating <code>m_tabTitlePins</code>, so the per-shell <code>titleChanged</code> handler and the 2 s tick both saw no pin and relabelled. Rename now routes through <code>setTabTitleForRemote</code> so non-empty names pin and empty names clear the pin — giving the user an in-UI "un-rename" path that didn't exist before.</li>
          <li><em>RIS (<code>ESC c</code>) preserves all 8 integration callbacks + <code>m_osc133Key</code>.</em> Previously <code>notifyCallback</code>, <code>progressCallback</code>, <code>lineCompletionCallback</code>, <code>commandFinishedCallback</code>, <code>userVarCallback</code>, and <code>osc133ForgeryCallback</code> silently became empty functions after any <code>tput reset</code>. Security impact for the forgery alarm: a well-timed reset silenced it permanently, enabling OSC 133 forgery to proceed unseen. <code>m_osc133Key</code> (read from <code>$ANTS_OSC133_KEY</code> at process start) also survives RIS.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Performance:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>VtParser printable-ASCII run coalescing.</em> SIMD fast path (<code>scanSafeAsciiRun</code> on SSE2/NEON) emits one <code>VtAction::Print</code> per run instead of one per byte. For a 10 KB TUI-repaint PTY read, allocation count drops from ~10 000 to 1 and dispatch count drops by the same factor. 8 MiB <code>ascii_print</code> 327 → 260 ms (−20%), <code>ansi_sgr</code> 291 → 255 ms (−12%). <code>newline_stream</code> and <code>utf8_cjk</code> are bound by scroll and UTF-8 decoding respectively, so their numbers are flat — no coalesce-applicable runs.</li>
          <li><em><code>TerminalGrid::handleAsciiPrintRun</code> batches per-row writes.</em> Skips the per-byte <code>wcwidth</code>, combining-char branch, wide-char branch, and <code>std::clamp</code> inside <code>cell()</code>. Fires <code>markScreenDirty</code> once per row instead of once per byte.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.16" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Per-tab Claude Code activity indicator — a small state-dependent dot at the leading edge of each tab whose shell has a Claude Code child process, so users running Claude across several tabs can see at a glance which one is waiting on them without cycling focus. Permission prompts route by the hook event's <code>session_id</code> (matched against the <code>&lt;session-uuid&gt;.jsonl</code> transcript filename) rather than the active-tab heuristic, so a prompt emitted in tab 3 lights up tab 3 specifically.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Per-tab Claude activity dot.</em> Colour encodes state: muted grey for Idle / Thinking, blue for generic ToolUse, green for Bash (split out as the highest-signal tool), cyan for Planning, violet for Compacting, and a bright orange dot with a white outline for AwaitingInput. Hover tooltip on each tab spells out the state ("Claude: thinking…", "Claude: Bash", etc.) so colours can be disambiguated without switching tabs.</li>
          <li><em>Settings → General: "Show per-tab Claude activity dot" checkbox.</em> Flips <code>claude_tab_status_indicator</code> (default on); change takes effect on the next paint via the live config reload path, no restart needed.</li>
          <li><em>New <code>src/claudetabtracker.{h,cpp}</code>.</em> Keys state by shell PID so tab reorder / close doesn't shift entries, and reuses the existing transcript parser through a shared static helper — no duplicated parsing logic. Contract and 11-invariant regression test at <code>tests/features/claude_tab_status_indicator/</code>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>ClaudeIntegration::parseTranscriptForState</code> refactored to a thin wrapper around a new static <code>parseTranscriptTail</code> helper.</em> Pure function, no side effects — safe to call from per-shell trackers. Behavior unchanged; <code>claude_status_bar</code> and <code>claude_plan_mode_detection</code> regression tests still green against the same transcripts.</li>
          <li><em>Hook events stash <code>session_id</code> in <code>ClaudeIntegration::lastHookSessionId()</code>.</em> Handlers of signals emitted by <code>processHookEvent</code> (e.g. <code>permissionRequested</code>) can now read the id to route the event per-session rather than treating every hook as "belongs to the active tab" — required for the per-tab indicator to flag the correct tab on PermissionRequest.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.15" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Fold-in of the 2026-04-23 re-review follow-up list. Six of nine items had already shipped in 0.7.12 but were never crossed off the ROADMAP; the remaining three are real new work — a <code>/tmp/kwin_*.js</code> orphan sweep, a behavioral replacement for a fragile source-grep gate test, and a signal-count assertion on the plan-mode tail-preservation path. Two new regression tests lock existing invariants.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Startup sweep for orphan <code>/tmp/kwin_*_ants_*.js</code> script files.</em> KWin helper scripts are written via <code>QTemporaryFile(autoRemove=false)</code> and removed by a chained dbus callback after KWin unloads them; a crash, SIGKILL, or dbus hang between write and unload orphans the file. <code>MainWindow</code> ctor now runs a once-per-process sweep of <code>kwin_{pos,move,center}_ants_*.js</code> older than one hour, avoiding a race with any in-flight script another Ants instance just wrote.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Remote-control opt-in gate test is now behavioral, not source-grep.</em> The 0.7.12 test grepped for <code>remoteControlEnabled()</code> within 400 chars of <code>m_remoteControl-&gt;start()</code> — a getter rename or helper-hoist would have silently defeated the gate while still passing. Replaced with a <code>Config</code> API round-trip (default false, setter persists across instances, value readable post-reload); a getter rename now fails at compile-time. The structural "<code>start()</code> must live inside a conditional" check is retained as a plain-substring lookback to catch outright gate removal — without the catastrophic-backtracking risk that killed the initial regex attempt.</li>
          <li><em>Plan-mode regression test asserts emission count, not just final value.</em> <code>runToggleFreeTailPreservesState</code> now confirms <code>planModeChanged</code> fires exactly once across both parse phases (seed toggles NotSet → plan = one emission; tail sees zero permission-mode events and must not re-fire). Guards against a regression that re-emits on every parse.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Tests:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em><code>config_parse_failure_guard</code> adds retention-cap invariant (INV-5).</em> Plants 8 stale <code>.corrupt-*</code> siblings with decreasing mtimes, trips a fresh parse-failure, asserts only the newest 5 (fresh + 4 old) remain. Verified to fail against a neutered prune loop (got 9, expected 5). Sets mtimes via <code>QFile::setFileTime</code> since <code>QDir::Time</code> ranks on mtime, not on the filename-embedded timestamp.</li>
          <li><em><code>remote_control_opt_in</code> adds behavioral Config round-trip section.</em> Sandboxed via <code>XDG_CONFIG_HOME</code> (not <code>setTestModeEnabled</code> — that routes to a Qt-test-specific path which has collided with real user configs in practice). Four invariants: fresh-default false, in-memory round-trip, cross-instance persistence, setter-back-to-false round-trip.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Internal: ROADMAP re-review follow-up list reconciled with shipped code — config backup retention cap, remote-control gate cache, kwin TOCTOU fix header-comment accuracy, <code>spec.md</code> timestamp format, and plugin/theme parse warnings were all landed by 0.7.12 but still listed as outstanding. Flipped with "Shipped 0.7.12" notes; no code changes for these items, just book-keeping reconciliation.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.14" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Three Claude Code integration robustness fixes from the 0.7.12+1 re-review checkpoint. All three failed silently — no errors, no degraded-mode logs — so the symptoms were a transcript-driven UI state that simply stopped updating, or a project that appeared under the wrong name in the picker. All three now have targeted fixture-based regression tests.</p>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Transcript tail window grows past large trailing events.</em> <code>parseTranscriptForState</code> previously read the final 32 KB of the JSONL transcript and skipped the first line after the seek as likely-truncated; when the final event was a user <code>tool_result</code> carrying inline file contents, the window landed inside that one event and the parser returned zero events, freezing UI state. Replaced with a doubling-grow window (32 KB → 4 MiB cap) that only trims a potentially-partial prefix line when the buffer contains at least two newlines.</li>
          <li><em>Transcript dialog renders <code>thinking</code> content blocks.</em> <code>ClaudeTranscriptDialog::formatEntry</code> only handled <code>text</code>, <code>tool_use</code>, and <code>tool_result</code>; <code>thinking</code> fell into an implicit else and was discarded. Now rendered as italicized, dimmed <code>Thinking:</code> paragraphs, distinguishing chain-of-thought from the visible reply.</li>
          <li><em><code>decodeProjectPath</code> preserves hyphens in project names.</em> Claude Code encodes absolute paths by replacing every <code>/</code> with <code>-</code> — lossy, since <code>my-project</code> (leaf) and <code>my/project</code> (two segments) produce the same string. The old decoder replaced every <code>-</code> with <code>/</code> unconditionally. Rewrote as a greedy left-to-right filesystem-probing walker: at each hyphen, prefer the <code>/</code> form if that directory exists, fall back to <code>-</code> otherwise. <code>extractCwdFromTranscript</code> remains the preferred source of truth; the probe-based decoder is the last-resort fallback.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Tests: new <code>claude_transcript_robustness</code> feature lane with six invariants covering tail-window growth past a 40 KB trailing event, the 4 MiB growth cap, leaf- and intermediate-segment hyphen preservation, legacy all-slashes fallback when filesystem hints are absent, and canonical repo-style decoding. Verified to fail against pre-fix code on the regression invariants.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.13" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Scope-tightening pass on the audit rule-pack trust boundary shipped in 0.7.12. The global <code>audit_trust_command_rules</code> bool over-granted after one opt-in — trusting Ants's own repo implicitly trusted every cloned repo the user later opened. 0.7.13 replaces the global flag with a per-project hash-bound trust store so trust is both narrow and self-invalidating.</p>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Per-project audit rule-pack trust store.</em> Global <code>audit_trust_command_rules</code> bool is retired. Trust is keyed on <code>(canonical projectPath, sha256(audit_rules.json bytes))</code> via three new <code>Config</code> methods: <code>isAuditRulePackTrusted</code>, <code>trustAuditRulePack</code>, <code>untrustAuditRulePack</code>. Trusting one project no longer extends to siblings; any edit to the rule pack invalidates trust (re-prompt on next open — silent post-trust modification is detected); <code>projectPath</code> is canonicalized via <code>QFileInfo::canonicalFilePath</code> so symlinks and trailing slashes resolve to a single record; <code>ANTS_AUDIT_TRUST_UNSAFE=1</code> remains an escape hatch for CI. Users with the legacy bool set to <code>true</code> are re-prompted per project on upgrade.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Audit dialog: "Untrusted rules: N" badge.</em> The skipped-rule count now appears on the Detected-types row alongside "User rules: N" and "Path rules: N", with a tooltip explaining the trust boundary and opt-in path. Stderr <code>qWarning</code> copy retained for headless / CI cases.</li>
          <li><em><code>CLAUDE.md</code> streamlined.</em> Compressed from 325 to 147 lines (~67% reduction) by dropping the full project-structure tree, collapsing the verbose audit pipeline prose, retiring the per-dep install-command list, and dropping the Config-keys table. Retained: non-obvious gotchas, rationale for design decisions, and the release-file triad rule.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Tests: new <code>tests/features/audit_command_rule_trust/</code> lane — seven-invariant regression test against the new trust API (default-untrusted, round-trip, hash-bound invalidation, cross-project isolation with byte-identical packs, path canonicalization through symlinks + trailing slashes, idempotent untrust, cross-<code>Config</code>-instance persistence through <code>config.json</code>). Spec-first: contract written before the code.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.12" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Independent-review sweep. A multi-agent <code>/indie-review</code> run across 14 subsystems surfaced 60 HIGH findings; the ship-this-week tier landed in this tag, followed by a re-review of the shipped batch that caught three more HIGH findings of the same shape, plus a polish pass handling the six mechanical follow-ups. Every fix carries a regression test anchored to an external signal — published spec, CVE, real on-disk data — not to the author's own reasoning. Closes the self-graded-homework loop.</p>
        <p>Security:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Remote-control opt-in by default.</em> New <code>remote_control_enabled</code> config key (default <code>false</code>, matches Kitty's <code>allow_remote_control=no</code>). <code>send-text</code> payloads pass through a C0 control-char filter stripping <code>{0x00..0x08, 0x0B..0x1F, 0x7F}</code> while preserving HT/LF/CR and UTF-8 multi-byte, unless the request carries <code>"raw": true</code>. Closes the UID-scope keystroke-injection chain. The gate snapshots once per process (static bool) so a second window reading the config after a runtime toggle matches the "requires restart" documentation.</li>
          <li><em>Silent-data-loss guard at three sites</em> (<code>src/config.cpp</code>, <code>src/claudeallowlist.cpp</code>, <code>src/settingsdialog.cpp</code> — Install Claude hooks). All three now rotate the corrupt file aside via the shared <code>rotateCorruptFileAside()</code> helper (ms-precision timestamp + collision-retry up to 10 suffixes, keep-newest-5 retention cap), log the backup path, and refuse to write further until the user intervenes. Settings dialog shows the backup path in a <code>QMessageBox</code>.</li>
          <li><em><code>std::rename</code> return checked in <code>Config::save</code>.</em> Failure logs <code>errno</code> and removes the orphan tmp file instead of silently stranding it on disk.</li>
          <li><em>SSH bookmark <code>extraArgs</code> sanitizer.</em> Rejects <code>-oProxyCommand=</code>, <code>-oLocalCommand=</code>, <code>-oPermitLocalCommand=yes</code>, <code>-oMatch=exec</code>, and <code>-oKnownHostsCommand=</code> in both single-token and space-separated forms, case-insensitive. Closes the CVE-2017-1000117-adjacent RCE-via-bookmark-field surface.</li>
          <li><em>AI <code>Insert Cmd</code> sanitize + confirm.</em> New <code>AiDialog::extractAndSanitizeCommand</code> strips C0 controls (minus HT/LF/CR), DEL, C1 controls (incl. NEL U+0085), line/paragraph separators, bidi overrides (Trojan Source, CVE-2021-42574), and zero-width codepoints. Capped at 4 KiB. Click handler requires explicit <code>QMessageBox::question</code> confirmation showing the literal bytes + "N bytes filtered" footer; truncation warning fires when the 500-char preview doesn't cover the full command. OWASP LLM01 + LLM02 mitigation. Language-hint heuristic now requires the first line be a single unbroken token before stripping it.</li>
          <li><em>Audit rule-pack <code>command</code> fields gated</em> on <code>Config::auditTrustCommandRules()</code> (default <code>false</code>) or <code>ANTS_AUDIT_TRUST_UNSAFE=1</code>. A cloned-but-untrusted repo can no longer run arbitrary shell via <code>audit_rules.json</code>.</li>
          <li><em><code>/tmp/kwin_*.js</code> migrated to <code>QTemporaryFile</code></em> at three callsites. Closes the same-name symlink-swap TOCTOU and the two-instance collision.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Claude plan-mode detection.</em> Was reading <code>value("mode")</code> — a field that never appears in Claude Code v2.1.87 JSONL. Fixed to <code>permissionMode</code>; toggle-free tail scan now preserves the latched state.</li>
          <li><em>Plugin manifest + user theme parse warnings.</em> Both loaders now emit <code>qWarning</code> with the parse-error byte offset so users can find their own typos.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Tests: five new feature-test lanes in <code>tests/features/</code> (<code>claude_plan_mode_detection</code>, <code>remote_control_opt_in</code>, <code>config_parse_failure_guard</code>, <code>ssh_extra_args_sanitize</code>, <code>ai_insert_command_sanitize</code>), each anchored to a published spec, CVE, or live on-disk bytes.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.11" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Housekeeping pass — two long-deferred items from the 0.8+ queue land early, plus a ROADMAP correction. The perf item rewrites the combining-char map shift in <code>deleteChars</code> / <code>insertBlanks</code> to use node-handle <code>extract()</code> + key mutate + <code>insert()</code> instead of rebuilding the map. The security item is a defence-in-depth stat-guard around the remote-control socket's <code>/tmp</code> fallback cleanup.</p>
        <p>Changes:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Changed — combining-char map shift without rebuild</em> (<code>src/terminalgrid.cpp</code>, <code>deleteChars</code> / <code>insertBlanks</code>). Old impl built a fresh <code>std::unordered_map</code>, moved each surviving entry into it (re-hashing every key), then move-assigned it back. Rewrote to collect affected keys in two small local vectors, erase the deleted ones, then for each shift extract the node handle, mutate its integer key, and reinsert — zero bucket reallocation, zero re-hashing of the value vectors. <code>deleteChars</code> processes shifts ascending; <code>insertBlanks</code> descending. Empty-map fast-path skips the block entirely, so steady-state rows pay nothing. Tests <code>combining_on_resize</code> and <code>osc8_insert_delete_lines</code> still pass.</li>
          <li><em>Security — IPC-socket <code>/tmp</code> fallback stat-guard</em> (<code>src/remotecontrol.cpp</code>). <code>RemoteControl::start()</code> used to call <code>QLocalServer::removeServer(path)</code> unconditionally on stale-socket recovery. The <code>XDG_RUNTIME_DIR</code> path is 0700-owned and safe, but the <code>/tmp/ants-terminal-&lt;uid&gt;.sock</code> fallback lives in shared-world-writable space where a symlink or foreign file could trick us into unlinking something unrelated. Added <code>safeToUnlinkLocalSocket()</code> that <code>lstat()</code>s the path and refuses removal unless it's an actual <code>S_ISSOCK</code> owned by <code>getuid()</code>. <code>ENOENT</code> passes through. On refusal the remote-control layer disables itself with a clear log message — no silent unlink of unknown files.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — ROADMAP accuracy.</em> The 💭 entry for "Per-frame <code>QString</code> construction in the text-run accumulator" was actually shipped in 0.7.9 (both <code>TerminalWidget::paintEvent</code> and <code>GlRenderer::render</code> accumulate codepoints into a reusable <code>std::vector&lt;char32_t&gt;</code> on the <code>Run</code> struct and call <code>QString::fromUcs4(data, size)</code> once at run-push time). Promoted to ✅ with a retrospective write-up matching the free-list entry.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.10" date="2026-04-23">
      <description>
        <p>Follow-through on the 0.7.9 null-result. The <code>std::rotate</code> scroll refactor was rejected because it paid for save/restore overhead without touching the real bottleneck — the per-scroll <code>vector&lt;Cell&gt;(m_cols)</code> heap allocation for the new bottom row. This release addresses that bottleneck directly with a small free-list of <code>m_cols</code>-sized cell buffers fed by any path that discards a row (scrollback eviction, <code>scrollDown</code>, <code>insertLines</code>, <code>deleteLines</code>) and drained by paths that need a fresh blank row. Steady-state scroll work on a full scrollback runs allocator-free.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>TerminalGrid</code> cell-buffer free-list.</em> New <code>m_freeCellBuffers</code> pool (cap 4 entries) + <code>takeBlankedCellsRow()</code> / <code>returnCellsRow()</code> helpers. <code>scrollUp</code>, <code>scrollDown</code>, <code>insertLines</code>, <code>deleteLines</code> now recycle cell buffers instead of calling <code>makeRow(m_cols, …)</code> on every scroll. When scrollback hits <code>m_maxScrollback</code> and a <code>pop_front</code> evicts the oldest line, its cells vector is salvaged into the pool; the next scroll's new bottom row pulls from it (blanked in place), skipping the allocator. <code>resize()</code> clears the pool. Pool stays at 0–2 entries in normal use. All 49 feature tests pass; <code>scroll_region_rotate</code> (shipped 0.7.9 to lock the contract) verifies the invariants held across the refactor.</li>
          <li><em>Performance — <code>newline_stream</code> 5.26 → 6.09 MB/s (+15.8 %).</em> Median of ten-run pairs. Other corpora are flat to mildly improved: <code>ascii_print</code> ~23 MB/s, <code>ansi_sgr</code> ~16.5 MB/s, <code>utf8_cjk</code> 8.9 MB/s (+12 % — CJK payload also hits <code>scrollUp</code>). First perf result to validate the 0.7.9 thesis that the container shuffle was a red herring and the allocator was the actual hot spot.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.9" date="2026-04-22">
      <description>
        <p>Planned-work pass — three ROADMAP items from the 0.7.7 "deferred to 0.8+" queue investigated and shipped or rejected with findings on record. The investigations that didn't ship still left value behind (a feature-test that locks scroll-region semantics for any future refactor), and the one that did ship consolidates 13 path strings through one header and halves the per-frame <code>QString::fromUcs4</code> call count in both render paths.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — <code>scroll_region_rotate</code> feature-test.</em> Locks the observable behavior of <code>TerminalGrid::scrollUp</code> / <code>scrollDown</code>: row motion inside <code>[scrollTop, scrollBottom]</code>, outside-region invariance, main-screen scrollback push, alt-screen no push, hyperlink tracking, and <code>count &gt; regionHeight</code> clamp. Six scenarios, eight invariants. Pins the contract so the 0.8 ring-buffer-screen work can refactor safely.</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>src/configpaths.h</code>.</em> Inline namespace consolidating <code>~/.claude/projects</code>, <code>~/.claude/sessions</code>, <code>~/.claude/settings.json</code>, <code>~/.claude/projects/&lt;enc&gt;/memory/MEMORY.md</code>, and <code>~/.config/ants-terminal/hooks/claude-forward.sh</code>. 13 duplicated path-concat sites across <code>claudeintegration.cpp</code> / <code>settingsdialog.cpp</code> collapsed to one call each. Future XDG-respect pass now has a single update surface.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — render path per-run <code>QString::fromUcs4</code>.</em> Both the QPainter (<code>terminalwidget.cpp</code>) and GL (<code>glrenderer.cpp</code>) paths now accumulate codepoints into a <code>std::vector&lt;char32_t&gt;</code> per run and build the <code>QString</code> once at flush/draw time, replacing the previous <code>runText += QString::fromUcs4(&amp;cp, 1)</code> pattern that allocated a small <code>QString</code> per non-space cell and reallocated the run string on every append. Ligature shaping via <code>QTextLayout</code> still receives the run text at the same point; behaviour identical.</li>
          <li><em>Investigated, not shipped — <code>std::rotate</code> scroll refactor.</em> Measured 12–15% regression on <code>bench_vt_throughput newline_stream</code> (5.2 → 4.6 MB/s) because the common <code>count == 1</code> case has rotate paying for a save/restore cycle that <code>vector::erase + push_back</code> avoids. Real bottleneck is the per-scroll row allocation, not container shuffle. Reverted; test stays. ROADMAP updated with scrollback-push cell-reuse as the real 0.8 candidate.</li>
          <li><em>Investigated, not shipped — DialogBase / ManagedProcess.</em> ROADMAP over-sold both: only 2 dialogs use the Ok/Apply/Cancel pattern (not 6), and <code>auditdialog.cpp</code> uses one shared <code>QProcess</code> member (not 6 copies). Both deferred until more justification.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.8" date="2026-04-22">
      <description>
        <p>Audit fold-in — every regression guard the 0.7.6 / 0.7.7 hardening pass left behind is now a repo-wide detector. Three new rules in the Project Audit dialog turn the one-off sweeps into persistent guards, so the next contributor who re-introduces the pattern gets caught at audit-time.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — <code>ssh_argv_dash_host</code> audit rule (Security, Major).</em> Flags any <code>&lt;&lt; shellQuote(…host…)</code> argv construction without a preceding <code>args &lt;&lt; "--"</code> argv terminator — the CVE-2017-1000117 class. Runtime filter drops findings when the guard appears within ±5 lines (spans the <code>if (!user.isEmpty()) / else</code> split in <code>sshdialog.cpp:67-71</code>).</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>qimage_load_without_peek</code> audit rule (Qt, Minor).</em> Flags <code>.loadFromData(</code> calls that aren't tagged <code>// image-peek-ok</code> or preceded by a <code>QImageReader</code> size-peek within ±5 lines — the image-bomb DoS vector that the 0.7.6 hardening sweep fixed. Both shipped sites in <code>terminalgrid.cpp</code> (OSC 1337 PNG + Kitty graphics) carry the reviewer sign-off tag and drop cleanly.</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>setPermissions_pair_no_helper</code> audit rule (Qt, Info).</em> Hygiene nudge toward <code>setOwnerOnlyPerms()</code> from <code>src/secureio.h</code> when a raw <code>setPermissions(QFileDevice::ReadOwner | QFileDevice::WriteOwner)</code> bitmask appears. Pattern excludes the 0755 hook-script case (extra <code>|</code> flags after <code>WriteOwner</code>) so <code>settingsdialog.cpp</code>'s one literal bitmask doesn't false-fire.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — audit self-test coverage:</em> three new <code>run_rule</code> lines in <code>tests/audit_self_test.sh</code>, coverage cross-check sees the new rule ids automatically. 55/55 pass (up from 52/52).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.7" date="2026-04-22">
      <description>
        <p>The 0.7.7 planned-work pass from the hardening four-dimensional review — every item marked as planned in ROADMAP.md's 0.7.7 section is now shipped. Two de-duplication refactors, three paint-path perf hoists, four regression feature-tests locking the 0.7.6 hardening fixes.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — regression coverage for the four 0.7.7 hardening fixes:</em> <code>tests/features/osc8_insert_delete_lines/</code> (CSI L / CSI M hyperlink sync invariant), <code>tests/features/hyperlink_resize_clamp/</code> (shrink-resize clamp on the active OSC 8 start coordinates), <code>tests/features/ssh_dash_host_rejected/</code> (the <code>--</code> argv terminator against CVE-2017-1000117 class hosts, 5 scenarios), and <code>tests/features/image_bomb_png_header_peek/</code> (static source-inspection guard ensuring every <code>loadFromData</code> is peeked first). Each test is designed to fail on pre-fix code and pass now. 49 feature/fast tests total.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>setOwnerOnlyPerms</code> helper</em> (<code>src/secureio.h</code>) replaces the 11 copies of <code>file.setPermissions(QFileDevice::ReadOwner | QFileDevice::WriteOwner)</code> scattered across <code>config.cpp</code>, <code>sessionmanager.cpp</code> (×2), <code>claudeallowlist.cpp</code>, <code>auditdialog.cpp</code> (×4), <code>claudeintegration.cpp</code> (×2), <code>remotecontrol.cpp</code>, and <code>auditrulequality.cpp</code>. One typo (<code>ReadOther</code>, <code>ReadGroup</code>) away from silently widening access to files that may hold an API key. Two overloads: one for open <code>QFileDevice&amp;</code> handles, one for existing path strings. The one 0755 case in <code>settingsdialog.cpp</code> (hooks shell script — needs executable bit) stays literal by design.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>shellQuote</code> helper</em> (<code>src/shellutils.h</code>) replaces the previous static function in <code>sshdialog.cpp</code> and the re-defined lambda in <code>mainwindow.cpp::openClaudeProjectsDialog</code>. The two earlier implementations differed on empty-string and no-special-chars handling; both call sites now share one inline implementation.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — paint-path hoists:</em> <code>QFontMetrics</code> is no longer constructed per underlined cell; <code>updateFontMetrics()</code> caches <code>underlinePos</code> and <code>lineWidth</code> into members refreshed on font change. Selection bounds are now normalised once per <code>paintEvent</code> into local scalars with an inline <code>cellInSelection</code> lambda, rather than running <code>std::swap</code> + <code>std::min</code>/<code>std::max</code> per cell. Measurable on search-highlighted + selection-active frames.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>isCellSearchMatch</code> now uses <code>std::lower_bound</code> instead of linear scan.</em> <code>m_searchMatches</code> is sorted by <code>globalLine</code>; the binary search jumps to the first match at or after the target line and iterates only the matches on that line. The previous implementation self-described as "binary search" but walked the whole vector from index 0 on every cell. Expected win: 5–20% of paint time on search-highlighted content in deep scrollback.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.6" date="2026-04-22">
      <description>
        <p>Closes the 0.7.x remote-control arc and the audit-signal gap opened by the 0.7.5 hygiene work. Seven rc_protocol commands now cover the "drive the terminal from a script" story end-to-end (ls, send-text, new-tab, select-window, set-title, get-text, launch), and the Project Audit panel gains two feature-coverage lanes that catch shipped features without locking tests and spec prose that drifted past a rename.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Audit feature-coverage lanes:</em> two in-process checks in <code>src/featurecoverage.{cpp,h}</code>. Lane 1 (spec↔code drift) extracts backtick-fenced identifier tokens from <code>tests/features/*/spec.md</code> and reports ones that no longer appear under <code>src/</code>. Lane 2 (CHANGELOG↔feature-test coverage) fuzz-matches Added/Fixed bullets in the top CHANGELOG section against feature-spec titles. Both lanes plug into the existing parseFindings → suppress → render pipeline via <code>AuditCheck::inProcessRunner</code>. Pinned by 17 invariants in <code>tests/features/feature_coverage/</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control <code>launch</code>:</em> seventh and final rc_protocol command. Spawns a command in a new tab in one round-trip, auto-appending a trailing newline — the convenience differentiator from <code>new-tab</code>, which stays byte-faithful.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control <code>get-text</code>:</em> returns the trailing N lines of (scrollback + screen), default 100, capped server-side at 10 000. Reuses the AI dialog's context-capture accessor so format stays consistent.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control <code>set-title</code>:</em> pins a tab label against both OSC 0/2 shell updates and the 2 s refresh timer. Empty title clears the pin; pin storage cleaned up on tab close.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control <code>select-window</code>:</em> switches the active tab by 0-based index; focus follows so chained <code>send-text</code> lands on the new pane.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control <code>new-tab</code>:</em> opens a fresh tab and returns its index; optional cwd and command. 200 ms settle before writing the initial command; QPointer-guarded against tab-close-before-fire races.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control <code>send-text</code>:</em> writes UTF-8 bytes byte-for-byte to a tab's PTY. Control chars and escapes pass through unchanged, matching Kitty's rc_protocol <code>send-text</code> semantics. Reads stdin until EOF when <code>--remote-text</code> is absent.</li>
          <li><em>Added — remote-control protocol scaffold:</em> Kitty-style JSON-over-Unix-socket RPC. QLocalServer on <code>$ANTS_REMOTE_SOCKET</code> or <code>$XDG_RUNTIME_DIR/ants-terminal.sock</code>; LF-terminated one-request/one-response. The same binary doubles as the client via <code>--remote &lt;cmd&gt;</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added — main-thread stall detector:</em> 200 ms heartbeat QTimer in MainWindow measures gap between its own firings; logs drift + cumulative count + worst-case when the event loop was blocked. Gated by <code>ANTS_DEBUG=perf</code>, zero cost when off.</li>
          <li><em>Added — VT throughput benchmark harness:</em> drives four fixed corpora (ascii_print, newline_stream, ansi_sgr, utf8_cjk) through VtParser → TerminalGrid at <code>-O2</code>, emits CSV. Registered under ctest label <code>perf</code>; first step of the 0.8.0 throughput investigation.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — dropdown-flicker suppression extended</em> to <code>QEvent::HoverMove</code> / <code>HoverEnter</code> / <code>HoverLeave</code> in <code>MainWindow::eventFilter</code>. The 0.7.5 NoAnimStyle fix only partially reduced the mouse-movement-triggered flicker; Qt's style engine consults WA_Hover independently of QMouseEvent. Residual flicker still visible — pushed to the 0.8.0 roadmap for a different-angle fix.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — <code>new-tab</code> caller-owns-newline contract:</em> first ship used <code>writeCommand</code> (auto-appends <code>\n</code>), contradicting the documented send-text-style semantics. <code>newTabForRemote</code> now uses <code>sendToPty</code> (raw bytes). Convenience "open + run" moved to the new <code>launch</code> command.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.5" date="2026-04-20">
      <description>
        <p>Same-day follow-up to 0.7.4 that resolves the dropdown-menu flicker the 0.7.4 "Known Issue" section called out. Root cause finally pinpointed via the Debug Mode instrumentation that shipped in 0.7.4: Fusion's QWidgetAnimator was creating a 60 Hz QPropertyAnimation(target=QWidget, prop=geometry) cycle on the idle window — 1439 animation completions in a 23 s idle log, each driving a full LayoutRequest → UpdateRequest → Paint cascade. Neither setEffectEnabled(UI_AnimateMenu, false) nor QMainWindow::setAnimated(false) covers the style-hint-driven cycle.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed — dropdown-menu flicker (root cause):</em> a NoAnimStyle QProxyStyle in src/main.cpp zeroes SH_Widget_Animation_Duration and SH_Widget_Animate, wrapped around Fusion at startup. Idle-log result: 0 QPropertyAnimation events (was ≈62 Hz in 0.7.4). Total event volume dropped &gt;99% (29 096 → 62 log lines in 4 s idle). Pinned by the new no_anim_style feature test.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — Debug Mode animation-creation hook:</em> switched from QEvent::ChildAdded to QEvent::ChildPolished. At ChildAdded time the child's vtable still points at QObject (derived ctor hasn't run) so the QPropertyAnimation filter never matched — silently useless on the 0.7.4 investigation. ChildPolished fires post-construction and now correctly logs animation creation sites.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.4" date="2026-04-20">
      <description>
        <p>A session's worth of user-facing UI fixes plus a new Debug Mode that made them possible. Tools → Debug Mode gives 14 independent category toggles (Paint, Events, Input, PTY, VT, Render, Plugins, Network, Config, Audit, Claude, Signals, Shell, Session) that write timestamped lines to ~/.local/share/ants-terminal/debug.log, enabled narrowly (one category) or broadly (all). The instrument pinpointed a ~54 Hz full-window repaint cascade that had been driving the menubar / dropdown / paste-dialog flicker across several releases.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Debug Mode:</em> env-var bootstrap (<code>ANTS_DEBUG=all</code> or <code>ANTS_DEBUG=paint,events,vt</code>) or in-app Tools → Debug Mode menu with checkable categories + Open Log File + Clear Log actions. Hot-path cost when disabled is a single bit-test.</li>
          <li><em>Added — OSC 133 prompt-on-new-line guard:</em> when a shell emits OSC 133 A (prompt start) and the cursor is not at column 0, the terminal nudges it to a new line first. Fixes "prompt glued onto the end of the previous command's output" (e.g. <code>cat file.json</code> with no trailing newline). Equivalent to zsh's PROMPT_SP, but terminal-side so it works for bash / fish / any shell that emits OSC 133.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — menubar hover flash:</em> QMenuBar now sets <code>autoFillBackground(true)</code> + <code>Qt::WA_StyledBackground</code> so the stylesheet background-color paints reliably under a WA_TranslucentBackground parent; <code>:hover</code> mirrors <code>:selected</code> to close the one-frame pre-selected hover gap; <code>setNativeMenuBar(false)</code> made explicit.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — paste-confirmation dialog:</em> rewrote to the fully async Review-Changes pattern (heap QDialog + WA_DeleteOnClose + show()/raise()/activateWindow(), no exec(), no QEventLoop). Three prior attempts via QMessageBox::exec, QDialog::exec, and show()+QEventLoop all hit the ApplicationModal-vs-frameless-parent click-swallow regression that was originally diagnosed for the Review-Changes dialog at 0.6.29.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — Command Palette idle timer churn:</em> the palette's hidden QListWidget ran its QAbstractItemView timer machinery at ~50 Hz from MainWindow construction onward, cascading a full-window repaint every frame. Lazy-create the list in <code>CommandPalette::show()</code> so the view doesn't exist until the user first presses Ctrl+Shift+P.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — QMainWindow dock animator:</em> <code>setAnimated(false)</code>. Ants has no dock widgets, but QMainWindow's built-in QWidgetAnimator ran continuously at idle.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — Qt UI effect animations disabled globally</em> (<code>UI_AnimateMenu</code>, <code>UI_FadeMenu</code>, <code>UI_AnimateCombo</code>, <code>UI_AnimateTooltip</code>, <code>UI_FadeTooltip</code>, <code>UI_AnimateToolBox</code>). These drove QPropertyAnimation(geometry) at 60 Hz on menu open/close; we have no use case for animated chrome.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — titlebar button tooltips removed.</em> A Qt / KWin / Wayland quirk fired the QTipLabel show/hide cycle on every frame while the cursor was near a titlebar button, animating the tooltip's geometry at ~60 Hz. Diagnosed via the debug-log system. Button glyphs (✥ / ✕ / ⬜ / ⟩) + hover-colour feedback give enough affordance without tooltip text.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — TerminalWidget base class:</em> QOpenGLWidget → plain QWidget. The GL widget composites its FBO through the parent's backing store and that always invalidates the top-level; PartialUpdate, WA_OpaquePaintEvent, swapInterval(0), and alpha-buffer opt-out all failed to break it. The QPainter path is unaffected (still ligature-aware via QTextLayout / HarfBuzz). The optional GL glyph-atlas renderer is dormant in 0.7.4 and returns later as an embedded QOpenGLWindow via createWindowContainer.</li>
          <li><em>Tests —</em> <code>menubar_hover_stylesheet</code>, <code>paste_dialog_custom</code>, and new <code>terminal_partial_update_mode</code> pin the invariants above (35/35 pass).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.3" date="2026-04-20">
      <description>
        <p>H6.1 of the 📦 distribution-adoption plan lands: Lua plugins inside the Flatpak sandbox. The 0.7.2 manifest shipped with plugin support disabled because <code>org.kde.Sdk//6.7</code> does not carry <code>lua54-devel</code> and <code>flathub/shared-modules</code> has no Lua 5.4 entry today. 0.7.3 closes that gap with an in-manifest Lua archive module, so a Flatpak build loads plugins the same way the openSUSE, Arch, and Debian builds do.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Lua 5.4 archive module in <code>packaging/flatpak/org.ants.Terminal.yml</code>:</em> a dedicated <code>lua</code> module appears before <code>ants-terminal</code>, built from the upstream Lua 5.4.7 source tarball with a pinned <code>sha256</code> and the <code>linux-noreadline</code> target (Ants links <code>liblua.a</code> statically — pulling readline into the sandbox would be pure bloat). <code>MYCFLAGS="-fPIC"</code> keeps the archive PIE-safe for linking into the <code>ants-terminal</code> executable; installed to <code>/app</code> via <code>make install INSTALL_TOP=/app</code>, which is exactly where CMake's <code>FindLua</code> searches by default when <code>CMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=/app</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added — auto-refresh of the Lua tarball hash:</em> the <code>lua</code> module carries an <code>x-checker-data:</code> stanza pointing at the upstream Lua FTP listing with <code>version-pattern: lua-(5\.4\.\d+)\.tar\.gz</code> and a <code>url-template</code> that substitutes the matched version into the canonical tarball URL. Flathub CI opens a PR against the Flathub repo with a refreshed <code>url</code> + <code>sha256</code> on each Lua 5.4.x point release — no manual hash churn, and 5.5.x majors are excluded (they would break the in-source <code>find_package(Lua 5.4)</code> floor).</li>
          <li><em>Added — feature test <code>tests/features/flatpak_lua_module/</code>:</em> source-grep regression pinning six invariants against the manifest YAML — Lua module precedes ants-terminal, <code>type: archive</code> with a pinned <code>sha256:</code>, <code>MYCFLAGS="-fPIC"</code> in the build commands, <code>make install INSTALL_TOP=/app</code>, the <code>linux-noreadline</code> target (guarding against the default <code>make linux</code> alias to <code>linux-readline</code>), and the <code>x-checker-data</code> stanza with the 5.4.x version-pattern.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>packaging/flatpak/README.md</code>:</em> the "Lua plugins — limitation" section is replaced with a "Lua plugins" section documenting the enabled path (archive-module build, <code>linux-noreadline</code> rationale, <code>x-checker-data</code> automation, success criterion of <code>PluginManager</code> loading a plugin inside the sandbox). Manifest header comment updated to describe the in-manifest module and the automated hash-refresh path.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>ROADMAP.md</code> H6.1</em> flipped from 📋 to ✅ (shipped in 0.7.3).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.2" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>H6 of the 📦 distribution-adoption plan lands: Flatpak packaging. One artifact that runs on every distro that ships <code>flatpak</code>, with a PTY path wired for the sandbox so the user's shell reaches the host's <code>$PATH</code> and filesystem. Unblocks the "packaged everywhere" roadmap gate without per-distro maintenance.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — Flatpak manifest</em> (<code>packaging/flatpak/org.ants.Terminal.yml</code>): targets <code>org.kde.Platform//6.7</code> so the KDE SDK brings cmake, ninja, and every Qt6 component the build needs. <code>finish-args</code> cover Wayland + fallback-X11 + DRI, network (AI endpoint + SSH), portals (<code>org.freedesktop.portal.*</code> for global shortcuts / file dialogs), desktop notifications, and XDG config/data directories. Single <code>cmake-ninja</code> module; Ants source enters via <code>type: dir / path: ../..</code> for local builds and re-points to <code>type: git / url / tag</code> for Flathub submission.</li>
          <li><em>Added — Flatpak host-shell wiring in <code>ptyhandler.cpp</code>:</em> the forked child probes <code>FLATPAK_ID</code> and <code>/.flatpak-info</code> (either signal triggers the branch) and exec's the user's shell via <code>flatpak-spawn --host</code> with <code>--env=</code> forwarding for TERM / COLORTERM / TERM_PROGRAM / TERM_PROGRAM_VERSION (pulled from the <code>ANTS_VERSION</code> compile definition, not a literal) / COLORFGBG, plus <code>--directory=&lt;workDir&gt;</code> gated on <code>!workDir.isEmpty()</code>. The terminal emulator itself (VT parser, renderer, plugin VM) stays inside the sandbox; only the child shell escapes so tools and <code>$HOME</code> are reachable. Same PTY model as Ghostty's Flathub build. Outside Flatpak the existing <code>execlp</code> path runs byte-for-byte unchanged.</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>packaging/flatpak/README.md</code>:</em> local build (<code>flatpak-builder --install --user</code>), host-shell rationale, Flathub submission workflow, and the documented Lua-plugins-disabled limitation for the initial manifest (plugin support returns once a shared-modules Lua entry is wired up).</li>
          <li><em>Added — <code>packaging/README.md</code> Flatpak section:</em> layout tree adds <code>flatpak/</code>; "Flatpak — <code>org.ants.Terminal.yml</code>" section mirrors the openSUSE / Arch / Debian sections; shared-concerns header updated from three recipes to four.</li>
          <li><em>Added — feature test <code>tests/features/flatpak_host_shell/</code>:</em> source-grep regression test pinning the branch shape — detection probes both signals in an OR, <code>--host</code> and <code>--</code> separators appear in argv, every TERM var crosses via <code>--env=</code>, workDir gates on <code>isEmpty()</code>, direct-exec fallback is preserved verbatim, <code>_exit(127)</code> is the post-exec fall-through on <code>execvp</code> failure.</li>
          <li><em>Changed — <code>ROADMAP.md</code> H6</em> flipped from 📋 to ✅ manifest (0.7.2) + 📋 Flathub submission residual.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.1" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>First of the 0.8.0 🎨 multiplexing roadmap items lands ahead of the larger mux-server / remote-control work: SSH ControlMaster auto-multiplexing from the bookmark dialog. A second tab to the same host now reuses the first tab's session, skipping the full auth handshake — same precedent as kitty's <code>ssh</code> kitten, Warp's SSH blocks, and iTerm2's SSH profiles.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>SSH ControlMaster auto-multiplexing:</em> connects opened from the SSH Manager carry <code>-o ControlMaster=auto</code>, <code>-o ControlPath=$HOME/.ssh/cm-%r@%h:%p</code>, and <code>-o ControlPersist=10m</code> when the new <code>ssh_control_master</code> config key is true (default). Opt-out available for sites that forbid lingering multiplex sockets by policy. <code>$HOME</code> resolves in-process via <code>QDir::homePath()</code> so the ControlPath works under dash / POSIX <code>sh</code>; <code>%r@%h:%p</code> are OpenSSH ControlPath substitution tokens and survive shell quoting intact. Feature test <code>ssh_control_master</code> pins six invariants covering token presence/absence, <code>$HOME</code> resolution, positional ordering, and coexistence with the legacy <code>-p</code> / <code>-i</code> / extraArgs flags.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.0" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Shell integration + triggers — the 0.7.0 minor release rolls up the 0.6.1 → 0.6.45 patch-release arc into the theme the 0.7 ROADMAP plotted out. Command blocks become first-class UI, <code>.cast</code> recording ships, semantic history turns <code>path:line:col</code> into Ctrl-click jumps, OSC 133 markers gain HMAC verification, the full iTerm2-parity trigger set lands, the VT parser goes SIMD with a dedicated PTY/parse worker thread, Quake mode runs Wayland-native via layer-shell + GlobalShortcuts portal, and the H1–H4 distribution slice (SECURITY.md, AppStream metainfo, man page, shell completions) takes Ants from "side project" to "distro-ready." No breaking API changes — every plugin that loaded against 0.6.45 loads against 0.7.0.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Shell integration:</em> command blocks as first-class UI with OSC 133 prompt/command/output grouping, Ctrl+Shift+Up / Down jumps, collapsible output with "… N lines hidden" summaries, a 2px pass/fail stripe, and per-block right-click menu (Copy Command, Copy Output, Re-run, Fold/Unfold, Share as <code>.cast</code>). Asciinema <code>.cast</code> v2 recording — full-session via Ctrl+Shift+R or per-block via the context menu.</li>
          <li><em>Semantic history:</em> Ctrl-click on a <code>path:line:col</code> capture in scrollback opens the file at the cited position. CWD resolution via <code>/proc/&lt;pid&gt;/cwd</code> so relative paths Just Work. Editor support covers VS Code family, vi-family, nano, Sublime, Helix, Micro, and JetBrains.</li>
          <li><em>Security:</em> shell-side HMAC verification for OSC 133 markers — when <code>$ANTS_OSC133_KEY</code> is set, forged markers are dropped and a status-bar counter surfaces the count. Plugin capability audit UI renders every declared permission as a revocable checkbox in Settings → Plugins. Image-bomb defenses cap total decoded image bytes at 256 MB per terminal across Sixel / Kitty / iTerm2 OSC 1337.</li>
          <li><em>Triggers + plugin events:</em> full iTerm2-parity trigger rule set (<code>bell</code>, <code>inject</code>, <code>run_script</code>, <code>notify</code>, <code>sound</code>, <code>command</code>, <code>highlight_line</code>, <code>highlight_text</code>, <code>make_hyperlink</code>) with an <code>instant</code> flag. OSC 1337 SetUserVar with <code>user_var_changed</code> event. Command-palette plugin registration via <code>ants.palette.register()</code>. New events: <code>command_finished</code>, <code>pane_focused</code>, <code>theme_changed</code>, <code>window_config_reloaded</code>, <code>user_var_changed</code>, <code>palette_action</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Performance:</em> SIMD VT-parser scan — ground-state hot path scans 16 bytes at a time via SSE2 (x86_64) / NEON (ARM64). Dedicated PTY read + VT parse worker thread decouples input from the GUI with bounded back-pressure (≤ 8 batches in flight). Incremental reflow on resize skips the allocation-heavy rewrap round-trip for standalone lines.</li>
          <li><em>Platform — Wayland native:</em> layer-shell Quake mode promotes the window to <code>zwlr_layer_surface_v1</code> at <code>LayerTop</code> when <code>layer-shell-qt6-devel</code> is present (XCB path preserved for X11). Freedesktop GlobalShortcuts portal wires the <code>toggle-quake</code> id on KDE Plasma 6 and xdg-desktop-portal-hyprland / -wlr; in-app <code>QShortcut</code> fallback stays active on GNOME Shell.</li>
          <li><em>Distribution readiness (H1–H4):</em> <code>SECURITY.md</code> + <code>CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md</code> (coordinated-disclosure policy, Contributor Covenant 2.1) clear the Debian / Fedora / Ubuntu security-team review gate. AppStream metainfo + polished desktop entry with Desktop Actions for NewWindow + QuakeMode. <code>groff -man</code> man page at <code>packaging/linux/ants-terminal.1</code>. Shell completions for bash / zsh / fish installed to conventional vendor paths — auto-discovered on system-wide installs. CI runs <code>appstreamcli validate --explain</code>, <code>desktop-file-validate</code>, and <code>groff -man -Tutf8 -wall</code> on every push.</li>
          <li><em>Dev experience:</em> Project Audit gains four new rules (<code>unbounded_callback_payloads</code>, <code>qnetworkreply_no_abort</code>, <code>silent_catch</code>, <code>missing_build_flags</code>, <code>no_ci</code>), fixture-per-check self-consistency enforcement (<code>audit_fixture_coverage</code>), and a build-asan CI lane running ctest + binary smoke under ASan/UBSan on every push. <code>CONTRIBUTING.md</code> covers build modes, test layout, adding an audit rule, version-bump checklist. <code>actions/checkout</code> bumped v4.2.2 → v5.0.1 to pre-empt the 2026-06-02 Node 20 deprecation.</li>
          <li><em>Notes:</em> 0.7.0 is a minor-release rollup of 30 patch releases; the individual <code>0.6.x</code> CHANGELOG entries remain authoritative for the SHAs they shipped under. Deferred items (EGL swap-with-damage on GL, Domain abstraction, persistent workspaces, Kitty Unicode-placeholder graphics) are explicitly re-scoped to 0.8.0+.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.45" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Deferred VT-standards items from the 10th-audit research report, plus atomic-write hardening for long-lived audit state. The 11th periodic audit returned 0 of ~103 actionable findings — the baseline stays clean. User-visible win: modern Go / Rust TUIs (delta, lazygit, fzf, jj, neovim, bat, most <code>termenv</code>-based tools) can now auto-detect Ants' dark-vs-light theme without the unreliable <code>COLORFGBG</code> env var, and tmux / neovim / kitty-kitten can save-and-restore terminal state around their own output.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> OSC 10 / 11 / 12 colour queries. Apps that probe <code>\e]10;?\e\\</code> etc. get the xterm 16-bit-per-channel reply <code>\e]&lt;n&gt;;rgb:RRRR/GGGG/BBBB\e\\</code>. Only the query form is honoured — the set form is deliberately silently dropped so default fg / bg / cursor colour stays theme-driven and in-terminal programs can't inject a theme.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> DECRQSS (Request Status String). DCS <code>$q</code> requests for <code>DECSTBM</code> (scroll-region, <code>r</code>), <code>SGR</code> (current attributes, <code>m</code>), and <code>DECSCUSR</code> (cursor shape, <code> q</code>) reply with <code>DCS 1 $ r …</code> per the xterm spec. Unknown settings reply "invalid" (<code>DCS 0 $ r …</code>) rather than dropping silently so callers fall back to defaults. The DECRQSS branch gates on the <code>$q</code> prefix before Sixel's <code>q</code> search, so Sixel image traffic still routes to the image handler.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> atomic JSON writes via <code>QSaveFile</code> for four long-lived audit-state files — <code>audit_rule_quality.json</code> (frequent per-fire / per-suppression writes; corruption loses every rule score), <code>.audit_cache/trend.json</code> (cumulative severity totals), <code>.audit_cache/baseline.json</code> (fingerprints anchoring the "new findings only" filter), and the <code>.audit_suppress</code> v1 → v2 migration rewrite. Torn writes from crash or <code>kill -9</code> can no longer corrupt any of these. The one-line <code>.audit_suppress</code> append path stays non-atomic on purpose — the loader already skips malformed lines.</li>
          <li><em>Tests:</em> new <code>osc_color_query</code> feature test locks the OSC 10/11/12 response shape plus the query-only gate (set form MUST NOT produce a response); new <code>decrqss</code> test locks the DECSTBM / SGR / DECSCUSR replies, the "invalid" reply bytes, and a Sixel-routing regression guard so the new DECRQSS branch can't eat image traffic.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.44" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Project Audit dialog self-review pass. The 10th periodic audit returned 0 of 55 actionable findings — the nature of the 55 pointed at three bits of friction the dialog was creating for itself: it was auditing its own output, every "is this noise?" verdict needed an individual click, and users had no summary-level readout for "how much of this run was signal?". All three are closed in this release.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> signal-ratio readout in the summary banner. <code>renderResults()</code> now prints an "X% actionable" figure — signal / (signal + noise) where noise = suppressions + AI-verdict <code>FALSE_POSITIVE</code> — below the severity pills with colour coding (green ≥60%, amber 20–59%, red &lt;20%). A 30-day rolling average pulled from <code>RuleQualityTracker</code> sits next to it as a peer comparison ("30d avg X% actionable, n=Y fires").</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> batch AI triage. A <code>🧠 Triage visible (N)</code> button next to the confidence-sort toggle sends every visible, not-yet-triaged finding to the configured LLM in a single JSON request (hard cap 20 per batch; above that it slices and dispatches sequentially). Responses are spliced back by dedup key so a reordering model can't misalign results. Prompt-injection hardening inherited from the single-finding path. Hidden entirely when AI isn't configured.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> <code>isGeneratedFile()</code> now auto-skips prior audit artifacts — <code>docs/AUTOMATED_AUDIT_REPORT_*.{json,md,html,txt}</code> (SHA-256 dedup keys that gitleaks flagged as high-entropy secrets), <code>.audit_cache/</code> and <code>audit_rule_quality.json</code> (the dialog's own baseline + self-learning ledger; auditing them is circular), and <code>tests/audit_fixtures/**</code> (<code>bad.*</code> fixtures intentionally embed strings third-party scanners misread as real findings). No project configuration needed.</li>
          <li><em>Notes:</em> no schema changes. <code>audit_rule_quality.json</code> and <code>audit_rules.json</code> are read-compatible with prior versions. The 30-day actionable% uses <code>fires</code> as the denominator rather than run count, because run count isn't directly recorded — the label makes the denominator explicit (<code>n=&lt;count&gt; fires</code>).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.43" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Two user-reported regressions closed, plus a quality-of-life default flip. The 0.6.42 focus-redirect guards didn't cure the menubar hover flash — the real culprit was a stylesheet gap, not focus churn. And users coming back to the app expected their tabs to be waiting for them; session persistence now ships default-on, matching every modern terminal (iTerm2, Kitty, WezTerm, Konsole).</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> menubar hover no longer flashes. The 0.6.42 pass narrowed focus-redirect firing but didn't address the root cause. The stylesheet defined <code>QMenuBar::item:selected</code> without a matching base <code>QMenuBar::item</code> rule, so Qt fell back to the native style for the non-selected state and composited native drawing under the <code>:selected</code> overlay. Added an explicit transparent-background <code>QMenuBar::item</code> base rule plus a <code>:pressed</code> rule so every menubar item state is owned entirely by the stylesheet; the 0.6.42 focus guards remain as defense-in-depth.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> tabs are now remembered between sessions by default. <code>Config::sessionPersistence()</code> defaulted to <code>false</code>, so users who never toggled Settings → General → "Save and restore sessions" lost their tab set on every quit. Flipped the default to <code>true</code>; users with <code>session_persistence: false</code> explicit in <code>config.json</code> still get their opt-out honoured — only the absent-key path reads the new fallback. The 5-second uptime floor in <code>saveAllSessions()</code> still protects against crash-on-launch wiping real state.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> <code>Config::sessionPersistence()</code> default flipped from <code>false</code> to <code>true</code>. First-run users now get tab restore out of the box; explicit values in <code>config.json</code> are respected unchanged.</li>
          <li><em>Tests:</em> new <code>tests/features/session_persistence_default/</code> three-invariant feature test pins the truth table — missing key → true, explicit true → true, explicit false → false. Linked against <code>src/config.cpp</code> only (no GUI dependency). Brings the feature-test count to 25 and the total ctest count to 26.</li>
          <li><em>Internal:</em> cleaned up a <code>-Wshadow</code> warning at <code>mainwindow.cpp:3921</code> (Review-Changes finalizer lambda's <code>const Theme &amp;th</code> shadowed the outer <code>th</code>; renamed to <code>lth</code>) and dropped an unused <code>&lt;cstdlib&gt;</code> include from the new test.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.42" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Focus-redirect guard rails. Two user-visible regressions from the 0.6.26 auto-return-to-terminal behaviour — a flashing highlight as the mouse crossed the menubar, and the paste-confirmation dialog's "Paste" button silently swallowing mouse clicks — both traced back to the same <code>QApplication::focusChanged</code> handler firing through narrow windows it shouldn't. New guards short-circuit the redirect when a popup is open, when the cursor is over a menu or menubar, or when any top-level <code>QDialog</code> is visible — the last covers the <code>QMessageBox::exec()</code> modality-handshake tick during which <code>activeModalWidget()</code> can briefly be null.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> menubar File / Edit / View hover no longer flickers. The focus-redirect lambda now early-returns when <code>QApplication::activePopupWidget()</code> is non-null and when <code>QApplication::widgetAt(QCursor::pos())</code> has a <code>QMenu</code> or <code>QMenuBar</code> ancestor. Both guards are mirrored in the deferred <code>QTimer::singleShot(0,…)</code> fire-time block so a menu opened between queue and fire is still honoured.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the paste-confirmation <code>QMessageBox</code> no longer swallows clicks on the "Paste" button (pre-0.6.42 only the <code>&amp;Paste</code> mnemonic worked). The redirect now walks <code>QApplication::topLevelWidgets()</code> at queue time and early-returns on any visible <code>QDialog</code>, mirroring the fire-time check and covering the brief <code>show()</code> handshake window where <code>activeModalWidget()</code> returns null.</li>
          <li><em>Tests:</em> new <code>tests/features/focus_redirect_menu_guard/</code> source-grep pins six invariants on the focusChanged lambda in <code>src/mainwindow.cpp</code> — the popup and menu-hover guards (queue + fire time), the visible-dialog walk, and the five pre-existing guards (<code>activeModalWidget</code>, <code>QAbstractButton</code>, <code>mouseButtons</code>, <code>QDialog</code> parent chain, <code>CommandPalette</code>) that must not regress. Uses the balanced-brace scanner from 0.6.41 to avoid <code>std::regex</code> stack blow-out on a 4000+ line file.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.41" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Quake-mode + OSC 133 UX polish. Surfaces the out-of-focus portal binding state in Settings so users can tell at a glance whether their Quake hotkey escapes focus, and adds a scrollbar-adjacent tick-mark gutter that exposes OSC 133 command boundaries across the full scrollback — jump targets for <code>Ctrl+Shift+Up/Down</code> that were previously invisible.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> command-mark gutter (<code>show_command_marks</code>, default on) — a 4-px vertical strip just left of the scrollbar draws one tick per <code>PromptRegion</code>, color-coded by last exit status: green (success), red (non-zero exit), gray (in-progress, OSC 133 D not yet emitted). Positions compress linearly so a 50,000-line scrollback stays fully visible in the widget height.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> Settings → Terminal → Scrollback toggle "Show command markers in scrollbar gutter" (default on) with a tooltip explaining the color states. Propagates to all live terminals via <code>applyConfigToTerminal</code> — no restart needed.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> portal-binding status label in Settings → Quake. One line under the hotkey field reports either "Portal binding active" (green, hotkey works when Ants is unfocused — KDE Plasma 6, Hyprland, wlroots) or "Portal unavailable" (amber, hotkey works only while focused), based on <code>GlobalShortcutsPortal::isAvailable()</code> at dialog construction.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> gutter drawing gates on <code>m_showCommandMarks</code> AND non-empty <code>promptRegions()</code>, so users without shell integration see nothing change; ticks never overlap the scrollbar thumb (offset by <code>m_scrollBar->width()</code>).</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.40" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>OSC 133 shell-integration polish. Adds two keyboard-driven "last completed command" actions that complement the existing block-at-cursor right-click menu with no-selection-needed top-level equivalents — the iTerm2 ⇧⌘O / WezTerm <code>CopyLastOutput</code> convention, surfaced through the View menu, the command palette, and configurable keybindings.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>TerminalWidget::copyLastCommandOutput()</code> slot — walks <code>promptRegions()</code> backwards for the most recent region with <code>commandEndMs &gt; 0 &amp;&amp; hasOutput</code> and copies the full output via <code>outputTextAt(idx)</code> (unbounded). Skips in-progress tails so <code>Ctrl+Alt+O</code> during <code>sleep 30</code> copies the previous command's output, never the partial in-progress one.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>TerminalWidget::rerunLastCommand()</code> slot — same backwards-walk / skip-in-progress rule, then writes the command text + <code>\r</code> to the PTY via <code>rerunCommandAt(idx)</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> View menu entries "Copy Last Command Output" (default <code>Ctrl+Alt+O</code>, config key <code>copy_last_output</code>) and "Re-run Last Command" (default <code>Ctrl+Alt+R</code>, config key <code>rerun_last_command</code>). Both surface automatically in the command palette; <code>Ctrl+Alt+*</code> avoids the already-taken <code>Ctrl+Shift+O</code> (split pane) and <code>Ctrl+Shift+R</code> (record session).</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> status-bar toasts for discoverability — success path shows "Copied N chars of last command output"; failure path shows "No completed command to copy (enable shell integration)", a load-bearing hint that OSC 133 needs bash/zsh/fish shell-integration hooks.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> locked by <code>tests/features/osc133_last_command</code> (CTest labels <code>features;fast</code>, part of the release gate) — pins the backwards-walk, the <code>outputTextAt</code>-not-<code>lastCommandOutput</code> choice, the keybinding wiring, and the toast contract.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.39" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Wayland-native Quake-mode, part 2 of 2 — completes the 0.7.0 roadmap item. When the <code>xdg-desktop-portal</code> service is available on the session bus, Ants Terminal now registers its Quake toggle with the Freedesktop Portal <code>org.freedesktop.portal.GlobalShortcuts</code> API (KDE Plasma 6, <code>xdg-desktop-portal-hyprland</code>, <code>xdg-desktop-portal-wlr</code>). The hotkey fires whether or not Ants has focus. On GNOME Shell (portal service present but no GlobalShortcuts backend yet) and on minimal desktops without a portal, the in-app <code>QShortcut</code> fallback from 0.6.38 stays as the activation path — no regression.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>GlobalShortcutsPortal</code> client class wrapping the three-step D-Bus handshake (<code>CreateSession</code> → session handle → <code>BindShortcuts</code> → <code>Activated</code>) behind a single Qt signal. Handles request-path prediction, custom meta-type registration for the <code>a(sa{sv})</code> shortcuts array, and session lifecycle.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> portal-aware Quake setup in <code>MainWindow</code> — when the portal is available, binds the <code>toggle-quake</code> id with <code>config.quake_hotkey</code> as the preferred trigger.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> focused double-fire debounce between the in-app <code>QShortcut</code> and the portal <code>Activated</code> paths (500 ms window) so a focused system doesn't hide-then-show the window in one frame.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>qtKeySequenceToPortalTrigger</code> helper that converts Qt's <code>"Ctrl+Shift+`"</code> into the freedesktop shortcut-syntax <code>"CTRL+SHIFT+grave"</code>. Deliberately minimal — modifiers plus a handful of common punctuation; unrecognised keys pass through.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> new <code>tests/features/global_shortcuts_portal/</code> regression test pins (1) <code>isAvailable()</code> gate on portal construction; (2) canonical D-Bus service / path / interface / method literals; (3) bound id <code>"toggle-quake"</code> matches the Activated handler filter; (4) in-app <code>QShortcut</code> fallback stays wired; (5) both activation paths debounce via <code>m_lastQuakeToggleMs</code>; (6) CMakeLists.txt lists the source + keeps <code>Qt6::DBus</code> linked; (7) header surfaces the expected public API.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.38" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Wayland-native Quake-mode, part 1 of 2. When <code>layer-shell-qt6</code> is present at build time, Ants Terminal's drop-down Quake mode now promotes its window to a <code>zwlr_layer_surface_v1</code> at the top layer, anchored to the top edge of the active screen — the Wayland equivalent of the X11 <code>_NET_WM_STATE_ABOVE</code> + client-side <code>move()</code> the XCB path has used all along. Also fixes a long-standing dead-code bug: the <code>quake_hotkey</code> config key was saved from Settings but never wired to a shortcut; the QLineEdit value is now honoured in-app. True out-of-focus global hotkey registration (via the Freedesktop Portal GlobalShortcuts API) is the 0.6.39 follow-up.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>LayerShellQt</code> integration — <code>CMakeLists.txt</code> does <code>find_package(LayerShellQt CONFIG QUIET)</code> and defines <code>ANTS_WAYLAND_LAYER_SHELL</code> when found. Missing = Wayland Quake falls back to the Qt toplevel path; X11 Quake is unaffected.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the <code>quake_hotkey</code> config key is now wired to a <code>QShortcut</code> invoking <code>toggleQuakeVisibility()</code>. Pre-0.6.38 the Settings dialog saved the user's chosen sequence but nothing consumed it.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the slide-up/slide-down animation no longer snaps on Wayland — <code>QPropertyAnimation</code> on <code>pos()</code> is a no-op there (the compositor owns position), so the Wayland path uses a plain show/hide toggle. XCB slide animation is unchanged.</li>
          <li><em>Packaging:</em> openSUSE spec adds <code>BuildRequires: cmake(LayerShellQt)</code>; Arch <code>PKGBUILD</code> adds <code>layer-shell-qt</code> to <code>makedepends</code> + <code>optdepends</code>; Debian <code>control</code> adds <code>liblayershellqt6-dev</code> to <code>Build-Depends</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Invariant:</em> new <code>tests/features/wayland_quake_mode/</code> regression test pins (1) the layer-shell include is guarded by <code>ANTS_WAYLAND_LAYER_SHELL</code>; (2) <code>setupQuakeMode()</code> dispatches X11 vs Wayland at runtime; (3) <code>toggleQuakeVisibility()</code> skips the <code>pos()</code> animation on Wayland; (4) the <code>quake_hotkey</code> → <code>QShortcut</code> wire exists; (5) CMake uses the <code>QUIET</code> flavour of <code>find_package</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.37" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Phase 3 of the 0.7.0 threading refactor. The <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> kill-switch introduced in 0.6.34 is retired, and the legacy single-threaded read/parse code paths are deleted from <code>TerminalWidget</code>. The bake period (0.6.34 → 0.6.37) proved the worker path; the 0.6.35 hotfix proved the kill-switch worked. Every launch now goes through <code>VtStream</code> on the worker thread — one path, one set of invariants, four feature tests.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Removed:</em> the <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> environment kill-switch and the legacy <code>TerminalWidget::startShell()</code> branch it guarded.</li>
          <li><em>Removed:</em> legacy <code>m_pty</code> / <code>m_parser</code> members and the <code>onPtyData</code> slot — the widget no longer owns a <code>Pty</code> or <code>VtParser</code> directly; both live inside <code>VtStream</code> on the worker thread.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> <code>hasPty()</code> and <code>ptyChildPid()</code> simplified to worker-only checks; no behaviour change at the call sites.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.36" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Tenth periodic audit. Two actionable findings across ~110 raw — a 2% signal ratio consistent with the codebase's audit-calibration anchor. Both fixed in a single pass.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> <code>RuleQualityTracker::prune()</code> was dead code — <code>save()</code> inlined the same retention logic. Removed the dead function; <code>save()</code> is now the single source of truth for the 90-day cutoff.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> <code>pipeRun</code> regex in paste-confirmation was recompiled on every paste. Hoisted to <code>static const</code> so the pattern compiles once per process.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.35" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Hotfix for the 0.6.34 threaded-parse refactor. Keystrokes typed into the terminal were silently dropped — the echo never appeared on screen. Twelve PTY-write call sites in <code>TerminalWidget</code> (keystrokes, arrow keys, paste, focus reporting, scratchpad, context menu, and more) still carried pre-0.6.34 <code>if (m_pty) ptyWrite(...)</code> guards. Under the threaded parse path <code>m_pty</code> is null (the <code>Pty</code> now lives on the worker thread inside <code>VtStream</code>), so the guard silently swallowed every write. Replaced each with either <code>hasPty()</code> (path-agnostic) or an unconditional <code>ptyWrite(...)</code> call (the helper is null-safe). A new <code>threaded_ptywrite_gating</code> feature test pins the invariant at the source level so the bug can't come back quietly.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> keystrokes and paste no longer silently drop on the threaded parse path.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> <code>shellPid()</code> / <code>shellCwd()</code> / <code>foregroundProcess()</code> now work on the worker path via a new <code>ptyChildPid()</code> helper.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>threaded_ptywrite_gating</code> regression test — source-level guard against stale <code>m_pty</code> null-checks outside the allowlisted legacy-path functions.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.34" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Decouples PTY read and VT parsing from the Qt GUI thread. Previously, every byte of terminal output traversed the GUI thread through <code>QSocketNotifier → Pty::dataReceived → VtParser::feed → TerminalGrid::processAction</code> and then on to paint — so heavy streams (<code>find /</code>, <code>cat biglog</code>) blocked scroll and repaint. As of 0.6.34 read + parse run on a dedicated worker <code>QThread</code> (<code>VtStream</code>); only batched <code>VtAction</code> streams cross back to GUI for grid application and paint. Ships the first 0.7.0 performance item early since the architectural change landed clean with three feature-conformance tests locking the invariants.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>VtStream</code> worker wrapper (<code>src/vtstream.{h,cpp}</code>) — owns <code>Pty</code> and <code>VtParser</code> on a dedicated QThread, accumulates parser output into <code>VtBatch</code> and ships it to GUI over <code>Qt::QueuedConnection</code>. Grid and paint path stay on GUI so the refactor surface stays small.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> back-pressure — worker buffers up to 8 batches (~128 KB of unprocessed PTY bytes) before disabling its read notifier so the kernel applies flow control to the child; GUI re-enables reads on drain. Replaces "let RAM grow unbounded while GUI catches up" with kernel-natural flow control.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> <code>Pty::setReadEnabled(bool)</code> for the back-pressure path. <code>Pty::write</code> and <code>Pty::resize</code> are now slots so they can be invoked cross-thread via <code>QMetaObject::invokeMethod</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> three feature-conformance tests under <code>tests/features/</code> — <code>threaded_parse_equivalence</code> (11 fixtures × 6 chunking strategies, pins action-stream identity), <code>threaded_response_ordering</code> (DA1/CPR/DA2/mode-996/DSR-OK order across 3 feed strategies), and <code>threaded_resize_synchronous</code> (source-level contract that <code>invokeMethod</code> uses <code>Qt::BlockingQueuedConnection</code>).</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> all PTY-write call sites in <code>TerminalWidget</code> route through a new <code>ptyWrite()</code> helper — keystrokes, bracketed paste, Kitty kbd protocol, response callbacks, snippets, scratchpad. The helper branches on worker-active vs. legacy path; correctness is centralised.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> resize path uses <code>Qt::BlockingQueuedConnection</code> so the PTY winsize is updated before <code>resizeEvent</code> returns — no 1-frame flicker at the new grid size with old PTY dims.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> session logging and asciicast timestamps are now sampled on the worker at batch-flush time rather than on GUI at onPtyData time; asciicast recordings are more accurate under paint load. Log write granularity is per-batch rather than per-PTY-read (coarser but still monotonic).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Kill switch: set <code>ANTS_SINGLE_THREADED=1</code> in the environment to force the legacy single-threaded path while the new code proves itself. It will be removed in a follow-up release once no regressions surface.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.33" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Nine long-standing user-reported bugs around the status bar, scrollback integrity, session restore, and the Review Changes dialog — fixed in one pass. The quiet centerpiece is the root-cause diagnosis of the long tail of "Review Changes button does nothing" reports: a 0.6.26-era <code>focusChanged</code> lambda was firing a <code>singleShot(0)</code> refocus <em>between</em> a button's mousePress and mouseRelease, ripping focus off the button mid-click and silently cancelling the <code>clicked()</code> signal. Also retires the <code>ElidedLabel</code> + stylesheet-chip-padding class of bug by converting every fixed-width status-bar chip to plain <code>QLabel</code> / <code>QPushButton</code> with <code>QSizePolicy::Fixed</code>.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added:</em> one-click "Install Claude Code status-bar hooks" action in Settings &gt; General — writes <code>~/.config/ants-terminal/hooks/claude-forward.sh</code> and idempotently merges PreToolUse / PostToolUse / Stop / PreCompact / SessionStart entries into <code>~/.claude/settings.json</code>, preserving any existing hooks.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> frozen-view scrollback snapshot — while scrolled up, <code>cellAtGlobal</code> / <code>combiningAt</code> read from a snapshot of the screen at scroll-up time, not the live grid, so the viewport is completely immune to live screen writes. Locked by <code>tests/features/scrollback_frozen_view/</code>.</li>
          <li><em>Added:</em> richer Claude status vocabulary (idle / thinking / bash / reading / editing / searching / browsing / planning / auditing / prompting / compacting) with distinct theme colours; plan-mode and <code>/audit</code> detection in the transcript parser; new <code>planModeChanged</code> and <code>auditingChanged</code> signals; <code>notification_timeout_ms</code> and <code>tab_color_sequence</code> config keys.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> Review Changes button is now tri-state — hidden when not a git repo, disabled when clean and in-sync, enabled otherwise. Probe switched to <code>git status --porcelain=v1 -b</code> so unpushed commits count as reviewable work. The global <code>QPushButton:hover</code> rule is now <code>:enabled</code>-gated. The dialog is fully async — opens instantly with a placeholder and streams git output in, with the status-bar button disabled while it is open.</li>
          <li><em>Changed:</em> status-bar layout uses <code>QSizePolicy::Fixed</code> across the branch / process / Claude-status / button chips. Only the transient notification slot is elastic and elides. Branch chip colour moved from green to cyan so it is visually distinct from Claude-state chips.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> the focus-redirect race — the <code>focusChanged</code> lambda now exempts <code>QAbstractButton</code> focus targets and defers while a mouse button is held down, so button clicks on status-bar chrome are no longer cancelled mid-press.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> scrollback blank-line bloat on inactive tabs after session restart. Two root causes: <code>recalcGridSize</code> ran on unlaid-out tabs and shrank grids to 3×10 (pre-layout guard added); <code>TerminalGrid::resize</code> pushed every reflowed row to scrollback (now skips entirely-blank rows).</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> tab colours not persisting across restarts — UUID-keyed <code>tab_groups</code> only worked with session persistence enabled; an ordered <code>tab_color_sequence</code> fallback is now applied at startup.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Add-to-Allowlist button gains a 3-scan debounce against TUI-repaint flicker and a shared <code>toolFinished</code> / <code>sessionStopped</code> retraction path across scroll-scan and hook detections.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.32" date="2026-04-18">
      <description>
        <p>Audit self-learning layer + contributor-facing docs + a one-line CI hotfix for 0.6.31's OSC 133 verifier. The headline is a per-rule fire/suppression tracker that records every audit finding and user suppression to <code>&lt;project&gt;/audit_rule_quality.json</code>, plus a new "📊 Rule Quality" button in the audit dialog that surfaces the noisiest rules first. A longest-common-substring suggester turns the last few suppressions for a noisy rule into a one-line <code>dropIfContains</code> proposal that's a copy-paste away from the user's <code>audit_rules.json</code> override pack.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Added — audit self-learning:</em> <code>RuleQualityTracker</code> (<code>src/auditrulequality.{h,cpp}</code>) records per-rule fire and suppression events with a 90-day rolling window and 50 000-record-per-category cap. Saves on dialog destruction (RAII) and force-flushes on each suppression so user actions are durable.</li>
          <li><em>Added — Rule Quality dialog:</em> new modal table view listing per-rule 30-day fires, 30-day suppressions, FP rate (capped 0-100 %), all-time fires, and a proposed <code>dropIfContains</code> tightening when the heuristic suggester has enough samples. Sorted by FP rate desc so the noisiest rules surface first.</li>
          <li><em>Added — LCS tightening suggester:</em> longest common substring across the last 5 suppressed line texts per rule. Floor at 6 chars + at least one structural boundary character (space, paren, brace, bracket, semicolon, quote, angle bracket) so we propose rule-shape filters, not project-noun filters. Surfaces inline in the status bar on every suppression.</li>
          <li><em>Added — docs:</em> <code>docs/RECOMMENDED_ROUTINES.md</code> captures the four Claude Code routines that earn a slot on the shared account quota for this repo — nightly audit triage, PR security review, weekly audit-rule self-triage (the deeper LLM-driven counterpart to the always-on tracker), and a monthly ROADMAP-item scoper.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — CI build:</em> 0.6.31's OSC 133 verifier used a <code>QByteArrayView</code> overload of <code>QMessageAuthenticationCode::addData</code> not available on the Ubuntu runner's Qt 6.x. Switched to the <code>(const char*, qsizetype)</code> overload present everywhere; behaviour unchanged.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.31" date="2026-04-17">
      <description>
        <p>Security + reliability release. The headline is <em>OSC 133 HMAC-signed shell integration</em>: when <code>$ANTS_OSC133_KEY</code> is set, every prompt / command / exit marker must carry a matching <code>HMAC-SHA256</code> tag, and forged markers from in-terminal processes are dropped (with a throttled status-bar warning). When the key is unset, behaviour is unchanged from 0.6.30 — no upgrade penalty for users who don't opt in.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>Security:</em> OSC 133 HMAC verification closes the spoofing surface where any process writing to stdout (a malicious TUI, <code>cat malicious.txt</code>) could otherwise mint shell-integration markers and pollute prompt regions, exit codes, and the <code>command_finished</code> plugin event. Shell hooks ship under <code>${datarootdir}/ants-terminal/shell-integration/</code> for bash and zsh.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Review Changes status-bar button no longer silently swallows clicks on a clean repo — the disabled-but-visible state was advertising itself as actionable via the global hover stylesheet while never emitting <code>clicked()</code>. The button is now hidden on clean repos and reappears the moment a real diff exists.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Shift+Enter no longer wedges the terminal tab in bracketed-paste mode (0.6.26 regression). A <code>QByteArray(literal, 8)</code> truncation dropped the closing <code>[201~</code> end-paste marker; switched to <code>QByteArrayLiteral</code> so the size is derived at compile time.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed:</em> Status-bar Add-to-allowlist button no longer stacks duplicates when a scroll-scan detection fires while a hook-path container is already visible — dedup lookup now uses <code>QWidget*</code> for parity with the other lookup sites.</li>
          <li><em>Fixed — audit signal-to-noise:</em> Two-pass triage of the Ants and Vestige audit runs cuts the false-positive rate from ~97% to under 10% with no loss of real coverage. Tightened <code>memory_patterns</code>, <code>secrets_scan</code>, <code>file_perms</code>, and <code>header_guards</code> rules; dropped clazy <code>qt-keywords</code>; collapsed clang-tidy driver-error storms; added context-window suppressions to six rules; demoted tool timeouts and advisory checks to Info severity.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.30" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>Contributor-facing workflow infrastructure release. No runtime or behavior changes for end users — the binary is bit-identical to 0.6.29 modulo the version string. New files are tooling for contributors who clone the repo and work on it through Claude Code.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New <code>.claude/settings.json</code> wires a PostToolUse hook on Edit|Write that delegates to <code>packaging/hook-on-cmakelists-edit.sh</code>. The script runs <code>check-version-drift.sh</code> the moment an agent edits CMakeLists.txt and surfaces drift via systemMessage — closes the honor-system gap that allowed the 0.6.23 packaging slip.</li>
          <li>New <code>.claude/bump.json</code> recipe consumed by a user-level <code>/bump</code> skill. Lists the 6 version-bearing files with templated find/replace, plus 4 todos for content the recipe can't synthesise.</li>
          <li>New <code>packaging/hook-on-cmakelists-edit.sh</code>: small bash dispatcher; stdin is PostToolUse JSON, stdout is empty on clean state or a systemMessage on drift; always exits 0.</li>
          <li><code>.gitignore</code> narrowed <code>.claude/</code> → <code>.claude/*</code> with explicit exceptions for <code>settings.json</code> and <code>bump.json</code> so the team-shared workflow files commit while developer-local <code>settings.local.json</code> and <code>worktrees/</code> stay ignored.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.29" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>Status-bar reliability pass — nail down every user-reported symptom in one go: git branch chip "…" under tight layout, Review Changes button not appearing until a tab-switch, Add-to-Allowlist button silently no-op on save failure, Claude status label 2 s stale after tab-switch.</p>
        <ul>
          <li><code>ElidedLabel::minimumSizeHint</code> now returns the full-text width (capped at <code>maximumWidth</code>). Short text is guaranteed to render without elision regardless of layout squeeze — the statusbar's QBoxLayout previously compressed chips to a 3-char minimum and the text came out as "…" even with ample space. <code>sizeHint</code> also no longer reflects post-elision text (avoiding the chicken-and-egg loop where elision fed its own minimum).</li>
          <li>Review Changes button is now refreshed on every 2 s status-bar tick (not only tab-switch + Claude hook <code>fileChanged</code>). Dirty repos on startup show the button immediately; manual <code>git add</code> / <code>git commit</code> / external editor workflows flip the button live without needing Claude hooks.</li>
          <li><code>ClaudeIntegration::setShellPid</code> calls <code>pollClaudeProcess()</code> immediately on PID change so the status label reflects the new tab within one event-loop iteration rather than being <code>NotRunning</code> for up to 2 s until the next timer tick.</li>
          <li><code>ClaudeAllowlistDialog::saveSettings</code> now returns <code>bool</code>; all three callers (prompt-prefill, OK, Apply) surface failure to the user via status message or validation label. Previously every open/write/commit failure was swallowed and the button appeared to do nothing.</li>
          <li>Add-to-Allowlist button is now prompt-scoped in both creation paths: the hook-server button-group QWidget has <code>objectName "claudeAllowBtn"</code> matching the scroll-scan path, so <code>onTabChanged</code> cleans up both; the hook-server path's cleared-listener covers every terminal (not just <code>currentTerminal()</code>) so approving on the originating tab after a brief visit to another still clears the button.</li>
          <li><code>showDiffViewer</code> replaces every silent <code>return</code> with an explicit status message so the Review Changes button can't click through to nothing — previously a failed <code>focusedTerminal</code>, empty <code>shellCwd</code>, or non-zero git exit all disappeared without feedback. Combined <code>git diff HEAD</code> in a single invocation (covers worktree + index) rather than two.</li>
          <li>New <code>tests/features/status_bar_elision</code> feature test locks the short-text-never-elides invariant inside a real QMainWindow + QStatusBar harness; fails against pre-fix <code>ElidedLabel</code>, passes on fix.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.28" date="2026-04-16">
      <description>
        <p>End-to-end feature review — same-class overflow sweep across the status bar, title bar, and audit dialog; quake-mode toggle fix; combining-character preservation on resize; disk-write durability hardening; auto-profile regex caching.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>New <code>ElidedLabel</code> widget truncates long text with "…" to a bounded width. Applied to the three status-bar text slots (git branch, transient message, foreground process), the window title label, the Claude status label, and the audit-dialog status label — each previously grew unbounded and pushed siblings off-screen.</li>
          <li>Quake-mode toggle no longer auto-hides the window 200 ms after a show toggle. The reused <code>QPropertyAnimation</code>'s <code>finished→hide()</code> slot from a prior hide toggle was still connected on the show branch; the slot is now disconnected before every <code>start()</code> and re-attached only on the hide branch.</li>
          <li>Terminal resize preserves the per-line combining-character side table on both main and alt screens. Pre-0.6.28 every resize wiped accents, ZWJ sequences, and diacritics because the simple-copy path walked cells only. Shrink cases cleanly evict combining entries whose column falls outside the new width. New <code>tests/features/combining_on_resize</code> feature test pins the three invariants.</li>
          <li>Config and session writes now <code>fsync()</code> the temp file before atomic rename, closing the kernel-crash data-loss window on ext4 <code>data=ordered</code>.</li>
          <li>Auto-profile rule regex is cached across the 2 s poll tick instead of recompiled per-rule-per-tick, and invalid patterns are detected via <code>QRegularExpression::isValid()</code> and warned once rather than silently never matching.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.27" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Seventh release in the 0.6 UX polish pass — ncurses <code>clear</code> scrollback fix, scroll-offset clamp, tab-close visibility, Claude "prompting" state.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>ncurses <code>clear</code> now correctly wipes scrollback on <code>TERM=xterm-256color</code>. The 0.6.26 Ink-overflow-repaint heuristic was false-matching the byte-burst because <code>clear</code>'s <code>\E[H\E[2J\E[3J</code> sequence overlaps with Ink's <code>clearTerminal</code>. Disambiguated via cursor position at <code>3J</code> time — <code>clear</code> emits <code>H</code> first so the cursor sits at (0,0); Ink emits <code>H</code> last so the cursor is at the bottom.</li>
          <li>Scroll-to-bottom button no longer lingers when scrollback shrinks. <code>m_scrollOffset</code> is now re-clamped in the single <code>updateScrollBar()</code> choke-point after every output batch.</li>
          <li>Tab close (×) button is always visible — removed the stylesheet rule that hid the glyph and left only an invisible hover hit-target.</li>
          <li>Claude status bar now shows "Claude: prompting" when a permission prompt is waiting, even if the transcript-driven state still reports idle/thinking. Critical when the user is scrolled up in history and can't see the live prompt.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.26" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>UX polish pass — status bar consistency, focus handling, Ink overflow-repaint fix, and tab colour gradient.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Claude Code (Ink/React TUI) overflow-repaint no longer destroys scrollback or duplicates the replay. <code>CSI 2J</code> followed within 50 ms by <code>CSI 3J</code> on the main screen is now treated as Ink's <code>clearTerminal</code> frame-reset marker (see <code>ink/build/ink.js:705</code>) rather than a user-initiated scrollback wipe — scrollback is preserved and the suppression window is armed for the subsequent replay. Standalone <code>CSI 3J</code> (user-initiated <code>clear -x</code>) still wipes scrollback as expected. Two new feature-conformance scenarios assert both behaviours.</li>
          <li>Status bar is now height-stable. <code>QStatusBar</code>'s size hint had been tracking its tallest child, so the bar grew when the transient "Add to allowlist" button appeared and shrank when it went away. A 32 px minimum-height floor keeps the bar consistent whether or not a button is attached.</li>
          <li>"Review Changes" status-bar button now matches the sibling "Add to allowlist" button's enabled look — it inherits the global <code>QPushButton</code> style instead of its own custom stylesheet (the 0.6.26 "bold to fix Gruvbox contrast" attempt made lowercase letters squish into a small-caps look on Fusion + monospace). Disabled state gets its own visual language (dashed border, italic, muted fg) so a clean-repo state reads clearly as non-actionable.</li>
          <li>Git branch chip now has a hard vertical divider separating it from the transient-status slot, visible on low-contrast themes where the chip's rounded-background treatment was indistinguishable from the status bar background.</li>
          <li>Focus auto-returns to the active terminal whenever focus lands on chrome widgets (status bar buttons, tab bar) with no dialog open. Clicking a status bar button, answering a prompt, etc., no longer leaves the keyboard parked on the button.</li>
          <li>Claude Code context-usage progress bar is hidden until the first real (non-zero) context percentage arrives. A fresh tab, or a tab where Claude was never started, no longer paints a persistent "0%" widget.</li>
          <li>Tab-colour badge replaced with a vertical gradient (transparent top → chosen colour bottom). The active-tab 2 px accent underline is preserved by excluding the bottom two pixels from the gradient area.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.25" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>User-reported scrollback regression fix plus packaging-rule hardening.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Scrolled-up viewport no longer shifts when streaming content arrives. The 0.6.21 pause and 0.6.22/0.6.24 CSI-clear window both skipped scrollback pushes, which froze the scroll anchor and let screen-scroll mechanics bleed into the user's viewport. Fix: push to scrollback while the user is scrolled up (anchor adjusts <code>m_scrollOffset</code> to compensate); the doubling-protection window still fires for the at-bottom case where the doubling symptom is observable.</li>
          <li>Extended the <code>packaging-version-drift</code> audit rule to scan <code>org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml</code>. The file's <code>&lt;release version=&gt;</code> entry is version-coupled to every release but was not previously checked. Flagged by the ninth periodic audit (2026-04-15).</li>
          <li>Extracted the drift-check logic into <code>packaging/check-version-drift.sh</code> — a standalone script that is the single source of truth. Both <code>src/auditdialog.cpp</code> and the CI workflow invoke the same script, so they can no longer drift apart.</li>
          <li>Wired the script into <code>.github/workflows/ci.yml</code> as a gating check; a PR that bumps CMakeLists.txt without updating every packaging file now fails CI instead of merging and requiring a follow-up tag.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.24" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Status-bar button-lifecycle and legibility fixes alongside the full-clear scrollback suppression extension.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Status-bar "Add to allowlist" button now persists for the full life of the Claude Code permission prompt — previously the button was retracted on the next repaint tick, vanishing within seconds of the prompt appearing.</li>
          <li>"Review Changes" button disabled-state text now readable on every theme. Previous textSecondary-based fix still failed WCAG AA on One Dark / Kanagawa; switched to textPrimary + italic + dissolved border so the label stays legible while still communicating the disabled state.</li>
          <li>Extended the 0.6.22 suppression window to <code>CSI H; CSI 0J</code> and corner-cursor <code>CSI 1J</code> — both produce the same post-state as <code>CSI 2J</code> and therefore exhibit the same doubling bug on TUI redraw bursts. Regression tests for both shapes added to <code>tests/features/scrollback_redraw/</code>.</li>
          <li>Packaging recipes (openSUSE spec, Arch PKGBUILD, Debian changelog, man page) bumped to 0.6.24 after drifting two releases behind — the exact drift the <code>packaging-version-drift</code> audit rule was written to catch.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.23" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Three user-reported UX fixes, an event-driven status-bar contract, and the first 0.7.0 performance item — SIMD VT-parser scan.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Allowlist "already covered" check no longer blocks legitimate compound rules — subsumption now splits on shell operators (<code>&amp;&amp;</code>, <code>||</code>, <code>;</code>, <code>|</code>) and requires every segment to match before declaring coverage.</li>
          <li>Right-click tab colour picker now renders visibly — a new <code>ColoredTabBar</code> paints a 3-px strip outside stylesheet influence (was defeated by QSS specificity).</li>
          <li>Status bar clears event-scoped transients (Allow buttons, notifications) on tab switch so state from one tab never leaks into another.</li>
          <li>Fixed a Shift+Enter paste-image regression.</li>
          <li>SIMD ground-state scan (SSE2 / NEON) — bulk <code>Print</code> emission on runs of safe printable-ASCII, with byte-identical action-stream regression guards.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.22" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Root-cause fix for main-screen TUI scrollback doubling, plus packaging catch-up across all recipes.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Scrollback no longer accumulates duplicates when a main-screen TUI (Claude Code v2.1+) repaints via <code>CSI 2J</code> — a 250 ms sliding window now suppresses scrollback pushes during the repaint burst.</li>
          <li>Packaging recipes (openSUSE spec, Arch PKGBUILD, Debian changelog) bumped to 0.6.22 after drifting three releases behind.</li>
          <li>openSUSE spec gains <code>%post</code>/<code>%postun</code> scriptlets for desktop-database and icon-cache refresh.</li>
          <li>Debian gains <code>postinst</code>/<code>postrm</code> scripts for the same purpose.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.21" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Audit-tool noise reduction, dialog theming, and a scrollback-insert pause for users actively reading history while a TUI repaints.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed a GNU grep 3.12 argument-ordering quirk that silently disabled the audit's <code>--include</code> file-type filter.</li>
          <li>Extended the QSS cascade so every popup dialog inherits the terminal's active theme.</li>
          <li>Added a scrollback-insert pause that stops TUI redraws from interleaving intermediate frames into the user's reading position.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.20" date="2026-04-15">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-adoption bundle H5: OBS, AUR, and Debian packaging recipes.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.19" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H4: bash, zsh, and fish shell completions plus CMake install rules.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.18" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H3: ants-terminal(1) man page with CMake install rule.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.17" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H2: AppStream metainfo and spec-compliant desktop entry.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added <code>org.ants.Terminal.metainfo.xml</code> for GNOME Software and KDE Discover discovery.</li>
          <li>Added <code>org.ants.Terminal.desktop</code> following the reverse-DNS naming convention.</li>
          <li>CMake install rules for desktop entry, metainfo, and hicolor-theme icons at six sizes.</li>
          <li>CI validates packaging artefacts with <code>appstreamcli</code> and <code>desktop-file-validate</code>.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.16" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Distribution-readiness bundle H1: community and security policy documents.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added <code>CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md</code> (Contributor Covenant 2.1) with dedicated reporting channels.</li>
          <li>Changelogged the previously shipped <code>SECURITY.md</code> coordinated-disclosure policy.</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.15" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Incremental scrollback reflow with a fast path for standalone lines.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.14" date="2026-04-14">
      <description>
        <p>Security hardening — URI scheme allowlist in <code>addRowHyperlink</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
